ROUND 5 TOSS-UP1) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Colloids formed by the dispersal of a gas in a liquid are called:W) emulsions X) foamsY) aerosols Z) solid solsANSWER: X) FOAMSBONUS1) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice If a substance has a molecular weight of 88, which of the following will it be:W) KCl X) C4H8O2 Y) RbFZ) C6H14ANSWER: X) C4H8O2 TOSS-UP2) PHYSICS Short Answer What color of light is produced when equal intensities of cyan light and red light are combined?ANSWER: WHITE(Solution: adding a primary color to the proper secondary color (called complementary colors) will give white light; complementary color pairs are one primary color and one secondary color, e.g. blue and yellow, red and cyan, or green and magenta.)BONUS2) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the resistance, in ohms, for an electric stove that draws 24 amps on a 240-volt circuit?ANSWER: 10(Solution: I = V/R; R = V/I; R = 240/24 = 10 ohms)2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 1TOSS-UP3) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the most common term for the specific type of cartilage that forms the disks between human vertebrae?ANSWER: FIBROCARTILAGEBONUS3) BIOLOGY Short Answer Name all of the following 4 choices that are considered part of the connective tissue: blood; adipocytes (read as: ADD-ih-poe-sites); muscles; nervesANSWER: BLOOD; ADIPOCYTESTOSS-UP4) MATH Short Answer What are the lengths, in centimeters, of the hypotenuse and the longer leg, respectively, of a 30-60-90 degree right triangle if the shorter leg is 12 centimeters long?ANSWER: HYPOTENUSE = 24; LONGER LEG = 12 3 (ACCEPT: LONGER LEG = 20 – 21) BONUS4) MATH Short Answer Giving your answer in terms of pi, what is the area of a circle whose circumference is 20?ANSWER: 100 π(Solution: C = πd; A = πr2 = π(10/π)2 = 100/π)    2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 2TOSS-UP5) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:W) Los Angeles is moving towards San Diego at a current rate of 2 to 3 meters per year X) the source of all igneous rocks is molten magmaY) silicates are the most abundant group of minerals in Earth’s crust and mantleZ) oceanic crust is generally thinner than continental crustANSWER: W) LOS ANGELES IS MOVING TOWARDS SAN DIEGO AT A CURRENT RATE OF 2 TO 3 METERS PER YEARBONUS5) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Order the following 4 Earth materials in order of INCREASING specific heat capacity: solid water; liquid water; granite; leadANSWER: LEAD; GRANITE; SOLID WATER; LIQUID WATER(Solution: lead = 0.03; granite = 0.2; solid water = 0.5; liquid water = 1.0 cal/goC)TOSS-UP6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following BEST describes the size of the average amoeba: W) 1 angstromX) 2 micrometers Y) 600 micrometers Z) 1 centimeterANSWER: Y) 600 MICROMETERSBONUS6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Rounded to the nearest whole number, convert 283K into degrees Fahrenheit:ANSWER: 50(Solution: 283 – 273 = 10oC; 10 × 1.8 + 32 = 50oF)2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 3TOSS-UP7) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the MOST common term for a galaxy that is emitting a large amount of radiation from a black hole at its center:W) bright galaxy X) luminous galaxy Y) active galaxyZ) event galaxyANSWER: Y) ACTIVE GALAXYBONUS7) ASTRONOMY Multiple choice Stars in the spectral class A would have a surface temperature of about: W) 5,000 K X) 10,000 K Y) 15,000 K Z) 20,000 KANSWER: X) 10,000 K TOSS-UP8) CHEMISTRY Short Answer How many nodes are in an ‘s’ orbital? ANSWER: NONE (ACCEPT: ZERO)BONUS8) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of glucose:W) when glucose joins with galactose, fructose is formed X) it is also called dextroseY) cellulose is a polymer of glucose moleculesZ) its formula is C6H12O6ANSWER: W) WHEN GLUCOSE JOINS WITH GALACTOSE, FRUCTOSE IS FORMED2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 4TOSS-UP9) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following colors of light would give the highest resolving power of a compound light microscope:W) infrared X) orange Y) greenZ) ultravioletANSWER: Z) ULTRAVIOLETBONUS9) PHYSICS Short Answer If Jim expends 200 watts of power to vertically lift a 200-newton rock 3 meters high, how many seconds did it take him to lift the boulder?ANSWER: 3(Solution: power = work/time = force × distance/s 200W = 200N × 3/x; x = 3s)TOSS-UP10) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Blood albumin is most directly involved with: W) osmoregulationX) hormone regulation Y) bile productionZ) acid base regulationANSWER: W) OSMOREGULATION10) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true in humans:W) trisomy X originates from a nondisjunction X) all enzymes are proteinsY) albumin is produced by the liverZ) the spleen produces red blood cells in the fetusANSWER: X) ALL ENZYMES ARE PROTEINSBONUS2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 5TOSS-UP11) MATH Short Answer Solve the following radical equation for x, when x is a real number: 5 x+1=2ANSWER: 31BONUS11) MATH Short Answer What is the greatest common factor for the numbers 63 and 273? ANSWER: 21TOSS-UP12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice An oligotrophic (read as: oh-lig-oh-TROW-fick) lake is one that is BEST defined as:W) deep, cold, and nutrient-poorX) deep, cold, and nutrient-richY) shallow, warm, and nutrient-poor Z) shallow, warm, and nutrient-richANSWER: W) DEEP, COLD, AND NUTRIENT-POORBONUS12) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer According to the Atterberg and U.S. Department of Agriculture classification scales, what type of soil particles have diameters of less than 0.002 millimeters and are considered the smallest particles of soil?ANSWER: CLAY  2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 6TOSS-UP13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Which of the following 5 sources accounts for the largest share of energy used in the U.S.: coal; petroleum products; nuclear energy; renewable energy; natural gasANSWER: PETROLEUM PRODUCTSBONUS13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer In 2004, 19.7 million barrels of petroleum products were used each day in the U.S. Rounded to the nearest gallon, how much does this represent per person per day?ANSWER: 3(Solution: (42 gal × 19.7)/300 million people = 3 gals)TOSS-UP14) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following is LEAST accurate:W) at the equator, stars appear to rise and set vertically X) all Mira stars are Red GiantsY) right ascension is analogous to longitudeZ) the Earth is closest to the Sun during DecemberANSWER: Z) THE EARTH IS CLOSEST TO THE SUN DURING DECEMBERBONUS14) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the MOST commonly accepted reason as to why the planet Uranus rotates on its side:W) it oscillates in its rotation orientation over thousands of yearsX) it captured four of its moons early in its development which radically affected its primordial disk rotationY) it was once struck by a massive objectZ) because of its orbital position and low density it was susceptible to a wide variety of axial rotational possibilitiesANSWER: Y) IT WAS ONCE STRUCK BY A MASSIVE OBJECT 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 7TOSS-UP15) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following statements regarding geometric or cis-trans isomers is NOT true:W) they have the same molecular formulaX) they have the same order of attachment of atomsY) they have the same orientation around a double bond Z) they have the same functional groupsANSWER: Y) THEY HAVE THE SAME ORIENTATION AROUND A DOUBLE BONDBONUS15) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the formal charge of nitrogen in the ammonia, or NH3, molecule?ANSWER: 0TOSS-UP16) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a composite material: W) boneX) plywood Y) woodZ) mild steelANSWER: Z) MILD STEELBONUS16) PHYSICS Short Answer If a 5,000-pound elephant is on one end of a plank at a distance of 5 feet from the pivot point and a 200-pound man is on the other end at a distance of 15 feet from the pivot, what will the available torque be, in foot-pounds, at the pivot while the plank is in motion?ANSWER: 22,000(Solution: (5000 lbs × 5ft) – (200 lbs × 15 ft) = 25,000 – 3000 = 22,000 ft lbs)2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 8TOSS-UP17) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following human cell types is MOST directly responsible for the secretion of antibodies:W) monocytesX) CD4+ cellsY) T activator lymphocytes Z) B cellsANSWER: Z) B CELLSBONUS17) BIOLOGY Short Answer What specific ion is most central to muscle contraction in striated human muscle?ANSWER: CALCIUM (ACCEPT: CALCIUM 2+ or Ca2+)TOSS-UP18) MATH Short Answer Give the value of c that completes the square of the following expression: x2 + 52 x + cANSWER: 1 (ACCEPT: 0.04 or 4 ) 25 100BONUS18) MATH Short Answer Reduce the following radical expression to its simplest radical form: 2 3 225 (read as: the square root of the cube root of 225)ANSWER: 3 15      2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 9TOSS-UP19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The Coriolis effect causes northward flowing air currents in the Northern hemisphere to veer off course:W) in the direction of rotationX) in the direction opposite to rotation Y) to the leftZ) at a 90o angleANSWER: W) IN THE DIRECTION OF ROTATIONBONUS19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following are the most important and abundant rock-forming minerals:W) carbonates X) silicatesY) iron sulfides Z) sulfatesANSWER: X) SILICATES TOSS-UP20) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the most common and accurate term for when a person’s immune system generates antibodies against its own body’s cells:W) autoimmune dysfunction X) homeostatic inflammation Y) heteroimmune reactionZ) anaphylactic reactionANSWER: W) AUTOIMMUNE DYSFUNCTIONBONUS20) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the BEST description of atherosclerosis:W) inflammation of the brain cortical tissuesX) paralysis of extremities and loss of sensationY) walls of blood vessels become thicker and less elastic Z) loss of ability to hear certain soundsANSWER: Y) WALLS OF BLOOD VESSELS BECOME THICKER AND LESS ELASTIC 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 10TOSS-UP21) ASTRONOMY Multiple choice A star is found to have a surface temperature of 20,000 kelvin. Which of the following spectral types is it most likely to be:W) A X) F Y) G Z) OANSWER: Z) OBONUS21) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What is the astronomical term for a planet’s orbital point that is closest to the Sun?ANSWER: PERIHELIONTOSS-UP22) CHEMISTRY Short Answer C6H6 is the molecular formula for what aromatic hydrocarbon? ANSWER: BENZENEBONUS22) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Consider a mixture of nitrogen and oxygen gases that has a total pressure of 0.63 atmospheres. If the partial pressure of nitrogen is 0.32 atmospheres, what is the partial pressure of oxygen in the mixture, in atmospheres to the second decimal place?ANSWER: 0.31 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 11TOSS-UP23) PHYSICS Multiple Choice In an application where ductility is required, which of the following materials would be your BEST choice:W) grey cast iron X) copperY) graniteZ) 1040 steelANSWER: X) COPPERBONUS23) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT correct:W) percent elongation compared to the known value for a material is sometimes used to detect impurities in metalX) the modulus of elasticity for a material is derived from its stress-strain curveY) ductile materials usually fail with little or no plastic deformationZ) a steel sample that is loaded beyond its elastic limit will not return to its original shape when the load is removedANSWER: Y) DUCTILE MATERIALS USUALLY FAIL WITH LITTLE OR NO PLASTIC DEFORMA TIONTOSS-UP24) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the botanical term for the stem of a group of flowers? ANSWER: PEDUNCLEBONUS24) BIOLOGY Short Answer In mammals, the action potential of a neuron is most dependent on the transmembrane movement of what 2 ions?ANSWER: SODIUM AND POTASSIUM (ACCEPT: Na+ and K+) 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 12TOSS-UP25) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following have largely replaced vacuum tubes that were used in electronics of the mid to later 20th century:W) capacitors X) transformers Y) transistors Z) amplifiersANSWER: Y) TRANSISTORS25) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of uranium:W) it is very denseX) all isotopes are radioactiveY) uranium is sometimes used in counterweights in yacht keels Z) there are only 3 isotopes of uraniumANSWER: Z) THERE ARE ONLY 3 ISOTOPES OF URANIUMBONUS2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 13