ROUND 6 TOSS-UP1) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the resulting electrical potential, in volts, when a charge of 12 coulombs is applied to a 1 farad capacitor?ANSWER: 12BONUS1) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:W) the magnetic field associated with the current on a straight long wire is inversely proportional to the distance from the wireX) Kirchhoff’s first rule has to do with the accounting of total charges entering and leaving a junction per unit timeY) superconducting quantum interference devices, or SQUID’s, are based on the Josephson Effect Z) resistance and voltage are the two most common parameters used to characterize a resistorANSWER: Z) RESISTANCE AND VOLTAGE ARE THE TWO MOST COMMON PARAMETERS USED TO CHARACTERIZE A RESISTORTOSS-UP2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a colligative property: W) vapor pressure lowering X) osmotic pressureY) boiling point elevation Z) color of solutionANSWER: Z) COLOR OF SOLUTIONBONUS2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is a type of colloid that is classified as a sol at room temperature:W) gelatinX) milkY) whipped cream Z) marshmallowANSWER: W) GELATIN(Solution: sol is a solid dispersed in a liquid)2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 1
TOSS-UP3) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following tissues is MOST directly responsible for the increased diameter of a tree trunk from year to year:W) apical meristem X) pericycleY) vascular cambium Z) pithANSWER: Y) VASCULAR CAMBIUMBONUS3) BIOLOGY Short Answer Name all of the following 3 metabolic processes which directly require oxygen: glycolysis; alcohol fermentation; electron transport systemANSWER: ELECTRON TRANSPORT SYSTEMTOSS-UP4) MATH Short Answer Convert log base 4 of 53 into a base 10 expression: ANSWER: log 53 (ACCEPT: log10 53 )BONUS4) MATH Short Answer Consider a 6-sided irregular polygon whose perimeter is 100 centimeters. If 4 of the sides have a length of 7 centimeters each, what is the length, in centimeters, of each of the remaining two sides if they are congruent?ANSWER: 36(Solution: 100 – 28 = 72; 72/2 = 36cm)   log4 log10 42007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 2
TOSS-UP5) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a man-made coastal structure that causes coastal erosion by blocking oceanic longshore drift:W) jettyX) barrier island Y) atollZ) fringing reefANSWER: W) JETTYBONUS5) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Used as a way to categorize rivers and streams, what is the term for the volume of water flowing through the cross-section of a channel over a given period of time?ANSWER: DISCHARGE (ACCEPT: DISCHARGE RATE)TOSS-UP6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Case hardening is a process through which:W) the surface of a metal is hardenedX) the metal is hardened completely through Y) the hardness of a metal is determinedZ) metals are shaped or formedANSWER: W) THE SURFACE OF A METAL IS HARDENEDBONUS6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The oil used with an oil-immersion objective in compound light microscopes takes advantage of what optical phenomenon to improve magnification:W) chromatic coherence X) index of refraction Y) polarizationZ) dispersionANSWER: X) INDEX OF REFRACTION 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 3
TOSS-UP7) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:W) the rotation of the Sun’s surface is faster at the equator than at the polesX) the apparent magnitude of an RR Lyrae depends most on its distance from the Earth Y) Venus appears its largest to nighttime observers when it is in its full phaseZ) a star’s light curve typically plots brightness verses timeANSWER: Y) VENUS APPEARS ITS LARGEST TO NIGHTTIME OBSERVERS WHEN IT IS IN ITS FULL PHASEBONUS7) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following techniques would you most directly be using if you were analyzing a Balmer and Lyman series:W) astrolabe measurements X) spectroscopyY) nuclear fissionZ) bolometric analysisANSWER: X) SPECTROSCOPY TOSS-UP8) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following is the strongest spectral line in the visible region of the hydrogen spectrum:W) red Balmer line X) orange Lyman line Y) green Paschen line Z) blue Brackett lineANSWER: W) RED BALMER LINEBONUS8) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following has the highest vapor pressure at standard temperature and pressure:W) mercuryX) ethyl alcohol Y) methyl alcohol Z) acetoneANSWER: Z) ACETONE2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 4
TOSS-UP9) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice According to the Arrhenius theory, an Arrhenius acid is any substance that does which of the following in a chemical reaction:W) donates a pair of electronsX) accepts a pair of electronsY) produces H+ ions in aqueous solution Z) produces OH– ions in aqueous solutionANSWER: Y) PRODUCES H+ IONS IN AQUEOUS SOLUTIONBONUS9) CHEMISTRY Short Answer If you were to evaporate 1 liter or kilogram of water, how many calories of latent heat are stored in the vapor?ANSWER: 540,000 (ACCEPT: 5.4 × 105) (Solution: lat heatvap = 540cal/g)TOSS-UP10) BIOLOGY Short Answer During meiosis, how many chromatids are in a chromosomal tetrad? ANSWER: 4BONUS10) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of nucleated mammalian cells:W) mast cells contain large amounts of histamineX) the golgi apparatus processes proteins for exocytosis Y) microtubules are components in ciliaZ) all the DNA in a nucleated cell is in the nucleusANSWER: Z) ALL THE DNA IN A HUMAN NUCLEATED CELL IS IN THE NUCLEUS (Solution: mitochondrial DNA is present) 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 5
TOSS-UP11) MATH Short Answer Solve the following equation for x: x2 – 20x + 19 = 0ANSWER: 19 AND 1BONUS11) MATH Short Answer Express the following radical in its simplest radical form: !2 (80a2b4c3)ANSWER: ! 8ab2c 5cTOSS-UP12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true about Earth’s history:W) the Ordovician Period predates the Silurian Period X) we currently live in the Cenozoic EraY) we currently live in the Pleistocene EpochZ) the Holocene Epoch began about 10,000 years agoANSWER: Y) WE CURRENTLY LIVE IN THE PLEISTOCENE EPOCHBONUS12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the global wind system that most influences weather in the U.S.:W) prevailing westerlies X) tropical easterliesY) trade windsZ) polar easterliesANSWER: W) PREVAILING WESTERLIES   2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 6
TOSS-UP13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer One metric ton equals how many grams? ANSWER: ONE MILLION (ACCEPT: 1 × 106 or 106)BONUS13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Gout in humans is the result of the precipitation of what substance in joints?ANSWER: URIC ACID (ACCEPT: LITHIC ACID or TRIKETOPURINE)TOSS-UP14) ASTRONOMY Short Answer With reference to the Sun’s position in the sky, when does a full Moon set?ANSWER: WHEN THE SUN RISESBONUS14) ASTRONOMY Short Answer In a Newtonian telescope, how many degrees is the secondary mirror tilted in reference to the primary?ANSWER: 45 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 7
TOSS-UP15) PHYSICS Multiple Choice If 1000 pounds is applied to a spring with spring constant of 100 pounds per inch on top of a hydraulic piston, how many pounds of force is transferred to the piston:W) 1,000 X) 900 Y) 100 Z) zeroANSWER: W) 1,000BONUS15) PHYSICS Multiple Choice If the atomic mass of carbon-12 is exactly 12 atomic mass units, why is the atomic mass of carbon not exactly 12 when listed on the Periodic Table:W) the mass deficitX) neutrons are not the same mass as protonsY) it adds the mass of the electronsZ) the presence in nature of about 1.1% carbon-13ANSWER: Z) THE PRESENCE IN NATURE OF ABOUT 1.1% CARBON-13TOSS-UP16) CHEMISTRY Short Answer How many carbon and hydrogen atoms are in a cyclopentane molecule?ANSWER: CARBON = 5; HYDROGEN = 10BONUS16) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the systematic IUPAC name for the following acid: HClOANSWER: HYPOCHLOROUS ACID 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 8
TOSS-UP17) BIOLOGY Short Answer What specific part of any member of the Anthophyta produces pollen?ANSWER: STAMEN (ACCEPT: ANTHER)BONUS17) BIOLOGY Short Answer Which one of the following 4 plant groups is phenotypically and phylogenetically LEAST related to the others: ferns; liverworts; hornworts; mossesANSWER: FERNSTOSS-UP18) MATH Short Answer Subtract the following complex numbers, giving your answer in standard form: (11 – 4i) – (–3 + 3i)ANSWER: 14 – 7iBONUS18) MATH Short Answer Solve the following inequality for x, giving your answer in fractional form: 13x+23<56x!2ANSWER: x> 16 (ACCEPT: x> 51) 33      2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 9
TOSS-UP19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The time interval between the generation of P and S waves from its arrival at a seismometer is BEST translated as:W) the magnitude of the earthquakeX) the distance to the epicenterY) the wave height of a potential tsunami Z) the distance to the nearest fault zoneANSWER: X) THE DISTANCE TO THE EPICENTERBONUS19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:W) sea levels dropped during the Pleistocene glaciation making the Bering Strait a land bridgeX) large animals such as the mastodon and dire wolves became extinct at the end of the Pleistocene Y) the Holocene may be an interglacial stageZ) recent ice ages are thought to be controlled by uniformitarian cyclesANSWER: Z) RECENT ICE AGES ARE THOUGHT TO BE CONTROLLED BY UNIFORMITARIAN CYCLESTOSS-UP20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What substance made of several fibrous materials was widely used in the 20th century for its heat resistant properties but is now banned because it can cause lung cancer when inhaled?ANSWER: ASBESTOSBONUS20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the medical term for the type of lung cancer specifically associated with asbestosis?ANSWER: MESOTHELIOMA 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 10
TOSS-UP21) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What planet is never more than 28o from the Sun in the evening sky?ANSWER: MERCURYBONUS21) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice At 8:00 AM in early August of 2006 in New York, the Moon could be seen low in the western sky. What phase was it most likely in:W) waxing crescent X) just past newY) a few days past full Z) first quarterANSWER: Y) A FEW DAYS PAST FULLTOSS-UP22) PHYSICS Short Answer How many nodes are there in the first overtone in a standing wave of a vibrating guitar string?ANSWER: 3BONUS22) PHYSICS Short Answer If g = 9.8 meters per second squared, to the first decimal place and in newtons, how many newtons of force are required to keep a 500 kilogram slab of granite moving across a horizontal surface at constant speed if there is a kinetic frictional coefficient of 0.10 between the surface and the slab?ANSWER: 490(Solution: 0.1 × 500kg × 9.8m/s2 = 490N) 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 11
TOSS-UP23) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Organic compounds that contain double bonds are said to be:W) saturatedX) unsaturatedY) unable to undergo cis-trans isomerization Z) unable to undergo addition reactionsANSWER: X) UNSATURATEDBONUS23) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Arrange the following 4 elements in order of increasing atomic radii: lithium; oxygen; potassium; sodiumANSWER: OXYGEN; LITHIUM; SODIUM; POTASSIUMTOSS-UP24) BIOLOGY Short Answer Which one of the following 4 animal groups is LEAST closely related to the others: brachiopods; gastropods; cephalopods; bivalvesANSWER: BRACHIOPODSBONUS24) BIOLOGY Short Answer From the OUTSIDE to the INSIDE, name the 3 embryonic germ layers in mammals:ANSWER: ECTODERM; MESODERM; ENDODERM 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 12
TOSS-UP25) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:W) actinides are characterized by occupying the f-block of the periodic table X) lanthanides are characterized by occupying the d-block of the periodic table Y) alkali metals are the most reactive of all metallic elementsZ) actinides are metalsANSWER: X) LANTHANIDES ARE CHARACTERIZED BY OCCUPYING THE D-BLOCK OF THE PERIODIC TABLEBONUS25) CHEMISTRY Short Answer In standard chemical nomenclature, what is the complete electron configuration for the sodium ion, Na+?ANSWER: 1s22s22p6 (ACCEPT: 1s22s22p63s0)2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 13