ROUND 12 TOSS-UP1) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Often some of the strongest spectral lines in cold interstellar gas are produced by:W) neutral lithiumX) ionized ironY) carbon and ironZ) calcium and sodiumANSWER: Z) CALCIUM AND SODIUMBONUS1) PHYSICS Short Answer The cosmic background radiation discovered by Penzias and Wilson closely matches the radiation from a black body with what temperature Kelvin, to the nearest whole number?ANSWER: 3TOSS-UP2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following salt solutions, all at 1.0 molar concentration, will have a pH value less than 7: W) NH4ClX) NaC2H3O2 Y) KClZ) LiBrANSWER: W) NH4Cl2) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Name all of the following 4 compounds that exhibit hydrogen bonding: CH4; H2S; NH3; CH3OHANSWER: NH3; CH3OHBONUS2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 1
TOSS-UP3) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In early experiments in the mid-1900’s, the source and fate of oxygen involved in photosynthesis was mostly determined through experiments that used:W) animals in closed containers that would die unless a plant was introduced into the container X) a heavy isotope of oxygen as a tracerY) fluorescent labeling of various enzymes and organic productsZ) simple accounting of the atomic mass of all the reactants and productsANSWER: X) A HEAVY ISOTOPE OF OXYGEN AS A TRACERBONUS3) BIOLOGY Short Answer By number or name, identify all of the following 4 processes that contribute directly to genetic variation in humans: 1) random fertilization of ova with sperm; 2) crossing over; 3) independent assortment; 4) mitosisANSWER: 1, 2 AND 3 (ACCEPT: ALL BUT #4)TOSS-UP4) MATH Short Answer If you roll 2 fair dice simultaneously, what is the probability, given as a fraction, that you will roll the number 6 on AT LEAST one die?ANSWER: 11/36BONUS4) MATH Short Answer Find the sum of all interior angles, in degrees, in a regular polygon having 14 sides:ANSWER: 2,160(Solution: (14 – 2)(180) = 2,160o) 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 2
TOSS-UP5) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the BEST example of a non-point source pollution:W) leaching from a landfillX) a leaking septic tankY) fertilizer runoff from agricultural fields Z) chemical spills at a mining siteANSWER: Y) FERTILIZER RUNOFF FROM AGRICULTURAL FIELDSBONUS5) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Arrange the following 4 layers of the Earth’s atmosphere in order of INCREASING air pressure: stratosphere; exosphere; thermosphere; troposphereANSWER: EXOSPHERE; THERMOSPHERE; STRATOSPHERE; TROPOSPHERETOSS-UP6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Some vitamin tablets contain high concentrations of zinc and must be formulated to include high levels of which of the following minerals in order to prevent an induced anemia: W) copperX) calciumY) magnesium Z) boronANSWER: W) COPPERBONUS6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common name for the technique that places a molecule in a strong magnetic field, irradiates the molecule with radio waves, and finally detects changes in the spin of atoms in the molecule?ANSWER: NUCLEAR MAGNETIC RESONANCE (ACCEPT: NMR or MAGNETIC RESONANCE SPECTROSCOPY)2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 3
TOSS-UP7) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Landform deposits called linear dunes that were recently found on the moon Titan are MOST directly produced by:W) tectonic activityX) windY) erosion by the retreat and advance of large seas of liquid methane Z) streaks in the surface following low-angle meteorite impactsANSWER: X) WINDBONUS7) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What is the magnifying power of the telescope with a focal length of 5 meters and an eyepiece of 20 millimeters?ANSWER: 250 (ACCEPT: 250X or 250 TIMES) (Solution: 5000mm/20mm = 250)TOSS-UP8) PHYSICS Multiple Choice The process in which an atom reradiates a photon after interacting with an incident photon of the same energy is called:W) Rayleigh scattering X) the Cherenkov effect Y) Bragg’s LawZ) Thomson scatteringANSWER: Z) THOMSON SCATTERINGBONUS8) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A protanomalous person has decreased sensitivity of the red cones in his or her eyes. Which of the following color pairs will this person have difficulty distinguishing between:W) red and greenX) blue and purpleY) yellow and turquoiseZ) dark navy blue and blackANSWER: X) BLUE AND PURPLE 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 4
TOSS-UP9) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is typically TRUE of organic compounds:W) acetylene contains delocalized pi bondsX) the simplest carboxylic acid is ethanoic acidY) ketones have no hydrogen atoms directly attached to the carbonyl group Z) alcohols contain nonpolar hydroxyl groupsANSWER: Y) KETONES HAVE NO HYDROGEN ATOMS DIRECTLY ATTACHED TO THE CARBONYL GROUPBONUS9) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Rounded to the nearest whole number, what is the percent of magnesium in magnesium carbonate, given the atomic mass of magnesium is 24 grams per mole?ANSWER: 29(Solution: MgCO3 = 24 + 12 + (3 × 16) = 84; 24/84 = 28.57%)TOSS-UP10) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In the famous experiment by Hershey and Chase that showed DNA was the genetic material, what did they use to transmit the DNA into E. coli: W) other E. coli X) electric shocks Y) a blenderZ) bacteriophageANSWER: Z) BACTERIOPHAGEBONUS10) BIOLOGY Short Answer In the Amanita mushroom, what is the name of the cell in which karyogamy and meiosis occur and what is the product of meiosis, respectively?ANSWER: CELL = BASIDIUM; PRODUCT = BASIDIOSPORE2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 5
TOSS-UP11) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following are coterminal angles in standard position (read slowly):W) 550o and 185o X) 80° and –190° Y) 1160° and 800° Z) 181° and –118°ANSWER: Y) 1160° AND 800°(Solution: 80 +3(360o) = 1160o; 80 +2(360o) = 800o)BONUS11) MATH Short Answer Solve the following equation for x, expressing your answer in simplest radical form over the real numbers: x4 – 9x2 + 8 = 0ANSWER: ±2 2 AND ±1 (ACCEPT ALL: +2 2, −2 2, +1, -1) TOSS-UP12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the BEST example of an ocean current found in the intertidal littoral zone that flows seaward:    W) rip currentX) tidal boreY) the Antarctic Circumpolar Current Z) equatorial tidal currentANSWER: W) RIP CURRENTBONUS12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of isotherms:W) they are more widely spaced over the equatorial regionsX) they are more closely spaced over North America in the summer than in the winter Y) they tend to be linear in form in the Southern Hemisphere south of 40o latitudeZ) they are lines that connect places with the same average temperatureANSWER: X) THEY ARE MORE CLOSELY SPACED OVER NORTH AMERICA IN THE SUMMER THAN IN THE WINTER2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 6
TOSS-UP13) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following instruments is BEST used to image small, transparent and fluorescent specimens and obtain optical sections without the need for mechanical sectioning:W) X-ray microanalyzerX) scanning electron microscopeY) transmission electron microscope Z) confocal laser scanning microscopeANSWER: Z) CONFOCAL LASER SCANNING MICROSCOPEBONUS13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer A relatively new scourge to the citrus growers in Florida, what is the common name of the citrus disease caused by a species of bacteria called C. liberibacter and spread by an introduced non-native insect?ANSWER: GREENING (ACCEPT: CITRUS GREENING)TOSS-UP14) ASTRONOMY Short Answer A sidereal drive is a motor on a telescope that turns it in a certain direction to keep the telescope aimed at a certain celestial object. Giving your answer as north, south, east or west, in what direction does it turn?ANSWER: WESTBONUS14) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice The Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe was specifically designed to:W) map all matter in the universe down to a resolution of 1 arc secondX) map the cosmic background radiation to much greater accuracy and precision than previous instrumentsY) map the size and locations of the Local GroupZ) map the exact location of the active galactic center of the Milky WayANSWER: X) MAP THE COSMIC BACKGROUND RADIATION TO MUCH GREATER ACCURACY AND PRECISION THAN PREVIOUS INSTRUMENTS 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 7
TOSS-UP15) PHYSICS Multiple Choice In a compound gearing arrangement where a 40-tooth gear drives an 80-tooth gear which is directly connected to a 50-tooth gear that drives a 100-tooth gear, the total reduction is a factor of:W) 2 X) 2.5 Y) 4 Z) 5ANSWER: Y) 4BONUS15) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Elastic deformation is BEST described as:W) the linear portion of a stress/strain curve X) the ultimate strength of a materialY) 0.02% elongationZ) permanent deformationANSWER: W) THE LINEAR PORTION OF A STRESS/STRAIN CURVETOSS-UP16) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following elements has the largest second ionization energy:W) fluorine X) nitrogen Y) boron Z) lithiumANSWER: Z) LITHIUM(Solution: core electrons must be removed)BONUS16) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Arrange the following compounds in order of INCREASING ionic characteristic: HCl; LiBr; CO; KFANSWER: CO; HCl; LiBr; KF 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 8
TOSS-UP17) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following are MOST often used to introduce foreign genes into mammalian genomes:W) sliceosomes (read as: sly-see-oh-somz) X) zinc fingersY) plasmidsZ) telomeresANSWER: Y) PLASMIDSBONUS17) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following regulate development in animals, plants and fungi, and were first discovered in Drosophila:W) homeobox (read as: HOME-ee-oh-box) genes X) p53Y) shock genesZ) oncogenesANSWER: W) HOMEOBOX GENESTOSS-UP18) MATH Short Answer What function is the inverse of y = 3x + 4? ANSWER: y= x−43BONUS18) MATH Short Answer Giving your answer as an ordered pair, find the solution of the system of the following 2 equations: 2x + 3y = 8, and 3x – 2y = –1ANSWER: (1, 2) (ACCEPT: 1 AND 2)  2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 9
TOSS-UP19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Orthoclase feldspar primarily weathers by which of the following processes to form clay minerals:W) abrasion X) hydrolysis Y) exfoliation Z) dissolutionANSWER: X) HYDROLYSISBONUS19) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the sedimentary rock that carries high concentrations of organic material in the form of kerogen, which can yield oil when heated and distilled?ANSWER: OIL SHALE (ACCEPT: SHALE)TOSS-UP20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 reagents that would NOT be labeled as a highly flammable substance:methanol; diethyl ether; 30% hydrogen peroxide; benzeneANSWER: 30% HYDROGEN PEROXIDEBONUS20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What engineering term is MOST commonly used to describe why a shaft with a radius at a transition in diameter is stronger than the same shaft with an abrupt transition in diameter?ANSWER: STRESS CONCENTRATION (ACCEPT: STRESS CONCENTRATION AT THE CHANGE IN DIAMETER) (DO NOT ACCEPT: STRESS) 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 10
TOSS-UP21) ASTRONOMY Short Answer If the surface temperature of a given star increased from 20,000K to 60,000K, how many times as much energy would the star release?ANSWER: 81 (ACCEPT: 34)BONUS21) ASTRONOMY Short Answer Name all of the following 4 celestial objects that, when viewed from the Earth, CANNOT be in opposition: Moon; Mercury; Mars; NeptuneANSWER: MERCURYTOSS-UP22) PHYSICS Short Answer What specific type of semiconductor is produced by adding phosphorus to silicon?ANSWER: N-TYPEBONUS22) PHYSICS Short Answer How many turns are in the secondary coil of a transformer that has a primary coil with 20,000 turns and is designed to step down 12,000 volts AC to 120 volts AC?ANSWER: 200(Solution: 12,000/120 = 20,000/x; x = 200) 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 11
TOSS-UP23) CHEMISTRY Short Answer The hybridization of one ‘s’ (read as: one <pause> s) orbital and 3 ‘p’ (read as: three <pause> p) orbitals and one ‘d’ (read as: one <pause> d) orbital creates how many sp3d hybrid orbitals?ANSWER: 5BONUS23) CHEMISTRY Short Answer A solution contains 0.50 moles of methanol in 100 grams of water. What is the mole fraction of methanol, to the second decimal place?ANSWER: 0.08 (DO NOT ACCEPT 8.0%)(Solution: 100g/18 g mol-1 = 5.56 moles; 0.5 mol/(5.56 + 0.5) = 0.0825)TOSS-UP24) BIOLOGY Short Answer Black water fever is a complication of malarial infection. The term black water comes from what oxidized product in the urine of infected individuals?ANSWER: HEMOGLOBIN (ACCEPT: MET-HEMOGLOBIN)BONUS24) BIOLOGY Short Answer Name all of the following 4 human blood cells that are considered lymphocytes: helper T cells; CD8 cells; CD4 cells; plasma cellsANSWER: HELPER T CELLS; CD8 CELLS; CD4 CELLS; PLASMA CELLS (ACCEPT: ALL) 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 12
TOSS-UP25) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Calculate the atom percent composition, rounded to the nearest whole number, for each atom in acetic acid:ANSWER: C = 25%; H = 50%; O = 25%BONUS25) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Calculate the mass percent composition, rounded to the nearest whole number, for each atom in acetic acid:ANSWER: C = 40%; H = 7%; O = 53%(Solution: C= 24/60 × 100% = 40%; H= 4/60 × 100% = 6.7%; O= 32/60 × 100% = 53.3%)2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 13