ROUND 1 TOSS-UP1) BIOLOGY Short Answer Rough endoplasmic reticulum is named rough because it possesses what cellular structures?ANSWER: RIBOSOMESBONUS1) BIOLOGY Short Answer In humans, backflow of blood from ventricles into atria during contraction is prevented primarily by what structures?ANSWER: VALVESTOSS-UP2) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What are the names for positive and negative ions, respectively? ANSWER: POSITIVE = CATIONS; NEGATIVE = ANIONSBONUS2) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Arrange the following 4 substances in order of increasing pH: orange juice; human gastric juice; blood; aqueous ammoniaANSWER: HUMAN GASTRIC JUICE; ORANGE JUICE; BLOOD; AQUEOUS AMMONIA 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 1
TOSS-UP3) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the scientific term for a change in velocity per unit time? ANSWER: ACCELERATIONBONUS3) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the most common term in physics for the product of mass times velocity?ANSWER: MOMENTUMTOSS-UP4) MATH Short Answer What is the 5th term in the geometric progression whose first three terms are: 64, 16, 4ANSWER: 1/4 (ACCEPT: 0.25)BONUS4) MATH Short Answer Giving your answer in centimeters to the first decimal place, if one leg of an isosceles right triangle is 100 centimeters long, how long is the hypotenuse?ANSWER: 141.4(Solution: c = a 2 = 100 2 - 141.4cm)   2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 2
TOSS-UP5) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer As a percentage by volume in Earth’s atmosphere, what are the two most abundant gases in Earth’s atmosphere?ANSWER: NITROGEN AND OXYGEN (in any order)BONUS5) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What type of glacier flows outward from a center as opposed to down a mountain valley?ANSWER: CONTINENTALTOSS-UP6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice One kilogram is nearly equivalent to how many pounds: W) 454 X) 4.54 Y) 220 Z) 2.2ANSWER: Z) 2.2BONUS6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following reagents would be labeled as highly flammable because of its low flash point:W) glycerolX) methanolY) carbon tetrachloride Z) sulfuric acidANSWER: X) METHANOL2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 3
TOSS-UP7) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What is the most common term for the celestial phenomenon that causes a comet's tail in our solar system to point away from the Sun?ANSWER: THE SOLAR WINDBONUS7) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the BEST description of our Sun:W) a cool large star similar to Proxima CentauriX) a small-sized star about 6 billion years oldY) a mid-sized yellow dwarf starZ) a large-sized red giant about 4.7 billion years oldANSWER: Y) A MID-SIZED YELLOW DWARF STARTOSS-UP8) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following occurs in meiosis but NOT in mitosis:W) spindle apparatus attaches to kinetochores X) nuclear membrane is not visibleY) crossing overZ) chromosomes line up at central area of cellANSWER: Y) CROSSING OVERBONUS8) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the anatomical term for the specific section of the small intestine into which the pancreatic duct delivers its digestive enzymes?ANSWER: DUODENUM 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 4
TOSS-UP9) CHEMISTRY Short Answer In the combustion of methane, if the supply of oxygen is somewhat insufficient, what colorless, odorless and poisonous gas is produced?ANSWER: CARBON MONOXIDE (ACCEPT: CO)BONUS9) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Element number 19 has an isotope named potassium-40. How many neutrons does this isotope contain?ANSWER: 21TOSS-UP10) PHYSICS Multiple Choice. The amplitude of a sound wave most closely relates to its: W) frequency X) wavelength Y) loudness Z) overtonesANSWER. Y) LOUDNESSBONUS10) PHYSICS Short Answer What property of a sound wave most directly determines the pitch of a violin’s note?ANSWER: FREQUENCY2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 5
TOSS-UP11) MATH Short Answer Solve the following equation for x: – 3|x| = –15 (read as: minus 3 times the absolute value of x equals minus 15)ANSWER: 5 AND –5BONUS11) MATH Short Answer One-half of a number added to one third of the same number is 68 less than the number. What is the number?ANSWER: 408(Solution: x/2 + x/3 = x – 68; x = 408)TOSS-UP12) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Giving your answer as north, south, east, or west, from what general direction does the jet stream flow?ANSWER: WESTBONUS12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which of the following locations would you typically expect the average salinity of surface sea water to be the HIGHEST:W) at the mouth of the Mississippi River X) in the waters above the Arctic Circle Y) in the Black SeaZ) in the Dead SeaANSWER: Z) IN THE DEAD SEA 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 6
TOSS-UP13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer In the mks system, what are the 3 fundamental units? ANSWER: METERS; KILOGRAMS; SECONDSBONUS13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Giving your answer in scientific notation, convert 10 square meters into square millimeters:ANSWER: 1 × 107 (DO NOT ACCEPT: 107)TOSS-UP14) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:W) most of the meteorites that have been found have a high iron content X) a bolometer is used to measure the energy output of the SunY) the celestial coordinate analogous to latitude is called ascensionZ) sunlight reflecting off the Earth is called EarthshineANSWER: Y) THE CELESTIAL COORDINATE ANALOGOUS TO LATITUDE IS CALLED ASCENSIONBONUS14) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following BEST describes the zenith:W) the point in the sky that is at 180 degrees of inclination to the horizon X) 90 degrees opposite to the nadirY) the opposite position on the ecliptic to an observerZ) the point on the celestial sphere directly overhead of an observerANSWER: Z) THE POINT ON THE CELESTIAL SPHERE DIRECTLY OVERHEAD OF AN OBSERVER 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 7
TOSS-UP15) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following MOST closely represents the location of the temporal bone in humans:W) above the eyeX) cheek or lateral border of the eye Y) back of skullZ) top of skullANSWER: X) CHEEK OR LATERAL BORDER OF THE EYEBONUS15) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the common name for the joint that is formed by the articulation of the tibia, the fibula, and the femur?ANSWER: KNEETOSS-UP16) CHEMISTRY Short Answer How many unpaired electrons are in a neutral bromine atom? ANSWER: 1BONUS16) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the term used to describe the resistance to flow of a liquid:W) viscosityX) surface tension Y) maleabilityZ) vapor pressureANSWER: W) VISCOSITY 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 8
TOSS-UP17) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following is the most common term for the general type of wave that results from the vibration of a physical medium:W) mechanicalX) electromagnetic Y) perfectZ) pulsedANSWER: W) MECHANICALBONUS17) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following is LEAST accurate:W) alpha particles are the same as helium nucleiX) polarization of light supports the particle behavior of light Y) a photon is a particle of lightZ) light slows down when it moves from a vacuum into glassANSWER: X) POLARIZATION OF LIGHT SUPPORTS THE PARTICLE BEHAVIOR OF LIGHTTOSS-UP18) MATH Short Answer Evaluate the expression, x(y + z)2, when x = 2, y = -8; and z = 3: ANSWER: 50BONUS18) MATH Short Answer If Emily can paint a fence in 4 hours but Kathy takes 6 hours, how many hours will it take them to paint the fence if they work together?ANSWER: 2 2 (ACCEPT: 12 or 2.4) 55(Solution: 1/x = 1/4 + 1/6; x = 12/5 hrs or 2 2/5 hrs)   2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 9
TOSS-UP19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is considered the principal volcanic gas:W) carbon dioxide X) water vaporY) sulfur dioxide Z) methaneANSWER: X) WATER VAPORBONUS19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Calcite belongs to which of the following mineral groups:W) oxideX) sulfateY) carbonateZ) calcium silicateANSWER: Y) CARBONATE (Solution: CaCO3) TOSS-UP20) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a fermentation product of yogurt:W) acetaldehyde X) formaldehyde Y) acetic acidZ) lactic acidANSWER: X) FORMALDEHYDEBONUS20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Convert 1 cubic decimeter into cubic centimeters: ANSWER: 1,0002007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 10
TOSS-UP21) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What is the Latin-derived term for the relatively smooth lunar plains that are areas of the Moon that appear dark as viewed from Earth?ANSWER: MARE (ACCEPT: MARIA)BONUS21) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What planet has the greatest variation in temperature over a single one of its planetary days?ANSWER: MERCURYTOSS-UP22) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is typically the largest organelle of a mature plant cell and can comprise up to 80% of the cell’s volume?ANSWER: CENTRAL VACUOLE (ACCEPT: VACUOLE)BONUS22) BIOLOGY Short Answer What eukaryotic cell organelle primarily functions to modify, sort, and package products for exocytosis?ANSWER: GOLGI (ACCEPT: GOLGI APPARATUS, COMPLEX or STACK) 2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 11
TOSS-UP23) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What scientific principle BEST describes why fresh pickles soaked in brine shrivel up after a period of time?ANSWER: OSMOSISBONUS23) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice If two solutions that are separated by a semipermeable membrane have the same osmotic pressure, they are said to be:W) isotonicX) hypotonicY) hypertonic Z) hyperosmoticANSWER: W) ISOTONIC TOSS-UP24) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A circuit with 2 different resistors wired in series will have a total resistance that is:W) equal to the sum of the two resistances X) less than either resistanceY) equal to that of the greater resistance Z) equal to that of the lesser resistanceANSWER: W) EQUAL TO THE SUM OF THE TWO RESISTANCESBONUS24) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the most common isotope of carbon? ANSWER: CARBON-12 (ACCEPT: C-12 or 12)2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 12
TOSS-UP25) BIOLOGY Short Answer How many walking legs are found in arachnids? ANSWER: 8BONUS25) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the MOST common term for the general type of nourishment characteristic of mushrooms where the organism derives its nutrients by absorbing the biological products of another organism?ANSWER: SAPROPHYTIC (ACCEPT: SAPROBE or SAPROPHAGE or SAPROPHYTE)2007 Regional Science Bowl – Page 13