ROUND 12 TOSS-UP1) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Kepler’s third law states that the square of a planet’s period is proportional to the:W) cube of its average distance from the sunX) square root of its average distance from the sunY) cube of its average distance from its two neighboring planets Z) square of its average distance from the sunANSWER: W) CUBE OF ITS AVERAGE DISTANCE FROM THE SUNBONUS1) PHYSICS Short Answer Order the following 4 categories of electromagnetic radiation from the LOWEST frequency to the HIGHEST: Ultraviolet, VHF TV, AM radio, radiation from 60 hertz AC currentANSWER: RADIATION FROM 60 HERTZ AC CURRENT; AM RADIO; VHF TV; ULTRAVIOLETTOSS-UP2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice A substance’s heat of sublimation at a given temperature is equal to which of the following at the same temperature:W) heat of fusionX) heat of vaporizationY) heat of fusion plus heat of vaporization Z) heat of fusion minus heat of vaporizationANSWER: Y) HEAT OF FUSION PLUS HEAT OF VAPORIZATIONBONUS2) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Order the following 4 acids from the strongest to the weakest: nitric acid; perchloric acid; hydrochloric acid; acetic acidANSWER: PERCHLORIC ACID; HYDROCHLORIC ACID; NITRIC ACID; ACETIC ACID 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12 Page 1TOSS-UP3) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following molecules is best described as recognizing a specific nucleotide sequence and sniping the DNA at or near this recognition site:W) restriction enzyme X) DNA polymerase Y) RNA polymerase Z) DNA ligaseANSWER: W) RESTRICTION ENZYMEBONUS3) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice A double membrane is found in the:W) endoplasmic reticulum and nucleusX) nucleus and golgi (pronounced: GOAL-gee) Y) lysosomes and golgiZ) nucleus and chloroplastsANSWER: Z) NUCLEUS AND CHLOROPLASTSTOSS-UP4) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following constellations can be seen highest in the November sky of the northern hemisphere? W) OrionX) Cassiopeia Y) MensaZ) CancerANSWER: X) CASSIOPEIABONUS4) ASTRONOMY Short Answer The Stefan-Boltzman Law states that the energy emitted from a black body varies with what power of the temperature?ANSWER: FOURTH2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12 Page 2TOSS-UP5) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following Venn diagrams would best represent a relationship where sets A and B have no elements in common:W) 2 non-overlapping shaded circlesX) portions of circles A and B are overlapped and the intersection point is shaded Y) circle A is entirely within circle B and only circle A is shadedZ) only circle A is shownANSWER: W) 2 NON-OVERLAPPING SHADED CIRCLESBONUS5) MATH Short Answer Use the Binomial Theorem to expand and simplify the following equation: (1 – 2x)3ANSWER : 1 – 6x + 12x2 – 8x3TOSS-UP6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the study of the size and shape of the Earth, the measurement of terrestrial gravitational forces, and the location of fixed points on the earth's surface: W) geography X) geology Y) geotropy Z) geodesyANSWER: Z) GEODESYBONUS6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following types of magma would LEAST likely be involved in a nonexplosive volcanic eruption:W) basaltic magmaX) a relatively viscous magmaY) a relatively low silica content magma Z) a relatively high-temperature magmaANSWER: X) A RELATIVELY VISCOUS MAGMA2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12Page 3TOSS-UP7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A type of lens aberration whereby the lens cannot focus the image of a flat subject onto a flat surface is called:W) barrel distortionX) chromatic aberration Y) field curvatureZ) spherical aberrationANSWER: Y) FIELD CURVATUREBONUS7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice One of the major challenges to making more accurate atomic clocks was:W) high atomic frequencies were difficult to monitorX) maintaining constant atomic vibrationsY) finding pure elementary samples for studiesZ) cosmic ray interference disrupts the accurate measurements of atomic vibrationsANSWER: W) HIGH ATOMIC FREQUENCIES ARE DIFFICULT TO MONITORTOSS-UP8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice A hardware frame and set of electrical connection interfaces that enable a notebook computer to effectively serve as a desktop computer is called a: W) docking station X) local busY) proxy interface Z) swapping deckANSWER: W) DOCKING STATION8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice A client-server architecture is also known as:W) peer-to-peer architecture X) mainframe architecture Y) two-tier architectureZ) docking architectureANSWER: Y) TWO-TIER ARCHITECTURE2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12Page 4BONUSTOSS-UP9) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the resistance, in ohms, of an electric curling iron that draws 10 amps on a 120 volt line?ANSWER: 12(Solution: I = V/R, R = V/I, R = 120/10 = 12 ohms)BONUS9) PHYSICS Short Answer Consider a marble rolling in a straight path at 25 meters per second that slows to 15 meters per second in 5 seconds. In meters per second squared, what is the marble’s average acceleration?ANSWER: -2 (DO NOT ACCEPT: 2 OR +2) (Solution: (15-25) / 5 = -2 m/s2)TOSS-UP10) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice In the equation for Gibbs-free energy, if ∆H (read as: delta H) of a reaction is negative and ∆S (read as: delta S) is negative, then the reaction will occur:W) spontaneously at all temperaturesX) nonspontaneously at all temperaturesY) spontaneously only at high temperatures Z) spontaneously only at low temperaturesANSWER: Z) SPONTANEOUSLY ONLY AT LOW TEMPERATURESBONUS10) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Heating ethylene in the presence of water vapor at 300°C and under high pressure, is a common industrial method of producing billions of pounds of what substance?ANSWER: ETHANOL (ACCEPT: ETHYL ALCOHOL) 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12 Page 5TOSS-UP11) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following cells would NOT typically be found in the peripheral circulation:W) Polymorphonuclear leukocyte X) plasma cellY) reticulocyteZ) erythroblastsANSWER: Z) ERYTHROBLASTSBONUS11) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice The coat of a plant seed is typically derived from which of the following:W) the hypoderm X) the carpelY) the micropyle Z) the integumentANSWER: Z) THE INTEGUMENTTOSS-UP12) ASTRONOMY Short Answer How many degrees of arc are in 6 hours of right ascension? ANSWER: 90 DEGREESBONUS12) ASTRONOMY Short Answer Which 2 of the following 5 minor planets have the largest diameters: Eros, Juno, Ceres, Amor, ApolloANSWER: CERES AND JUNO2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12 Page 6TOSS-UP13) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following angles would be located in Quadrant IV of a rectangular coordinate system:W) 2/3 rev X) -480° Y) 3/16 rev Z) 0.8 revANSWER: Z) 0.8 REVBONUS13) MATH Short Answer In the following number sequence, what are the values for a, b and c: a, b, 38, 22, 14, 10, cANSWER: a=134; b=70; c=8TOSS-UP14) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice A number of “8” on the Beaufort Scale indicates a wind speed of: W) 7–10knots X) 17–21knots Y) 34–40knots Z) 40–64knotsANSWER: Y) 34 – 40 KNOTSBONUS14) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice In what 5-year period did the U.S. experience the highest level of North Atlantic hurricane activity:W) 1970 - 1975 X) 1980 - 1985 Y) 1985 - 1990 Z) 1995 - 2000ANSWER: Z) 1995 - 20002002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12Page 7TOSS-UP15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In the oceanic ecosystem, which zone is defined by the depth of light penetration:W) probiotic X) euphotic Y) photobiotic Z) bathyalANSWER: X) EUPHOTICBONUS15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Most manufactured glass used to make bottles, tableware, lamp bulbs, and window and plate glass, is of what composition:W) potassium silicate X) borosilicateY) soda-limeZ) leadANSWER: Y) SODA-LIME TOSS-UP16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a protocol associated with the workings of the internet:W) POP3 X) FTP Y) HTML Z) TFTANSWER: Z) TFT(Solution: TFT = Thin Film Transistor)BONUS16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Short Answer In the BASIC programming language, what does the acronym BASIC stand for?ANSWER: BEGINNERS ALL-PURPOSE SYMBOLIC INSTRUCTIONAL CODE2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12 Page 8TOSS-UP17) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Wein’s law expresses the relationship between the wavelength at the peak emission in black body radiation and:W) the change in pressureX) the black body’s structureY) the temperature in KelvinsZ) the interference patterns of associated electronsANSWER: Y) THE TEMPERATURE IN KELVINSBONUS17) PHYSICS Short Answer Assuming g = 10.0 m/sec2 and friction is 0, if a rock is thrown vertically upward at 10.0 m/sec, how far up in meters will it be after 1 second?ANSWER: 5 METERS(Solution: d=Vot+1⁄2at2 =10×1-1⁄210×12 =10–5=5meters)TOSS-UP18) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice A ketone is a class of compounds that contains a carbonyl group bonded to: W) 2 carbon atomsX) 2 hydrogen atomsY) 2 nitrogen atomsZ) 1 hydrogen and 1 carbon atomANSWER: W) 2 CARBON ATOMSBONUS18) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the primary product produced when ethyl alcohol is heated to 170°C in the presence of 95% sulfuric acid?ANSWER: ETHYLENE2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12 Page 9TOSS-UP19) BIOLOGY Short Answer Of the primary, secondary, tertiary and quaternary levels of protein structure, at what level would a beta-pleated sheet be placed?ANSWER: SECONDARYBONUS19) BIOLOGY Short Answer Exchange of DNA among chromosomes occurs in what phase of meiosis-one?ANSWER: PROPHASE (ACCEPT: PROPHASE-ONE)TOSS-UP20) MATH Short Answer What is the most common statistical term for the assumption, when comparing sample means, that there is no significant difference between the two samples?ANSWER: NULL HYPOTHESISBONUS20) MATH Multiple Choice Using the Cartesian coordinate system, find the distance between the points (-4, 3) and (2, 6):W) 3 5 X) 12Y) 3 Z) 5 3ANSWER: W) 3 5     2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12Page 10TOSS-UP21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT associated with sedimentary rocks:W) beddingX) fossilsY) foliationZ) ripple marksANSWER: Y) FOLIATIONBONUS21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Also known as mock suns or parhelia, what is the name for a pair of brightly colored spots, one on either side of the sun, that are caused by sunlight passing through a thin layer of ice crystals:W) sun pillarsX) cloud iridescence Y) sundogsZ) silver liningANSWER: Y) SUNDOGS TOSS-UP22) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Rust is a plant disease that attacks cereal plants such as wheat and rye and is caused by a:W) virusX) larval insect Y) bacterium Z) fungusANSWER: Z) FUNGUSBONUS22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Thin layer chromatography most commonly employs what substance as the matrix for the chromatographic separation?ANSWER: SILICA (ACCEPT: SILICA GEL)2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12 Page 11TOSS-UP23) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Fermi noted that the biggest advantage of bombarding nuclei with neutrons was because:W) they have no electric chargeX) they were easily produced in large numbersY) they often interacted with electronsZ) they seldom had enough energy to split the nucleusANSWER: W) THEY HAVE NO ELECTRIC CHARGEBONUS23) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the name of the particle detector in Ontario that is buried 2 kilometers underground in a nickel mine?ANSWER: SNO (ACCEPT: SUDBURY NEUTRINO DETECTOR OR SUDBURY NEUTRINO OBSERVATORY)TOSS-UP24) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of these substances is NOT attacked by hydrochloric acid: W) ironX) calciteY) barium phosphate Z) n-heptaneANSWER: Z) N-HEPTANEBONUS24) CHEMISTRY Short Answer A chemical reaction in which esters are hydrolyzed under basic conditions to give an alcohol and a salt of the acid is generally known as what type of reaction?ANSWER: SAPONIFICATION2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12 Page 12TOSS-UP25) BIOLOGY Short Answer The most common method used by Beadle and Tatum in generating mutant molds for their metabolic studies was to expose the molds to what?ANSWER: X-RAYSBONUS25) BIOLOGY Short Answer Which 2 of the following 4 amino acids contain nonpolar R groups? serine; glutamine; leucine; (read as: lew-seen), phenylalanine (read as: FEE-nal-AL-a-neen)ANSWER: LEUCINE; PHENYLALANINE2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 12 Page 13