ROUND 8 TOSS-UP1) PHYSICS Short Answer Neglecting friction, what is the acceleration, in meters per second squared, when a force of 144 Newtons is applied to a 12 kilogram object:ANSWER: 12(Solution: A = F/M; A = 144/12; A = 12 m/sec2)BONUS1) PHYSICS Multiple Choice When Johann Schweigger invented the first galvanometer, what did he recognize could be used to measure current:W) deflection of a compass needleX) movement of iron particles in a magnetic field Y) movement of electrons through a potentialZ) a magnetoANSWER: W) DEFLECTION OF A COMPASS NEEDLETOSS-UP2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following has the highest specific heat value:W) wood X) ice water Y) sandZ) goldANSWER: X) ICE WATER(Solution: wood = 0.42 Cal/g°C; ice water = 0.5; sand = 0.19; gold = 0.031)BONUS2) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Normal hydrogen at room temperature contains what two forms of hydrogen, as defined by the spins of their electrons and nuclei?ANSWER: PARA AND ORTHO 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8 Page 1TOSS-UP3) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice When the color of an organism alerts predators to stay away it is technically referred to as:W) aposematic coloration X) homological coloration Y) analogous coloration Z) camouflage colorationANSWER: W) APOSEMATIC COLORATIONBONUS3) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a hexose:W) mannoseX) glucoseY) fructoseZ) xylulose (pronounced: zyle-YOU-lows)ANSWER: Z) XYLULOSETOSS-UP4) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice A first quarter Moon will cross the meridian at what time of the day or night: W) midnight X) sunrise Y) sunsetZ) noonANSWER: W) MIDNIGHTBONUS4) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What is the most common astronomical term for the angle analogous to geographical longitude?ANSWER: RIGHT ASCENSION (ACCEPT: ASCENSION)2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8 Page 2TOSS-UP5) MATH Short Answer What is the equation of a line that has a slope of 4 and a y-intercept of 5? ANSWER: y=4x+5BONUS5) MATH Short Answer Factor the following expression as completely as possible: x4 – 16 ANSWER: (x – 2)(x + 2)(x2 + 4)TOSS-UP6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The salts and ions derived from the chemical weathering of rocks are carried by a stream are part of its: W) bed loadX) suspended load Y) dissolved load Z) salt loadANSWER: Y) DISSOLVED LOADBONUS6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The Sahara desert in Africa is an example of what type of desert:W) subtropical X) continental Y) rainshadow Z) coastalANSWER: W) SUBTROPICAL2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8Page 3TOSS-UP7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Electric appliances and tools are grounded to:W) complete the electrical circuitX) balance the voltage in both linesY) prevent the overloading of circuits Z) prevent surface static charge buildupANSWER: Z) PREVENT SURFACE STATIC CHARGE BUILDUPBONUS7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of a multiple fruit:W) appleX) sour cherry Y) pineapple Z) pearANSWER: Y) PINEAPPLE TOSS-UP8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice An email sent over the internet most likely uses what protocol:W) HTTP X) FTPY) SMTP Z) HMTTPANSWER: Y) SMTPBONUS8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the high-speed serial bus developed by Apple and Texas Instruments that allows for the connection of multiple devices, supports hot-swapping, and transfers data at rates of up to 400 million bytes per second:ANSWER: FIREWIRE (ACCEPT: IEEE 1394, I-LINK, AND LYNX)2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8 Page 4TOSS-UP9) PHYSICS Multiple Choice What branch of mechanics customarily deals with force and why objects move as they do:W) kinematics X) dynamics Y) staticsZ) mechanicsANSWER: X) DYNAMICS9) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Yellow light has a wavelength of approximately:W) 300-350 nanometers X) 450-500 nanometers Y) 550-600 nanometers Z) 650-700 nanometersANSWER: Y) 550-600 NANOMETERSBONUS TOSS-UP10) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice In which of the following pairs are both elements classified as semimetals:W) tellurium and tinX) selenium and bromine Y) scandium and silicon Z) arsenic and germaniumANSWER: Z) ARSENIC AND GERMANIUMBONUS10) CHEMISTRY Short Answer The f subshell is associated with what L quantum number? ANSWER: 32002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8 Page 5TOSS-UP11) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the predominant immunoglobulin class found in human saliva?ANSWER: IgABONUS11) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the common name for the part of a compound light microscope that functions to converge a light source so that it passes through the specimen:ANSWER: CONDENSERTOSS-UP12) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Because of precession, the celestial pole traces out a complete circle on the sky about every: W) 26,000 years X) 12,000 years Y) 6,000 years Z) 600 yearsANSWER: W) 26,000 YEARS12) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice The ecliptic is:W) the line that divides the sky into the northern half and the southern half X) the Sun's apparent path across the celestial sphereY) the point directly overheadZ) the line on the celestial sphere directly above the celestial equatorANSWER: X) THE SUN'S APPARENT PATH ACROSS THE CELESTIAL SPHEREBONUS2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8Page 6TOSS-UP13) MATH Short Answer If the universal set is represented by the numbers 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and set A is represented by the numbers 1, 2, 3; set B by the numbers 3, 4, 5, 6; and set C by the numbers 2, 3, 4, then what set is represented by the union of sets A and B?ANSWER: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6BONUS13) MATH Short Answer In the US Senate, Senator Bill received four-sixths of the votes, Senator George received two- tenths of the votes, and Senator Mary received the remaining votes. If 48 votes were cast for Senator Mary, how many votes did Senator Bill receive?ANSWER: 240TOSS-UP14) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following make up approximately 80% of all magma erupted by volcanoes on Earth:W) andesiticX) rhyoliticY) basalticZ) andesitic and rhyoliticANSWER: Y) BASALTIC(Solution: andesitic and rhyolitic 10% each)BONUS14) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer A mixture of molten rock, suspended mineral grains, and dissolved gasses that forms in the crust or mantle when temperatures are sufficiently high, is a definition of what?ANSWER: MAGMA 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8 Page 7TOSS-UP15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of a modular organism that grows by producing additional units of body construction that are very similar to the units of which it is already composed:W) sea sponge X) cockroach Y) spiderZ) turtleANSWER: W) SEA SPONGEBONUS15) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer A widely used dental amalgam is formed by reacting metallic mercury with an alloy consisting primarily of which 2 metals?ANSWER: SILVER AND TINTOSS-UP16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is TRUE about resolution:W) printed images resolve with dots per inch and displayed images resolve with pixelsX) printed images resolve with dots per inch and displayed images resolve with dots per inch Y) printed images resolve with pixels and displayed images resolve with dots per inchZ) printed images resolve with pixels and displayed images resolve with pixelsANSWER: W) PRINTED IMAGES RESOLVE WITH DOTS PER INCH AND DISPLAYED IMAGES RESOLVE WITH PIXELSBONUS16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice Fonts that are digital representations of fonts that are not scalable are called:W) bitmap fonts X) outline fonts Y) TrueType fonts Z) vector fontsANSWER: W) BITMAP FONTS 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8Page 8TOSS-UP17) PHYSICS Short Answer What scientist was the first to propose that in the absence of air resistance, all objects fall with the same constant acceleration?ANSWER: GALILEOBONUS17) PHYSICS Short Answer If a piano string is 1.6 meters long and has a fundamental frequency of 320 Hertz, what is the wavelength, in meters, of the fundamental?ANSWER: 3.2(Solution: wavelength = 2L; = (2)(1.6) = 3.2 meters)TOSS-UP18) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is considered a nonpolar molecule: W) H2S X) NH3 Y) NO2 Z) BeH2ANSWER: Z) BeH2BONUS18) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What general term describes a substance whose electrons are all spin-paired and that are weakly repelled by magnetic fields?ANSWER: DIAMAGNETIC2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8 Page 9TOSS-UP19) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the name for the group of muscles that stabilize the shoulder joint by holding the head of the humerus in its socket?ANSWER: ROTATOR CUFFBONUS19) BIOLOGY Short Answer The “one gene one enzyme” rule proposed by Beadle and Tatum was mostly based upon their work with what genus of organisms?ANSWER: NEUROSPORATOSS-UP20) MATH Short Answer An arc of length 2π is cut off by a central angle of π4 radians. What is the radius of the circle?  ANSWER: 8(Solution: r = S/α; = 2π / (π/4); = 8)BONUS  20) MATH Short Answer Simplify the following equation: ANSWER: x +1 (ACCEPT: 1+ x )9x + 9 −4x + 4  2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8Page 10TOSS-UP21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following types of plutons is a cylindrical conduit of igneous rock below a volcanic vent:W) laccolithX) dikeY) volcanic stock Z) volcanic pipeANSWER: Z) VOLCANIC PIPEBONUS21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Trellis drainage patterns are most likely to form on:W) coastal plains X) folded terrains Y) glacial outwash Z) permafrostANSWER: X) FOLDED TERRAINS TOSS-UP22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What contemporary of Autolycus wrote a set of thirteen books titled “Elements”, which remains among the most studied works in human thought and was a culmination of classical geometry?ANSWER: EUCLIDBONUS22) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In the tempering of steel, the slower the hot steel cools in the quenching process:W) the softer its core and the less the outer hardness penetrates X) the softer its core and the more the outer hardness penetrates Y) the harder its core and the less the outer hardness penetrates Z) the harder its core and the more the outer hardness penetratesANSWER: W) THE SOFTER ITS CORE AND THE LESS THE OUTER HARDNESS PENETRATES2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8 Page 11TOSS-UP23) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following explains why a sailboat can sail into the wind:W) Archimedes' Principle X) Bernoulli's LawY) Pascal's LawZ) Reynolds' NumbersANSWER: X) BERNOULLI'S LAW24) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Liver enzymes oxidize ethanol to:W) methanolX) formaldehyde Y) oxalic acidZ) acetaldehydeANSWER: Z) ACETALDEHYDEBONUS23) PHYSICS Multiple Choice If the resolution of the human eye is about 0.1 millimeter and the resolution of a light microscope is about 2,000 angstroms, what is the approximate useful magnification of a human eye combined with a light microscope:W) 250 times X) 500 times Y) 1,000 times Z) 2,000 timesANSWER: X) 500 TIMES TOSS-UPBONUS24) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Which of the gas laws describes how the volume of a gas is affected by changes in pressure, temperature, and amount?ANSWER: IDEAL GAS LAW2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8 Page 12TOSS-UP25) BIOLOGY Short Answer In bacterial transference of genes, what is the term for when naked DNA enters the cell from the surroundings:ANSWER: TRANSDUCTIONBONUS25) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the type of plant leaf that lacks a palisade and spongy mesophyll:W) common crabgrass X) dandelionY) apple treeZ) lotus plantANSWER: W) COMMON CRABGRASS2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 8Page 13