ROUND 11TOSS-UP1) PHYSICS Short Answer In their studies of trans-uranium elements and crystallization studies of barium, Hahn and Meitner discovered what process?ANSWER: FISSION (ACCEPT: NUCLEAR FISSION)BONUS1) PHYSICS Short Answer Assuming g = -32 feet/sec2 and friction is negligible, if a coffee bean is thrown upward from the top of a building with a vertical velocity of +32 ft/sec, what will its velocity be in ft/sec after 3 seconds?ANSWER: -64 (ACCEPT: -64 or 64 DOWN)TOSS-UP2) BIOLOGY Short Answer Afferent neuron is to sensory neuron as efferent neuron is to: ANSWER: MOTOR NEURONBONUS2) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is most accurate about the pasteurization of milk:W) it heats milk to the boiling point for about 1minuteX) it kills all bacteria by passing steam through the milkY) it kills most of the germs in the milk by moderate heating Z) it kills all the bacteria but not the viruses in the milkANSWER: Y) IT KILLS MOST OF THE GERMS IN THE MILK BY MODERATE HEATING 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11 Page 1
TOSS-UP3) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Hydrocarbons that contain a carbon-carbon double bond are generally know as what:ANSWER: ALKENES (ACCEPT: OLEFINS)BONUS3) CHEMISTRY Short Answer If you have 1 milliliter of a 75% ethanol stock solution, how much water, in milliliters, must be added to the 1 milliliter stock solution to obtain a 25% ethanol solution?ANSWER: 2(Solution: 75%/25% = 3df; 1 part stock + 2 parts water = 3df)TOSS-UP4) ASTRONOMY Short Answer The total amount of energy of a star’s surface radiated into space each second is most commonly referred to as what?ANSWER: ABSOLUTE LUMINOSITY (ACCEPT: LUMINOSITY, INTRINSIC BRIGHTNESS, OR ABSOLUTE BRIGHTNESS)BONUS4) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice If you could shrink the Earth to a quarter its present diameter while maintaining its mass, by what factor would the escape velocity change?W) the escape velocity would be doubledX) the escape velocity would be four times larger Y) the escape velocity would remain unchanged Z) the escape velocity would be reduced by halfANSWER: W) THE ESCAPE VELOCITY WOULD BE DOUBLED (Solution: escape velocity ~ (M/R)1/2; Ve = √2GM/r) 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11Page 2
TOSS-UP5) MATH Short Answer What is the term for the part of the secant contained between the points of intersection on a curve?ANSWER: CHORDBONUS5) MATH Short Answer Find the solution set of the following inequality: x2 – x – 2 ≤ 0 ANSWER: -1≤x≤2TOSS-UP6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The Hawaiian Islands originated from magma:W) intruding along the boundary between two lithospheric plates X) formed within an island arcY) injected along a mid-ocean fracture zoneZ) coming from a hotspot within the mantleANSWER: Z) COMING FROM A HOTSPOT WITHIN THE MANTLEBONUS6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is classified as a silicate mineral:W) gypsum X) malachite Y) haliteZ) quartzANSWER: Z) QUARTZ 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11Page 3
TOSS-UP7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A severe and chronic deficiency in what vitamin causes the disease known as pellagra:W) vitamin C X) vitamin D Y) niacinZ) thiamineANSWER: Y) NIACINBONUS7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What tree in the North-Central to Northeast US has heart-shaped leaves and a light-colored wood which is prized by wood carversW) pin oakX) cottonwoodY) American sycamore Z) basswoodANSWER: Z) BASSWOOD TOSS-UP8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice This distributed information system was prevalent in the years before the World Wide Web:W) Gopher X) SSLY) LINUX Z) FoxANSWER: W) GOPHERBONUS8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice Dynamic RAM is called such because:W) the value it holds can be dynamically changed at any timeX) the address space the RAM refers to can be dynamically changedY) the value it holds must be dynamically refreshed every few milliseconds Z) the value it holds must be dynamically refreshed once a sessionANSWER: Y) THE VALUE IT HOLDS MUST BE DYNAMICALLY REFRESHED EVERY FEW MILLISECONDS2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11 Page 4
TOSS-UP9) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following exhibits the least resistivity at 20°C:W) goldX) tungsten Y) ironZ) copperANSWER: Z) COPPERBONUS9) PHYSICS Short Answer If a violin string is 0.5 meters long and has a mass of 3.0 grams, what tension, in Newtons, must be on the string to give a wave velocity of 14.14 meters per second?ANSWER: 1.2(Solution: V = mT/ l ; = m/l × v2 = T; (0.003/0.5)(200) = 1.2 newtons)TOSS-UP10) BIOLOGY Short Answer The coronal suture is found between what two bones? ANSWER: PARIETAL AND FRONTAL (accept in any order)BONUS10) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following infectious agents is NOT properly matched with its disease:W) Trichophyton (read as:TRI-co-fie-ton) and ringworm X) Hepatitis A and serum hepatitisY) Rubella and German measlesZ) Epstein Barr and infectious mononucleosisANSWER: X) HEPATITIS A AND SERUM HEPATITIS (Solution: Hepatitis A causes infectious hepatitis)  2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11Page 5
TOSS-UP11) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Polystyrene is produced by which of the following reactions:W) free radical vinyl polymerization from the monomer styrene X) metalocene catalysis polymerizationY) graft copolymerizationZ) butadiene polymerizationANSWER: W) FREE RADICAL VINYL POLYMERIZATION FROM THE MONOMER STYRENEBONUS11) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following molecular shapes would you expect from O3:W) bentX) trigonal planar Y) linearZ) see-sawANSWER: W) BENT TOSS-UP12) ASTRONOMY Short Answer When a one solar mass star becomes a red giant for the first time, its energy comes mainly from the fusion of helium forming into what final element?ANSWER: CARBONBONUS12) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following distance-measuring techniques measures the farthest:W) radar rangingX) stellar parallaxY) variable starsZ) standard candle/Tully-Fisher relationANSWER: Z) STANDARD CANDLE/TULLY-FISHER RELATION2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11Page 6
TOSS-UP13) MATH Multiple Choice In a normal distribution, a mean of a sample population, plus or minus 1 standard deviation, includes what percentage of the sample:W) 16% X) 32% Y) 68% Z) 95%ANSWER: Y) 68%BONUS13) MATH Short Answer What is the 13th term in the following arithmetic progression: 2, 7, 12... ANSWER: 62(Solution: an = 2 + (13 – 1)5)TOSS-UP14) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice When two halves of a crystal aggregate are mirror images of each other and joined together in some definite, shared crystallographic orientation, such crystals are referred to as being: W) polymorphs X) symmetrical Y) twinnedZ) anhedralANSWER: Y) TWINNEDBONUS14) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is FALSE about the Coriolis Effect:W) it is an apparent force due to the precession of the EarthX) it is an apparent force due to the rotation of the EarthY) it causes winds in the Northern Hemisphere to be deflected to the right Z) it causes winds in the Southern Hemisphere to be deflected to the leftANSWER: W) IT IS AN APPARENT FORCE DUE TO THE PRECESSION OF THE EARTH2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11 Page 7
TOSS-UP15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A wave with a wavelength of 40 meters and a height of 2 meters, will NOT be refracted in water with a depth of more than:W) 1 meter X) 2 meters Y) 10 meters Z) 20 metersANSWER: Z) 20 METERSBONUS15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The mass of a new 2002 USA quarter is about how many grams:W) 3.0 X) 4.5 Y) 5.5 Z) 7.0ANSWER: Y) 5.5 TOSS-UP16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which printer uses bits of plastic that effectively are melted onto the surface of the paper:W) thermal X) ink jetY) laserZ) dot matrixANSWER: Y) LASERBONUS16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is true for a binary tree but not for a regular tree:W) it stores only zeros and onesX) each parent node has no more than two children Y) its branches are orderedZ) nodes without children are called leavesANSWER: X) EACH PARENT NODE HAS NO MORE THAN TWO CHILDREN 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11Page 8
TOSS-UP17) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Red light has a wavelength of:W) 300-350 nanometers X) 450-500 nanometers Y) 550-600 nanometers Z) 650-700 nanometersANSWER: Z) 650-700 NANOMETERSBONUS17) PHYSICS Short Answer Bose-Einstein condensates were initially created by using elements from what specific part of the periodic table:ANSWER: GROUP 1 (ACCEPT: ALKALI METALS)TOSS-UP18) BIOLOGY Short Answer From what vitamin is NAD derived? ANSWER: NIACINBONUS18) BIOLOGY Short Answer Penicillium notatum is to penicillin as Bacillus subtilis (pronounced: SUT-ill-iss) is to:ANSWER: BACITRACIN 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11 Page 9
TOSS-UP19) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following radioactive isotopes emits alpha particles:W) hydrogen-3 X) cobalt-60 Y) carbon-14 Z) radium-226ANSWER: Z) RADIUM-226BONUS19) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the molecular formula for the conjugate acid of the following Brønsted-Lowry base: HCO3–ANSWER: H2CO3TOSS-UP20) ASTRONOMY Short Answer In North America, what is typically the most spectacular meteor shower in the month of August?ANSWER: PERSEIDSBONUS20) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice A bolometer (pronounced: bowl-O-meter) is used to:W) measure the energy output of the Sun X) measure the length of a bowling alley Y) measure the size of celestial bodies Z) standardize the azimuth of a sextantANSWER: W) MEASURE THE ENERGY OUTPUT OF THE SUN 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11Page 10
TOSS-UP21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice As the intensity of metamorphism increases, which of the following transformations occurs:W) granite to slateX) schist to slateY) gneiss to quartzite Z) limestone to marbleANSWER: Z) LIMESTONE TO MARBLEBONUS21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which of the following latitudes would you expect belts of high pressure to typically develop:W) 30° North X) 0°Y) 50° North Z) 60° SouthANSWER: W) 30° NORTH TOSS-UP22) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is classified as a water- insoluble fiber:W) algal polysaccharides X) pectinY) ligninZ) gumsANSWER: Y) LIGNINBONUS22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Methods that cause hair to have curls usually rely on manipulating disulfide bonds in what amino acid?ANSWER: CYSTINE2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) PHYSICS Multiple Choice The line spectra of low density gases is usually produced by the emission or absorption of light by:W) moleculesX) crystalsY) crystal lattices Z) individual atomsANSWER: Z) INDIVIDUAL ATOMSBONUS23) PHYSICS Short Answer What was the last name of the father and son team that developed the theory and technique of X-ray diffraction by crystals?ANSWER: BRAGGTOSS-UP24) BIOLOGY Short Answer Avery and Macleod attributed the transforming principle to what substance?ANSWER: DNABONUS24) BIOLOGY Short Answer What other vitamin acts like an antagonist and has the most similar structure to vitamin K?ANSWER: VITAMIN E (Solution: both are isoprenoids) 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11 Page 12
TOSS-UP25) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Reaction with a copper compound is a qualitative test for which functional group:W) alcoholX) aldehydeY) ketoneZ) carboxylic acidANSWER: X) ALDEHYDEBONUS25) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Name the two elements that have atomic numbers less than that of lead that have no stable isotopes:ANSWER: TECHNETIUM AND PROMETHIUM (ACCEPT: Tc and Pm)2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 11 Page 13