ROUND 4 TOSS-UP
1) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the angular velocity of a wheel with a radius of 15 meters and a surface velocity of 120 meters/sec:
ANSWER: 8 RAD/SEC (Solution: T = v/r = 120/15 = 8)
BONUS
1) PHYSICS Short Answer Assuming friction is negligible, how long will it take an object to stop if it has an initial velocity of 5 meters per second, if the average braking force is 20 Newtons, and if the object’s mass is 20 kilograms?
ANSWER: 5 SECONDS
(Solution:v=at,f=ma =>t=v/a =vm/f=20x5/20=5seconds)
TOSS-UP
2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice For individuals who are “Lactose Intolerant,” the reason for their gastric distress is the production of:
W) methane
X) acetic acid and nitrogen
Y) lactic acid and carbon dioxide Z) acetic acid and methane
ANSWER: Y) LACTIC ACID AND CARBON DIOXIDE
BONUS
2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which acid connects the 2-deoxyribose units within every DNA strand:
W) acetic acid
X) phosphoric acid Y) citric acid
Z) glycolic acid
ANSWER: X) PHOSPHORIC ACID
 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4
Page 1
TOSS-UP
3) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following organisms does NOT belong to the Class Arachnida:
W) scorpions X) lobsters Y) mites
Z) ticks
ANSWER: X) LOBSTERS
BONUS
3) BIOLOGY Short Answer What anatomical structure is responsible for the various colors of eyes in humans?
ANSWER: IRIS
TOSS-UP
4) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following planets is NOT known to have any orbiting satellites:
 W) Venus X) Mars Y) Uranus Z) Saturn
ANSWER: W) VENUS
4) ASTRONOMY Short Answer Cassini’s division is associated with what planet? ANSWER: SATURN
BONUS
2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4
Page 2
TOSS-UP
5) MATH Short Answer Convert 135° into radians: ANSWER: 3π
BONUS
 4
5) MATH Short Answer Solve the following inequality: 3 – 6x > 15 ANSWER: x < -2
TOSS-UP
6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Hawaiian volcanoes such as Kilauea and Mauna Loa are examples of which of the following types of volcanoes:
 W) basaltic
X) rhyolitic
Y) andesitic
Z) andesitic and rhyolitic
ANSWER: W) BASALTIC
BONUS
6) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer In reference to glacial ice, the process by which ice below the snow line is lost by evaporation and melting is called what?
ANSWER: ABLATION
2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4 Page 3
TOSS-UP
7) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is a quantity that has only a magnitude most commonly called?
ANSWER: SCALAR
BONUS
7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What pioneer bacteriologist in 1873 located a particular bacterium that caused anthrax in the spleen of infected cattle and, after transferring it serially to mice, recovered the same bacterium in the end:
W) Louis Pasteur
X) Robert Koch (pronounced: Coke) Y) Rudolf Virchow
Z) Peter Vogt
ANSWER: X) ROBERT KOCH
 TOSS-UP
8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Short Answer In most computer systems, a byte is a unit of data that is how many binary digits long?
ANSWER: 8
8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term for half a byte, or four bits? ANSWER: NIBBLE (ACCEPT: NYBBLE)
BONUS
2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4
Page 4
TOSS-UP
9) PHYSICS Short Answer In a standing wave of a vibrating wire cord, what are the points of constructive interference most commonly called where the cord oscillates with maximum amplitude?
ANSWER: ANTINODES
BONUS
9) PHYSICS Short Answer For a radioactive element with a half-life of 5000 years, if a sample of the radioactive element is left to decay for 15,000 years, what fraction of the original radioactive atoms in the sample will be left?
ANSWER: 1/8 (ACCEPT: 12.5%)
TOSS-UP
10) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following elements is found in Period 3 and main Group 5A:
 W) phosphorous X) silicon
Y) nitrogen
Z) arsenic
ANSWER: W) PHOSPHOROUS
BONUS
10) CHEMISTRY Short Answer From the lowest to the highest atomic number, give the full names of any 4 alkaline earth metals:
ANSWER: BERYLLIUM; MAGNESIUM; CALCIUM; STRONTIUM; BARIUM; RADIUM
2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4 Page 5
TOSS-UP
11) BIOLOGY Short Answer Which is the more common specific name for the polymorphonuclear (read as: poly-morph-oh-nuclear) leukocyte?
ANSWER: NEUTROPHIL (ACCEPT: PMN)
BONUS
11) BIOLOGY Short Answer Tobacco, jimsonweed, belladonna, and tomatoes all belong to what family of plants?
ANSWER: NIGHTSHADE (ACCEPT: SOLANACEAE)
TOSS-UP
12) ASTRONOMY Short Answer How many degrees above the horizon will the north celestial pole be for someone standing at latitude 53° North?
ANSWER: 53
BONUS
12) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What kind of celestial bodies have cores that consist primarily of neutral particles in a superfluid state and are thought to have evolved from stars with masses more than about 1.4 times the Chandrasekhar limit?
ANSWER: NEUTRON STARS (DO NOT ACCEPT: PULSAR)
 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4 Page 6
TOSS-UP
13) MATH Short Answer What is the formula for the volume of a sphere? ANSWER: 43 πr3 (read as: four third pi radius cubed)
BONUS
13) MATH Short Answer Subtract the following 2 polynomials: (-4x3y+2x3y2 +2x2y3 +2y)–(4x3y–7x3y2 +x2y3 –y)
ANSWER: –8x3y + 9x3y2 + x2y3 + 3y
TOSS-UP
14) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice A measure of how easily water flows through rock is called its:
  W) porosity
X) aquifer system Y) permeability
Z) zone of aeration
ANSWER: Y) PERMEABILITY
BONUS
14) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer In coastal engineering terms, the area from the shoreline to just beyond the breaker zone is called what?
ANSWER: LITTORAL ZONE (ACCEPT: INTERTIDAL ZONE)
2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4 Page 7
TOSS-UP
15) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What ardent behaviorist and author of “Walden Two” believed that human behavior is strongly influenced by what he referred to as operant reinforcement?
ANSWER: B.F. SKINNER (ACCEPT: SKINNER)
BONUS
15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple choice The total amount of sediment a stream can carry past a point in a given amount of time, is known as its:
W) competence X) capacity
Y) abrasion
Z) dissolved load
ANSWER: X) CAPACITY
 TOSS-UP
16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Short Answer In word processing, a collection of letters and associated characters in the same typeface, style and point size is called:
ANSWER: FONT
BONUS
16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple choice A logic chip that is just 20 nanometers wide would be about how many times wider than a single silicon atom?
W) 5 X) 50 Y) 200 Z) 500
ANSWER: Y) 200
2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4
Page 8
TOSS-UP
17) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which physical phenomenon explains the flotation of boats and air balloons:
W) Bernoulli’s principle
X) Archimedes principle
Y) Newton's second law of motion Z) Galileo’s law of displacement
ANSWER: X) ARCHIMEDES PRINCIPLE
BONUS
17) PHYSICS Short Answer A runner, with her feet braced against her starting blocks, accelerates with a horizontal magnitude of 5 meters per second squared. How much horizontal force, in Newtons, must she exert on the blocks to produce this acceleration if the she has a mass of 70 kilograms?
ANSWER: 350 NEWTONS (ACCEPT: 350) (Solution: F=MA; F=70x5; F=350)
TOSS-UP
18) CHEMISTRY Short Answer How many electrons would fill the 4d energy subshell? ANSWER: 10
BONUS
18) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice In which element is the first crossing in the orbital-filling order encountered, whereby the next 2 electrons go into the 4s subshell rather than filling the 3d orbitals?
W) argon
X) scandium Y) rubidium Z) potassium
ANSWER: Z) POTASSIUM
 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4
Page 9
TOSS-UP
19) BIOLOGY Short Answer What section of the brain is sometimes referred to as the body’s thermostat?
ANSWER: HYPOTHALAMUS
BONUS
19) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Removal of a predatory starfish results in an overabundance of mollusks dramatically altering the community population. The starfish would be considered:
W) a keystone species X) primary competitor Y) secondary producer Z) an endangered species
ANSWER: W) A KEYSTONE SPECIES
TOSS-UP
20) MATH Short Answer In statistics, what is the square root of the variance most commonly known as?
ANSWER: STANDARD DEVIATION
BONUS
20) MATH Short Answer To the nearest cubic inch, find the volume of a sphere whose diameter is 4 inches:
ANSWER: 33 (ACCEPT: 32 – 34)
(Solution: V = 4/3 πr3; = 4/3 (3.14)(8); = 33.49)
 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4 Page 10
TOSS-UP
21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice On a topographical map, what are the lines drawn that connect points of the same elevation above or below mean sea level called:
W) isobars X) ridges Y) isohyets Z) contours
ANSWER: Z) CONTOURS
BONUS
21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The abyssal plain of the Atlantic ocean lies directly adjacent to the:
W) continental slope X) continental rise Y) continental shelf Z) continental crust
ANSWER: X) CONTINENTAL RISE
 TOSS-UP
22) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In 1905, on the basis of apparent irregularities in the orbital motion of Neptune that later proved to be incorrect, who predicted the existence of a ninth planet with an orbit beyond Neptune:
W) Percival Lowell
X) Charles Dillon Perrine Y) George Ellery Hale
Z) Johannes Franz Hartman
ANSWER: W) PERCIVAL LOWELL
BONUS
22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What native tree, prized for its wood, which looked like oak, and valued also for its fruit, is now almost extinct in the wild in the US?
ANSWER: AMERICAN CHESTNUT (DO NOT ACCEPT CHESTNUT)
2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4 Page 11
TOSS-UP
23) PHYSICS Short Answer The speed of light in a vacuum divided by the speed of light in a specific material is a way to compute what common optical value:
ANSWER: INDEX OF REFRACTION
BONUS
23) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the potential difference, in volts, if 35 joules of work is needed to move 5 coulombs of charge in a uniform electric field?
ANSWER: 7
(Solution: v = 35/5 = 7 volts)
TOSS-UP
24) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice All elements in a given period of the periodic table have similar:
W) valence-shell electron configuration X) maximum principal quantum number Y) atomic radii
Z) atomic number
ANSWER: X) MAXIMUM PRINCIPAL QUANTUM NUMBER
BONUS
24) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the systematic name for the compound FeCO3? ANSWER: IRON(II) CARBONATE (read as: iron 2 carbonate)
(DO NOT ACCEPT: FERROUS CARBONATE OR IRON CARBONATE)
 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4 Page 12
TOSS-UP
25) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is a feeding structure in arachnids :
W) dentipalps
X) radula
Y) proboscis
Z) chelicerae (read as: chill-iss-err-aye)
ANSWER: Z) CHELICERAE
25) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a cranial bone:
W) parietal X) occipital Y) sphenoid Z) lacrimal
ANSWER: Z) LACRIMAL (Solution: Lacrimal is a facial bone)
BONUS
2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 4
Page 13