ROUND 14 TOSS-UP1) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice The triple point of a substance can be represented in what type of graphical representation:W) Lewis diagramX) phase diagramY) energy diagramZ) time-temperature transformation diagramANSWER: X) PHASE DIAGRAMBONUS1) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Based on the acid dissociation constants of the following acids, order the following 4 acids from the strongest to the weakest in acid strength: HBr; HCl; HF; HIANSWER: HI; HBr; HCl; HFTOSS-UP2) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Color photography and the eventual development of the color television was advanced most directly by:W) Planck’s quantum theory of lightX) Young’s and Helmholtz’s three color theory of light Y) the three color pigment theoryZ) Kichoff’s understanding of the photoelectric effectANSWER: X) YOUNG’S AND HELMHOLTZ’S THREE COLOR THEORY OF LIGHTBONUS2) PHYSICS Short Answer Ignoring friction and assuming g = 9.8 m/s2, how high will a stone reach, in meters rounded to the first decimal place, if launched vertically from rest at 15 m/s?ANSWER: 11.5 METERS 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14 Page 1
TOSS-UP3) BIOLOGY Short Answer Oligodendrocytes are responsible for producing what nerve coating that speeds nerve conduction:ANSWER: MYELIN SHEATH (ACCEPT: MYELIN)BONUS3) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following are mostly under the control of the hypothalamus:W) metabolism, heart rate, sleepX) metabolism, heart rate, ovulation Y) metabolism, heart rate, micturition Z) metabolism, heart rate, balanceANSWER: W) METABOLISM, HEART RATE, SLEEPTOSS-UP4) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice To a stargazer in Ohio, a star far enough south of the celestial equator to be circumpolar such as Miaplacidus is:W) only seen for about 6 hoursX) only seen briefly for about half an hour on the horizon Y) only seen on the winter solsticeZ) never seenANSWER: Z) NEVER SEENBONUS4) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Non-circumpolar stars that lie north of the celestial equator when viewed from Michigan will:W) spend less than 6 hours above the horizonX) spend more than 6 hours but less than 12 hours above the horizon Y) spend more than 12 hours but less than 24 hours above the horizon Z) spend 24 hours above the horizonANSWER: Y) SPEND MORE THAN 12 HOURS BUT LESS THAN 24 HOURS ABOVE THE HORIZON 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14 Page 2
TOSS-UP5) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following trigonometric relationships is TRUE:W) sine θ × cotangent θ = 1 (read θ as theta) X) tangent θ × cotangent θ = 1Y) secantθ–cosineθ=1Z) sineθ+cosecantθ=1ANSWER: X) TANGENT θ × COTANGENT θ = 1BONUS5) MATH Short Answer Given the points, (0, 0) and (–4/5, 3/5), find the distance between them: ANSWER: 1 (ACCEPT: 1 )(Solution: r2 = (x1 – 0)2 + (y1 – 0)2; = (–4/5)2 + (3/5)2; = 1)TOSS-UP6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT classified as an intrusive igneous rock:  W) granite X) diorite Y) rhyolite Z) gabbroANSWER: Y) RHYOLITEBONUS6) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Order the following three types of magma based on their typical percentage of dissolved gas, starting with the lowest: andesitic, basaltic, rhyoliticANSWER: BASALTIC, ANDESITIC, RHYOLITIC2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14 Page 3
TOSS-UP7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The neutralization of the magnetic field around a body by encircling it with a conductor through which a current is maintained is called:W) demodulation X) degaussing Y) debuggingZ) dehissingANSWER: X) DEGAUSSINGBONUS7) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer For his discovery of a new form of radiation in 1895, what person received the first Nobel prize in physics?ANSWER: WILHELM RÖNTGEN (ACCEPT: RÖNTGEN)TOSS-UP8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice In most microprocessors, cache memory built into the microprocessor is what kind of cache: W) L1 X) L2 Y) L3 Z) L4ANSWER: W) L1BONUS8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Short Answer A component of the CPU, what does the acronym ALU stand for?ANSWER: ARITHIMETIC LOGIC UNIT2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14 Page 4
TOSS-UP9) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Of the following, which is the most powerful tool available for the quantitative elemental analysis of metals in solutions:W) potentiometryX) nuclear magnetic resonance spectrometry Y) atomic absorption spectrometryZ) liquid chromatographyANSWER: Y) ATOMIC ABSORPTION SPECTROMETRYBONUS9) CHEMISTRY Short Answer A sodium chloride solution in water has a weight percent of 6%. What mass of solution, in grams, contains 1.5 grams of sodium chloride?ANSWER: 25(Solution: mass = 1.5gNaCl × 100g soln / 6gNaCl; = 25g solution)TOSS-UP10) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following forms of ionizing radiation expends most of its energy over the shortest distance when passing through human tissue: W) alpha particles X) beta particles Y) x-raysZ) gamma particlesANSWER: W) ALPHA PARTICLESBONUS10) PHYSICS Short Answer Consider a sailor off the coast of Cape Cod, Massachusetts. How far from a fog horn, in meters, is the sailor if it takes 5 seconds to hear the horn at 10° C?ANSWER: 1685 (ACCEPT: 1680 TO 1690)(Solution: 0 .6 x 10 = 6 6 + 331 = 337 337 x 5 = 1685 meters)2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14 Page 5
TOSS-UP11) BIOLOGY Short Answer Okazaki (read as: OH-kah-zak-ee) fragments are joined by what specific enzyme?ANSWER: DNA LIGASE (ACCEPT: DNA POLYMERASE I)BONUS11) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Assuming a man has Daltonism and marries a homozygous, normal woman, their children would most likely have which of the following genetic distributions:W) 100% of the females would be carriers and 50% of the males would be carriers X) 100% of the females would be carriers and 100% of the males would be normal Y) 50% of the females would be carriers and all of the males would have Daltonsim Z) both the females and the males would all have DaltonsimANSWER: X) 100% OF THE FEMALES WOULD BE CARRIERS AND 100% OF THE MALES WOULD BE NORMALTOSS-UP12) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice What shape do interstellar dust particles have since the light emitted by stars is dimmed and partially polarized: W) sphere X) cube Y) disk Z) rodlikeANSWER: Z) RODLIKEBONUS12) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What astronomical instrument, used to determine the position of celestial bodies, uses light in parallel rays falling on a mercury surface, which then pass through a prism and into a telescope?ANSWER: PRISMATIC ASTROLABE (ACCEPT: ASTROLABE OR IMPERSONAL ASTROLABE)2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14 Page 6
TOSS-UP13) MATH Multiple Choice For a population of 100 individuals with a normal distribution, how many individuals will be found to fall greater than 1 standard deviation above the mean:W) 12 X) 16 Y) 32 Z) 68ANSWER: X) 16BONUS13) MATH Short Answer Solving for x, find the roots of the following equation: x2 – 2x – 2 = 0 ANSWER: x=1± 3 (ACCEPT: x=1+ 3 AND x=1- 3)TOSS-UP14) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following minerals has a hardness of 7, often has good crystal shape with 6 sides, varies from colorless to white, pink, purple and several other colors, and exhibits conchoidal fracture:    W) quartz X) diamond Y) pyroxene Z) olivineANSWER: W) QUARTZBONUS14) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Calculate the percent relative humidity for air at 70°F containing 10 millibars of water vapor if the saturation vapor pressure is 25.0 millibars at that temperature:ANSWER: 40%(Solution: RH = 10/25 × 100% = 40)2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14 Page 7
TOSS-UP15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In population ecology, which of the following best defines the number of individuals of a species per unit of area:W) population size X) population density Y) biomassZ) cohortANSWER: X) POPULATION DENSITYBONUS15) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Recent studies of Troglodytes indicate they are some of the most sensitive endangered life forms. In what specific environment do Troglodytes typically live?ANSWER: CAVESTOSS-UP16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice In Java, a vector is different from an array in that:W) it is unorderedX) it has no API to support itY) it can store only integersZ) its size does not need to be explicitly declaredANSWER: Z) ITS SIZE DOES NOT NEED TO BE EXPLICITLY DECLAREDBONUS16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following operating systems came first:W) UNIXX) LinuxY) Windows 3.1 Z) OS/2ANSWER: W) UNIX 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14Page 8
TOSS-UP17) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the common name for the following compound: benzene with a methyl group on carbon #1 and a chlorine atom on carbon #2W) chlorotoluene (Pronounced: KLOR-o-tol-you-een) X) o-chlorotolueneY) p-chlorotolueneZ) m-chlorotolueneANSWER: X) o-CHLOROTOLUENEBONUS17) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the oxidation number of the sulfur atom in H2SO4? ANSWER: +6 (ACCEPT: 6)(Solution: 2(+1) + S + 4(-2) = 0; S = +6)TOSS-UP18) PHYSICS Multiple Choice If e is energy, f is frequency, and h is Planck’s constant, which of the following is NOT possible according to Planck’s quantum hypothesis: W) e=hf X) e=0.5hf Y) e=1hf Z) e=2hfANSWER: X) E = 0.5 HFBONUS18) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Einstein proposed that the photoelectric effect was a test for which of the following:W) the wave nature of lightX) that light traveled a constant speed in a vacuum Y) the photon theory of lightZ) the wave particle duality of lightANSWER: Y) THE PHOTON THEORY OF LIGHT2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14Page 9
TOSS-UP19) BIOLOGY Short Answer Give the common chemical name for where new bases are added to a DNA strand:ANSWER: 3 PRIME HYDROXYL (ACCEPT: 3 PRIME END)BONUS19) BIOLOGY Short Answer Which one of the following 5 intermediates of the citric acid cycle is considered a 6 carbon intermediate: citric acid, oxaloacetic acid, succinic acid, alpha ketogluteric acid, fumaric aciddANSWER: CITRIC ACIDTOSS-UP20) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following is not a characteristic of the terrestrial planets:W) low average density X) closely spaced orbits Y) craters in old surfaces Z) very few moonsANSWER: W) LOW AVERAGE DENSITYBONUS20) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of Kepler’s works in astronomy:W) Kepler gathered most of his data from his monitoring of the planets with a quadrantX) Kepler very seldom observed the planets and looked through a telescope only a few times in his lifeY) many of Kepler’s computations were based on data gathered by Tycho BraheZ) Kepler assumed planetary motion was not circularANSWER: W) KEPLER GATHERED MOST OF HIS DATA FROM HIS MONITORING OF THE PLANETS WITH A QUADRANT 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14 Page 10
TOSS-UP21) MATH Short Answer Find sin 2θ (read as: sine 2 theta) given that tan θ (read as: tangent theta) equals minus three-fourths and θ is in the second quadrant:ANSWER: – 24 25(Solution: sin θ = 3/5; cos θ = -4/5; sin 2θ = 2 sin θ cos θ; = 2(3/5)(-4/5) = -24/25)BONUS21) MATH Short Answer Find the solution set of the following equation: x2 + 6x + 6 = 0 ANSWER:-3± 3TOSS-UP22) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In keeping with developments in the science of physics, Freud incorporated which of the following into his personality theory:W) relativityX) quantum theoryY) conservation of energyZ) entropy constantly increasesANSWER: Y) CONSERVATION OF ENERGYBONUS22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Which of the following 5 metals has the lowest thermal conductivity: iron; lead; tin; magnesium; zincANSWER: LEAD(Solution: iron – 80.2; lead - 35.3; tin – 66.6; magnesium - 156; zinc – 116)   2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is a naturally occurring amino acid that is NOT found in proteins?W) threonine (read as: three-oh-neen) X) histidineY) ornithine (read as: oar-nih-thine) Z) isoleucineANSWER: Y) ORNITHINEBONUS23) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Which two of the following 5 amino acids contain nonpolar R groups? valine, lysine, arginine, alanine, histidineANSWER: V ALINE, ALANINETOSS-UP24) PHYSICS Short Answer If the Earth was the same mass but half its present diameter, by what multiple, to the first decimal place, would escape velocity increase?ANSWER: 1.4BONUS24) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the energy used in Kilowatt–hours if a current of 2 amps flows though a circuit whose resistance is 5 ohms for one hour?ANSWER: 0.020 (ACCEPT: 0.020 KILOWATT – HOURS) (Solution: W = (2A)2 × 5 ohms × 1 hr = .020 Kilowatt-hours) 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14 Page 12
TOSS-UP25) BIOLOGY Short Answer What common organic molecule has a hydrocarbon phytol tail and a multi-ring structure with a magnesium metal ion in the center?ANSWER: CHLOROPHYLL (ACCEPT: ANY CHLOROPHYLL)BONUS25) BIOLOGY Short Answer Order the following 3 monosaccharides from the smallest to the largest: xylose, threose, glyceraldehydeANSWER: GLYCERALDEHYDE, THREOSE, XYLOSE2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 14 Page 13