ROUND 13 TOSS-UP1) BIOLOGY Short Answer Which of the human plasma proteins plays the greatest role in osmoregulation?ANSWER: ALBUMINBONUS1) BIOLOGY Short Answer Which 2 of the following 5 genera of organisms are not Monerans? Leishmania, (read: LIE-shh-mania), Rickettsia, Neisseria, (read: NYE-sear-e-ah) Echinococcus,(read: E-kine-o-coccus), Klebsiella (read as: KLEB-see-ella) ANSWER: LEISHMANIA, ECHINOCOCCUSTOSS-UP2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice In the typical titration of a weak acid, such as 0.1 molar acetic acid, with a strong base, such as 0.1 molar sodium hydroxide, what is the best description of the characteristic titration curve:W) at the equivalence point, the pH is primarily controlled by the acetate ion X) at the equivalence point, the pH drops dramaticallyY) the second equivalence point is primarily controlled by the hydroxide ion Z) the pH at the equivalence point is almost always 7ANSWER: W) AT THE EQUIVALENCE POINT, THE PH IS PRIMARILY CONTROLLED BY THE ACETATE IONBONUS2) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Calculate the density, in grams per liter, of diatomic helium gas at 100K and at a pressure of 2 atmospheres:ANSWER: 2(Solution: n/V = P/RT; = 2atm/(0.08L.atm/m.K)(100K); = .25m/L; (.25m/L)(8g/m)=2gHe2/L)) 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13 Page 1
TOSS-UP3) PHYSICS Short Answer If 8 coulombs of charge pass through a conductor in 1⁄2 second, how many amperes did the conductor carry?ANSWER: 16 AMPERESBONUS3) PHYSICS Short Answer Assuming the velocity of light is 300,000 kilometers per second in a vacuum, what is the velocity of light, in kilometers/sec, in a transparent substance with a refractive index of 1.25?ANSWER: 240,000 (ACCEPT: 240,000 Km/sec) (Solution: Vm=V0÷n; 300,000÷1.25 = 240,000 Km/sec)TOSS-UP4) ASTRONOMY Short Answer Tripling the distance to a star will typically reduce its apparent brightness by about how many times?ANSWER: 9BONUS4) ASTRONOMY Short Answer Assuming that the Hubble constant = 40 km/sec/megaparsec, how far away, in megaparsecs, is a galaxy whose red shift is 20,000 km/sec?ANSWER: 500 MEGAPARSECS (Solution: d = v/H0; = 20,000/40 = 500) 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13 Page 2
TOSS-UP5) MATH Multiple Choice If one considers the distribution of the means of 5 groups, such a distribution is most accurately referred to as a:W) sample distribution X) sampling distribution Y) composite distribution Z) population distributionANSWER: X) SAMPLING DISTRIBUTIONBONUS5) MATH Short Answer If the area of a right triangle ABC is 6 and leg BC is one-third the length of leg AB, what is the length of AB?ANSWER: 6(Solution: A=1⁄2bh; 6=1⁄2(x)(3x); =2; 3×2=6)TOSS-UP6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is responsible for the changing of the seasons:W) the Earth's axis is not perpendicular to the ecliptic X) the Earth's orbit is ellipticalY) the Earth's axis precessesZ) the Sun moves through spaceANSWER: W) THE EARTH'S AXIS IS NOT PERPENDICULAR TO THE ECLIPTICBONUS6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following surfaces would exhibit the highest albedo:W) bare rockX) an ocean at sunrise Y) an ocean at sunset Z) an ice fieldANSWER: Z) AN ICE FIELD 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13Page 3
TOSS-UP7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The profundal zone of a lake is the:W) bottom of the lakeX) area between the shore and water extending to a depth of about 10 meters Y) upper layer below which the temperature dropsZ) deeper part where light does not penetrateANSWER: Z) DEEPER PART WHERE LIGHT DOES NOT PENETRATEBONUS7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following chemicals is most predominant in chocolate:W) tyrosineX) theophylline Y) theobromine Z) caffeineANSWER: Y) THEOBROMINE TOSS-UP8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice One of the ways to start a computer running Windows 95 or 98 in Safe Mode is to:W) press control and F1 key at any timeX) restart and hold the Escape keyY) press Control + Alt + Delete key at the same time Z) restart and hold down F5 keyANSWER: Z) RESTART AND HOLD DOWN F5 KEYBONUS8) COMPUTER SCIENCE Short Answer Give the Binary, Octal, and Hexadecimal equivalents for the decimal number 9:ANSWER: BINARY = 1001; OCTAL = 11; HEXADECIMAL = 92002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13 Page 4
TOSS-UP9) BIOLOGY Short Answer When biologists use bacterial conjugation to map genomes, what electrical appliance is most often used to interrupt conjugation?ANSWER: BLENDER (ACCEPT: KITCHEN BLENDER)BONUS9) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the most accurate name for a molecule of glycerol with all three hydroxyl groups esterified to fatty acids :W) triacylglycerol (read as: tri-acyl-gliss-er-ol) X) fatty glycerolY) esterified lipidZ) triesterglyceride (read as: tri-ester-gliss-er-ide)ANSWER: W) TRIACYLGLYCEROLTOSS-UP10) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is incorrect: W) C5H11CHO is an aldehyde X) C11H20 is an alkaneY) C5H11OH is an alcoholZ) C5H11NH2 is an amineANSWER: X) C11H20 IS AN ALKANE10) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Order the following 4 ionic solids in terms of their lattice energies, going from the highest to the lowest: LiF; MgI2; KF; NaFANSWER: MgI2; LiF; NaF; KFBONUS2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13 Page 5
TOSS-UP11) PHYSICS Short Answer Murray Gell-Mann coined the name of these point-like entities that make up hadrons from a novel by James Joyce:ANSWER: QUARKSBONUS11) PHYSICS Short Answer To the nearest meter per second, what is the speed of sound in air if the temperature of the air is 15°C?ANSWER: 340 (ACCEPT: 341 METERS PER SECOND)(Solution: add 0.6 meters/sec to 331 or 332 m/sec for each increase in 1°C above 0oC) 12) ASTRONOMY Multiple ChoiceW) isotropic and homogeneousX) isotropic and non-homogeneous Y) anistotropic and homogeneousZ) anisotropic and non-homogeneousTOSS-UPMost astrophysicists believe that the universe is:ANSWER: W) ISOTROPIC AND HOMOGENEOUSBONUS12) ASTRONOMY Short Answer Of the following 5 planets, name all that can be in opposition to the Sun: Venus, Saturn, Mercury, Mars, JupiterANSWER: SATURN, MARS, AND JUPITER (accept in any order) (Solution: Only superior planets can be in opposition)2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13 Page 6
TOSS-UP13) MATH Short Answer Who was the first person known to have proved that the number of primes is infinite, calling them “numbers measured by no number but a unit alone”?ANSWER: EUCLIDBONUS13) MATH Short Answer A circle has a diameter of 20 and a minor arc whose interior angle is 90°. In terms of π, what is the arc length?ANSWER: 5π(Solution: arc length = (90°/360°)(2πr); = 1⁄4 (20)π; = 5π)TOSS-UP14) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following best approximates the relative humidity in the stratosphere: W) 1% X) 10% Y) 35% Z) 50%ANSWER: W) 1%14) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Name the 3 cloud families based on their shape: ANSWER: CUMULUS, STRATUS, CIRRUS (in any order)BONUS2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13Page 7
TOSS-UP15) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer According to Aristotle, the celestial bodies are made of what fifth element?ANSWER: ETHERBONUS15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice If you wanted to see the detailed internal structures of living unstained organisms, which type of microscope would you use:W) bright-fieldX) dark-fieldY) phase-contrastZ) scanning-tunnelingANSWER: Y) PHASE-CONTRAST TOSS-UP16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice In workflow modeling, which of the following is NOT part of the ACID properties of transactions:W) AtomicityX) Consistency Preservation Y) InvertibilityZ) DurabilityANSWER: Y) INVERTIBLITY (Solution: I = Isolation)BONUS16) COMPUTER SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a storage class specification in C programming:W) auto X) switch Y) register Z) staticANSWER: X) SWITCH2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13Page 8
TOSS-UP17) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following would be LEAST likely to diffuse through a typical plasma membrane:W) propaneX) methanolY) potassium ions Z) carbon dioxideANSWER: Y) POTASSIUM IONSBONUS17) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In which of the following cell types does phosphocreatine provide the greatest role:W) hepatocyteX) parafollicular cellY) endothelial cellZ) a skeletal muscle cellANSWER: Z) A SKELETAL MUSCLE CELLTOSS-UP18) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice An aldehyde is a class of compounds that contains a carbonyl group bonded to:W) 2 carbon atomsX) one or more hydrogen atoms Y) one or more nitrogen atoms Z) 2 sulfur atomsANSWER: X) ONE OR MORE HYDROGEN ATOMSBONUS18) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Order the following three lipids from lowest to highest melting points: lauric acid, myristic acid, palmitic acidANSWER: LAURIC ACID, MYRISTIC ACID, PALMITIC ACID 2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13 Page 9
TOSS-UP19) PHYSICS Short Answer A jet traveling at 800 kilometers per hour has how many more times the kinetic energy than the same jet traveling at 1⁄2 that speed?ANSWER: 4 TIMESBONUS19) PHYSICS Short Answer What color would be produced when mixing magenta and cyan pigments?ANSWER: BLUE20) ASTRONOMY Multiple choice against a dark sky:W) Mars X) Venus Y) Mercury Z) JupiterANSWER: Y) MERCURYTOSS-UPWhat planet is usually obscured by the sun and never seen BONUS20) ASTRONOMY Multiple choice In which of the following illustrative techniques would sunspots occur nearer the solar equator as the cycle of sunspot activity progresses:W) Kirkwood’s chart X) Maunder’s diagram Y) Hubble’s chartZ) HR diagramANSWER: X) MAUNDER’S DIAGRAM2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13Page 10
TOSS-UP21) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true about statistical correlation:W) correlation typically distinguishes between explanatory and response variables X) the correlation “r” always lies between +1 and -1Y) a negative correlation indicates a negative associationZ) correlation is usually strongly affected by outlying observationsANSWER: W) CORRELATION TYPICALLY DISTINGUISHES BETWEEN EXPLANATORY AND RESPONSE VARIABLESBONUS21) MATH Short Answer What is the sine of the angle θ (pronounced: theta) whose terminal side passes through the points (4, -3)?ANSWER: -3/5 (ACCEPT: -0.6)(Solution: first find r = (42 + 32)1/2 = 5; sin θ = y/r; = -3/5)TOSS-UP22) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice In meteorology, a center where air spirals inward around a low-pressure center and designated on weather maps by the letter “L” is called: W) a center of divergence X) coriolis inversionY) gradient windZ) cyclonic flowANSWER: Z) CYCLONIC FLOWBONUS22) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer In order and starting with the highest, name the 3 boundaries that separate the 4 thermal layers in the Earth’s atmosphere:ANSWER: MESOPAUSE, STRATOPAUSE, TROPOPAUSE2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) BIOLOGY Short Answer If one parent has an AB blood type and the other parent has an O blood type, what blood types will the children possibly inherit?ANSWER: A AND B (DO NOT ACCEPT: AB)BONUS23) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Southern blot is to DNA sequences as Northern blot is to:W) amino acid sequencesX) RNA sequencesY) DNA sequencesZ) hybrid DNA/RNA sequencesANSWER: X) RNA SEQUENCES TOSS-UP24) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice The starch amylopectin is:W) unbranched with alpha 1,6 linkages between the monomers X) highly branched with alpha 1,4 linkages at its branch points Y) highly branched with alpha 1,6 linkages at its branch points Z) unbranched with alpha 1,4 linkages between the monomersANSWER: Y) HIGHLY BRANCHED WITH ALPHA 1,6 LINKAGES AT ITS BRANCH POINTSBONUS24) CHEMISTRY Short Answer In the following reaction, H2 + Cl2 → 2HCl, assume the bond dissociation of H2 is 430 kilojoules per mole, of Cl2 is 240 kilojoules per mole, and of HCl is 400 kilojoules per mole. What is the standard enthalpy change, or ∆H°, (read as: delta H degree) for the reaction, in kilojoules:ANSWER: -130(Solution: ∆H° = (DH-H + DCl-Cl) – (2DHCl); = (430 + 240) – 800; = -130kJ)2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13 Page 12
TOSS-UP25) PHYSICS Short Answer What are the four most common names for the four fundamental forces of nature:ANSWER: GRAVITATION, ELECTROMAGNETISM, STRONG, WEAKBONUS25) PHYSICS Short Answer If a race car driver fully engages the brakes of his car traveling at 150 kilometers per hour, how many times farther will the car skid than if it was traveling at 50 kilometers per hour when the brakes were engaged?ANSWER: 9 TIMES2002 Regional Science Bowl B Round 13 Page 13