ROUND 2A          TOSS-UP1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which scientist is credited with discovering cells?W) Charles DarwinX) Anton van Leeuwenhoek [LAY-vuhn-hook] Y) Robert HookeZ) Francis CrickANSWER: Y) ROBERT HOOKEBONUS1) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What outer structure possessed by plant cells protects them from environmental changes and helps them maintain their shape during stress and times of water loss?ANSWER: CELL WALL _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The electron volt is a measure of which of the following?  W) Energy X) Inertia Y) Power Z) ChargeANSWER: W) ENERGYBONUS2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term given to the result of adding multiple waves together?ANSWER: SUPERPOSITIONMiddle School Round 2A Page 1TOSS-UP3) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following energy sources produces the greatest carbon dioxide emissions?W) WindX) CoalY) NuclearZ) GeothermalANSWER: X) COALBONUS3) ENERGY Multiple Choice In the coming years, most of the increases in U.S. natural gas production is expected to come from hydraulic fracturing in which type of sedimentary rock?W) Sandstone X) Limestone Y) ShaleZ) GypsumANSWER: Y) SHALE _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP4) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following atmospheric layers contains the ozone layer?W) Mesosphere X) Thermosphere Y) Stratosphere Z) TroposphereANSWER: Y) STRATOSPHEREBONUS4) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following organelles is full of digestive enzymes?W) Central vacuole [VAK-yoo-ohl]X) Endoplasmic reticulum [EN-duh-plaz-mik ri-TIK-yuh-luhm] Y) Lysosome [LY-suh-sohm]Z) Golgi apparatusANSWER: Y) LYSOSOMEMiddle School Round 2APage 2TOSS-UP5) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The wavelength of an ocean wave is defined by which of the following?W) The distance from crest to troughX) The height of the wave from crest to trough Y) The height change from trough to trough Z) The distance between crestsANSWER: Z) THE DISTANCE BETWEEN CRESTSBONUS5) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Which class of star cluster is most spherical in shape? ANSWER: GLOBULAR CLUSTERS           _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following pairs of angles is supplementary?W) 44o and 126o X) 75o and 105o Y) 65o and 25o Z) 36o and 54oANSWER: X) 75o AND 105oBONUS6) MATH Short Answer Use the distributive property to rewrite the following expression: 6t(4s - 3t + 7) [6t times the quantity 4s minus 3t plus 7].ANSWER: 24ts - 18t2 + 42t (ACCEPT: 24st - 18t2 + 42t)Middle School Round 2A Page 3TOSS-UP7) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following animals feeds by standing on its head and kicking food in its mouth?W) Limpet X) Barnacle Y) Sea star Z) CrabANSWER: X) BARNACLEBONUS7) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer In a marine environment, what name is given to the collective group of organisms that serve as primary producers?ANSWER: PHYTOPLANKTON _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The smallest particle that maintains the chemical properties of a compound is called which of the following?W) A molecule X) An isotope Y) A protonZ) An atomANSWER: W) A MOLECULEBONUS8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer How far will an object travel, in meters, if it is moving at 30 meters per second for 20 seconds?ANSWER: 600Middle School Round 2A Page 4TOSS-UP9) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes the overall process of meiosis [my-OH-sis]?W) One parent cell produces two daughter cells X) One parent cell produces four daughter cells Y) Two parent cells produce one daughter cell Z) Two parent cells produce two daughter cellsANSWER: X) ONE PARENT CELL PRODUCES FOUR DAUGHTER CELLSBONUS9) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Carbon has three isotopes: carbon-12, carbon-13, and carbon-14. How many protons are in the nucleus [NOO-klee-uhs] of these carbon atoms, respectively?ANSWER: 6, 6, 6 (ACCEPT: 6 IN ALL 3) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following does NOT increase ocean wave height?W) Increasing wind speedX) Longer periods of sustained windsY) Increased distance over which the wind blows the water Z) Irregular water depthANSWER: Z) IRREGULAR WATER DEPTHBONUS10) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Temperature increases with height in the stratosphere due to the absorption of UV energy by what molecule?ANSWER: OZONEMiddle School Round 2A Page 5TOSS-UP11) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following fractions is the SMALLEST?W) 5/10 X) 3/7 Y) 3/8 Z) 4/9ANSWER: Y) 3/8BONUS11) MATH Short Answer Find the height of a right triangle whose area and base are 10 and 5, respectively.ANSWER: 4_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP12) ENERGY Short Answer Which molecule is used for energy transfer and storage inside cells?ANSWER: ATP (ACCEPT: ADENOSINE TRIPHOSPHATE)BONUS12) ENERGY Multiple Choice Destruction of Earth’s ozone layer is expected to increase the incidence of all but which of the following?W) DiabetesX) Skin cancers Y) CataractsZ) Skin agingANSWER: W) DIABETESMiddle School Round 2APage 6TOSS-UP13) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following groups are all invertebrates?W) Snails, bats, fish, and earthwormsX) Snails, honeybees, sea star, and sea spongesY) Grasshoppers, fruit flies, electric eels, and sea horses Z) Cows, pigs, horses, and chickensANSWER: X) SNAILS, HONEYBEES, SEA STAR, AND SEA SPONGESBONUS13) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following terms is used by microbiologists to describe a bacterium with a rod shape?W) Coccus [KOK-uhs]X) Bacillus [buh-SIL-uhs]Y) Spirochete [SPY-ruh-keet] Z) HelicalANSWER: X) BACILLUS _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP14) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following subatomic particles are charged?W) Only electronsX) Electrons and neutronsY) Electrons and protonsZ) Electrons, neutrons, and protonsANSWER: Y) ELECTRONS AND PROTONSBONUS14) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What are the reactants in the equation: NaOH + HCl → H2O + NaCl?ANSWER: NaOH, HCl (ACCEPT: SODIUM HYDROXIDE, HYDROGEN CHLORIDE OR HYDROCHLORIC ACID)Middle School Round 2APage 7TOSS-UP15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What era are we currently living in?W) Mesozoic X) Paleozoic Y) Proterozoic Z) CenozoicANSWER: Z) CENOZOICBONUS15) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer In an aquatic system, what are the TWO major microbial producers?ANSWER: ALGAE AND PHYTOPLANKTON _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following gases is being captured at landfills and used as a fuel?W) Methylene [METH-uh-leen] X) Molecular hydrogenY) Hydrogen sulfideZ) MethaneANSWER: Z) METHANEBONUS16) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which country is expected to have the largest shale gas reserves in the world?W) United States X) NorwayY) ChinaZ) BrazilANSWER: Y) CHINAMiddle School Round 2APage 8TOSS-UP17) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Where do the charged particles that strike the Earth's atmosphere near the poles and cause the northern lights, or aurora, originate?ANSWER: THE SUN (ACCEPT: SOLAR WIND)BONUS17) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice A Keplerian [kep-LEER-ee-uhn] orbit is a description of an orbiting body considering the gravitational interaction of two point masses. Which of the following is NOT a Keplerian orbit?W) EllipseX) ParabolaY) CircleZ) Reuleaux curve [roo-LOH]ANSWER: Z) REULEAUX CURVE _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP18) MATH Multiple Choice All vertices of a triangle are within quadrant 3. If the triangle is rotated clockwise about the origin 180 degrees, in which quadrant will the new triangle be located?W) Quadrant I X) Quadrant II Y) Quadrant III Z) Quadrant IVANSWER: W) QUADRANT I18) MATH Short Answer Convert 2 1/8 to a decimal and to a percent. ANSWER: 2.125 AND 212.5%BONUSMiddle School Round 2APage 9TOSS-UP19) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer A dinoflagellate [din-uh-FLAJ-uh-layt] is responsible for what phenomenon, which ultimately kills fish?ANSWER: RED TIDE (ACCEPT: HARMFUL ALGAL BLOOM; HAB)BONUS19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the primary feeding pattern for Cnidarians [ny-DAIR-ee-uhns]?W) Piscivores [PI-si-vohrs]X) Herbivores [HUR-buh-vohrs] Y) ScavengersZ) CarnivoresANSWER: Z) CARNIVORES _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What makes a material a good insulator?W) Having electrons that are bound and cannot move completely away from their nucleus[NOO-klee-uhs]X) Having a nucleus that contains a number of positively charged protons Y) Having electrons that are farther away from the nucleusZ) Having electrons that can drift awayANSWER: W) HAVING ELECTRONS THAT ARE BOUND AND CANNOT MOVE COMPLETELY AWAY FROM THEIR NUCLEUSBONUS20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In general terms, an electric generator converts which of the following?W) Mechanical energy to electrical energy X) Mechanical energy to heatY) Heat to electrical energyZ) Chemical energy to mechanical energyANSWER: W) MECHANICAL ENERGY TO ELECTRICAL ENERGYMiddle School Round 2APage 10TOSS-UP21) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of vascular tissue in plants?W) ChloroplastsX) Xylem [ZY-luhm]Y) Cotyledon [kat-uhl-EED-uhn] Z) StomataANSWER: X) XYLEMBONUS21) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Put the following four in order from LEAST to MOST complex: 1) organs, 2) molecules, 3) tissues, 4) cells.ANSWER: MOLECULES, CELLS, TISSUES, AND ORGANS (ACCEPT: 2, 4, 3, 1) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP22) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the main mechanism of marine transport of most terrigenous [te-RIJ-uh-nuhs] sediments?ANSWER: GRAVITYBONUS22) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The part of a sea, lake, or river that is close to the shore is called which of the following?W) Littoral zone X) Riparian zone Y) WetlandZ) MarshANSWER: W) LITTORAL ZONEMiddle School Round 2APage 11TOSS-UP23) MATH Short Answer John's height is 0.23 meters less than Mike's height. Given that Mike's height is 1.88 meters, what is John's height in meters?ANSWER: 1.65BONUS23) MATH Short Answer What length of packing tape, in inches, is needed to wrap 3 times around a circular mirror with a radius of 8 inches?ANSWER: 48πMiddle School Round 2A Page 12