ROUND 1 A
          TOSS-UP
1) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer In plants and animals, what class of nucleic acid polymer is the primary form of genetic material that is heritable from one generation to the next?
ANSWER: DEOXYRIBOSE NUCLEIC ACIDS (ACCEPT: DNA)
BONUS
1) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What part of the pistil forms a closed receptacle for the ovules?
W) Carpel X) Petal
Y) Sepal
Z) Peduncle
ANSWER: W) CARPEL _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
2) MATH Multiple Choice Identify the 21st term of the arithmetic sequence with first three terms 5, 10, 15.
W) 100 X) 105 Y) 110 Z) 125
ANSWER: X) 105
BONUS
2) MATH Short Answer There are 5 different paths through a maze designated as Path 1, Path 2, Path 3, Path 4, and Path 5. Each path is equally likely to be chosen. What is the percent probability of NOT choosing Path 1?
ANSWER: 80%
Middle School Round 1A Page 1
TOSS-UP
3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following does NOT represent a chemical reaction?
W) Water falling from a tap
X) Grape juice turning into wine Y) Milk turning to cheese
Z) Rust forming on a nail
ANSWER: W) WATER FALLING FROM A TAP
BONUS
3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Thomas Edison championed the use of direct current for homes and industry. Who favored the use of alternating current because of its ability to be transmitted great distances?
ANSWER: NIKOLA TESLA (ACCEPT: TESLA, GEORGE WESTINGHOUSE, or WESTINGHOUSE)
           _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
4) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the common name of the members of the class Aves? ANSWER: BIRDS
BONUS
4) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following organisms were the earliest life forms to evolve in the ocean?
W) Protozoa [proh-tuh-ZOH-uh] X) Algae
Y) Bacteria
Z) Fungi
ANSWER: Y) BACTERIA
Middle School Round 1A
Page 2
TOSS-UP
5) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Ocean waves are created by which of the following?
W) Wind
X) Shape of the ocean floor Y) Water depth
Z) Currents
ANSWER: W) WIND
6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following are NOT found in both prokaryotes [proh-KAR-ee-ohts] and eukaryotes [yoo-KAR-ee-ohts]?
W) Flagella
X) Ribosomes [RY-buh-sohms]
Y) Mitochondria [my-tuh-KON-dree-uh] Z) Plasma membrane
ANSWER: Y) MITOCHONDRIA
BONUS
5) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What type of earthquakes occurring on the island of Hawaii are a result of magma movement underneath Kilauea [kee-lou-AY-ah]?
ANSWER: HARMONIC TREMORS (ACCEPT: VOLCANIC TREMORS)

TOSS-UP
6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Sand dollars, sea stars, sea cucumbers, and sea urchins all belong to what phylum [FY-luhm]?
ANSWER: ECHINODERMATA
BONUS
Middle School Round 1A
Page 3
TOSS-UP
7) MATH Multiple Choice Assuming that the Earth is a sphere of radius r, what is the surface area of the Northern hemisphere?
W) 2/3�r3 X) 2�r2 Y) 3�r2 Z) 4�r2
ANSWER: X) 2�r2
7) MATH Short Answer How many positive integers are between �3 and�82?
ANSWER: 8
_______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
8) ENERGY Short Answer Coal and natural gas are the leading sources of fuel for electricity production in the U.S. What is the third leading source?
ANSWER: NUCLEAR
BONUS
8) ENERGY Multiple Choice In most geothermal applications, what substance is used to rotate the generation turbines?
W) Liquid water X) Natural gas Y) Brine
Z) Steam
ANSWER: Z) STEAM
BONUS
  Middle School Round 1A
Page 4
TOSS-UP
9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following materials best prevents the flow of electricity?
W) Copper
X) Silicon
Y) Gold
Z) Distilled water
ANSWER: Z) DISTILLED WATER
BONUS
9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In the periodic table, elements are arranged by which of the following?
W) Atomic number
X) Binding energy
Y) Mass number
Z) Number of isotopes
ANSWER: W) ATOMIC NUMBER _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
10) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following has the function of modifying, sorting, and preparing substances for use within the eukaryotic [yoo-KAR-ee-oh-tik] cell or for transport outside of the cell?
W) Ribosome [RY-buh-sohm]
X) Endoplasmic reticulum [EN-duh-plaz-mik ri-TIK-yuh-luhm] Y) Golgi apparatus
Z) Mitochondria [my-tuh-KON-dree-uh]
ANSWER: Y) GOLGI APPARATUS
BONUS
10) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following marine organisms would be considered ectothermic?
W) Gull
X) Penguin Y) Sea turtle Z) Manatee
ANSWER: Y) SEA TURTLE
Middle School Round 1A
Page 5
TOSS-UP
11) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice In the deep ocean, the continuous shower of mostly organic detritus falling from the upper layers of the water column is called which of the following?
W) Marine snow X) Fecal snow Y) Organic snow Z) Carbon snow
ANSWER: W) MARINE SNOW
BONUS
11) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT considered a rift valley?
W) Mid-ocean ridges
X) Rhine River Valley
Y) Red Sea
Z) Mississippi River Valley
ANSWER: Z) MISSISSIPPI RIVER VALLEY _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
12) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer You are setting up an experiment looking at the effects of increased phosphorus concentrations on the growth of Glycine [GLY-seen] max. In this experiment, the concentration of phosphorus is what kind of variable?
ANSWER: INDEPENDENT
BONUS
12) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following BEST describes a hypothesis?
W) The process of investigating a question
X) A possible explanation based on prior evidence Y) A widely accepted explanation
Z) An observation
ANSWER: X) A POSSIBLE EXPLANATION BASED ON PRIOR EVIDENCE
Middle School Round 1A
Page 6
TOSS-UP
13) MATH Multiple Choice What is the standard form of the following equation: 2x = 3y - 5?
W) 2x - 3y = 5
X) 2x - 5 = 3y
Y) 2x + 3y = 5
Z) 2x - 3y = -5
ANSWER: Z) 2x - 3y = -5

BONUS
13) MATH Short Answer How many parallel pairs of faces does a right regular hexagonal prism have?
ANSWER: 4
_______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
14) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice An atom's ability to react with other atoms is determined by what type of subatomic particle?
W) Protons X) Neutrinos Y) Neutrons Z) Electrons
ANSWER: Z) ELECTRONS
BONUS
14) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The atomic weight (in amu) of an element most nearly reflects the atom's total number of which of the following?
W) Protons and neutrons X) Protons and electrons Y) Neutrons only
Z) Protons only
ANSWER: W) PROTONS AND NEUTRONS
Middle School Round 1A
Page 7
TOSS-UP
15) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which part of the plant would you expect to find the largest concentration of photosynthetic pigments?
W) Roots X) Shoots Y) Leaves Z) Fruit
ANSWER: Y) LEAVES

BONUS
15) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the vector for the organism that causes malaria?
ANSWER: MOSQUITO (ACCEPT: ANOPHELES)
TOSS-UP
16) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The hardness of a mineral determines how resistant it is to which of the following?
W) Mass loading
X) Fracture
Y) Scratching
Z) Temperature flux
ANSWER: Y) SCRATCHING
BONUS
16) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The early atmosphere of the Earth probably was rich in all EXCEPT which of the following gases?
W) Oxygen
X) Carbon monoxide Y) Carbon dioxide Z) Nitrogen
ANSWER: W) OXYGEN
Middle School Round 1A
Page 8
TOSS-UP
17) ENERGY Multiple Choice DC/DC converters operate on the principle of volt-second balance. Based on this assumption, which of the following average values is zero?
W) Voltage across the inductor(s) X) Voltage across the capacitor(s) Y) Voltage across the load(s)
Z) Voltage across the transistor(s)
ANSWER: W) VOLTAGE ACROSS THE INDUCTOR(S)
BONUS
17) ENERGY Short Answer What is thought to be driving the rapid (and accelerating) expansion of the universe, while accounting for nearly three-quarters of the mass and energy that exists in the universe?
ANSWER: DARK ENERGY (DO NOT ACCEPT: DARK MATTER) _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
18) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Which group of plants enclose their seeds within a fruit? ANSWER: ANGIOSPERMS
BONUS
18) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Atopic dermatitis is a medical condition predominantly affecting which organ system?
W) Hepatobiliary [hep-uht-oh-BIL-er-ee]
X) Integumentary [in-teg-yuh-MEN-tuh-ree] Y) Skeletal
Z) Circulatory
ANSWER: X) INTEGUMENTRY
Middle School Round 1A
Page 9
TOSS-UP
19) MATH Short Answer Mike buys hot dogs that come in packages of 10. If hot dog buns come in packages of 8, what is the fewest number of hot dog packages he can buy in order have the same number of hot dogs as buns?
ANSWER: 4
BONUS
19) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following conditions is NOT used for similarity of two triangles?
W) SSS [side, side, side]
X) AAA [angle, angle, angle] Y) SSA [side, side, angle] Z) SAS [side, angle, side]
ANSWER: Y) SSA _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice According to the Richter scale, which of the following is closest to the ratio of the energy released in a magnitude 10 earthquake to that released in a magnitude 8 earthquake?
W) 10 X) 20 Y) 100 Z) 1000
ANSWER: Z) 1000
BONUS
20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Atoms of which of these elements tend to form three covalent bonds?
W) Carbon X) Nitrogen Y) Oxygen Z) Chlorine
ANSWER: X) NITROGEN
Middle School Round 1A
Page 10
TOSS-UP
21) ENERGY Short Answer Ozone is an important gas in the stratosphere. What is the chemical formula of ozone?
ANSWER: O3
BONUS
21) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following rates, referring to costs for peak hour cost versus off-peak hour cost, respectively, would most incentivize a homeowner for running their large appliances during off-peak hours rather than peak hours?
W) $2 per kilowatt and $0.10 per kilowatt hour X) $1 per kilowatt and $0.10 per kilowatt hour Y) $1 per kilowatt and $0.12 per kilowatt hour Z) $3 per kilowatt and $0.10 per kilowatt hour
ANSWER: Z) $3 PER KILOWATT AND $0.10 PER KILOWATT HOUR _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
22) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer In what organelle of a plant cell does photosynthesis occur? ANSWER: CHLOROPLAST
BONUS
22) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice In addition to being birds, what do the Great Auk, moa, passenger pigeon, and Carolina parakeet have in common?
W) They are all listed as invasive species in North America
X) They are all extinct
Y) They are all listed as threatened species in their native habitats
Z) They are all being raised in captive breeding programs for later release into the wild
ANSWER: X) THEY ARE ALL EXTINCT
Middle School Round 1A
Page 11
TOSS-UP
23) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What must a glacier meet in order to form an ice shelf? ANSWER: AN OCEAN (ACCEPT: BODY OF WATER; SEA; OR BAY)
BONUS
23) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice What major geologic forces operate at the shoreline?
W) Surface water and wind
X) Waves and tides
Y) Wind and tides
Z) Chemical and physical weathering
ANSWER: X) WAVES AND TIDES
Middle School Round 1A
Page 12
