ROUND 12ATOSS-UP1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following species thrives in a mangrove?W) Blue crabs X) Sea turtles Y) Sea horses Z) AlligatorsANSWER: Z) ALLIGATORSBONUS1) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Flow cytometry [SY-to-muh-tree] is emerging as a valuable tool for quantifying photosynthetic cells in the environment. What property of photosynthetic cells is exploited in flow cytometry?ANSWER: FLUORESCENCETOSS-UP2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the name of the collection of galaxies that  contains the Milky Way, M31, M33 and the Magellanic Clouds [maj-uh-LAN-ik]?W) The Local GroupX) The Horsehead NebulaY) The extended milky wayZ) The Virgo clusterANSWER: W) THE LOCAL GROUPBONUS2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A neutrally charged atom has an atomic number of 11 and a mass number of 23. Identify the number of protons, neutrons, and electrons.ANSWER: PROTONS: 11; NEUTRONS: 12; ELECTRONS: 11Middle School Round 12A Page 1TOSS-UP3) ENERGY Multiple Choice Windows can be rated on the rate at which heat flows through them through which of the following measures?W) E-factor X) W- factor Y) U-factor Z) H-factorANSWER: Y) U-FACTORBONUS3) ENERGY Short Answer What is the major end product of glycolysis [gly-KOL-uh-sis]?ANSWER: PYRUVATE (ACCEPT: PYRUVIC ACID)TOSS-UP4) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Clusters of lymph nodes can be found in all EXCEPT which of the following areas?W) Axillae [ak-SIL-ee]X) BrainY) GroinZ) NeckANSWER: X) BRAINBONUS4) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name the three subdivisions of the small intestine. ANSWER: DUODENUM, JEJUNUM, ILEUM (IN ANY ORDER)Middle School Round 12A Page 2TOSS-UP5) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Mid-ocean ridge valleys are lined with what kind of faults? ANSWER: NORMAL (ACCEPT: DIP-SLIP)BONUS5) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice At what point in an inferior planet's orbit will it appear largest in the sky?W) OppositionX) Greatest elongation Y) Inferior conjunction Z) Superior conjunctionANSWER: Y) INFERIOR CONJUNCTION _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) MATH Multiple Choice If (x 2) 3 [the quantity x squared cubed] = 64, what is the value of x?W) 2 X) 4 Y) 16 Z) 64ANSWER: W) 2BONUS6) MATH Short Answer If the length of each edge of a cube is increased by 10%, by what percentage is its volume increased?ANSWER: 33.1 (ACCEPT: 33 1/10, 331/100)Middle School Round 12A Page 3TOSS-UP7) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice How does coral reproduce?W) It is pollinated by other fishX) Eggs and sperm are released in the open water Y) Male and female coral attract each otherZ) It fragments and regrows largerANSWER: X) EGGS AND SPERM ARE RELEASED IN THE OPEN WATERBONUS7) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What cellular component, common to bacteria, archaea [AHR- kee-uh], and eukaryotes [yoo-KAR-ee-ohts], is primarily responsible for protein synthesis?ANSWER: THE RIBOSOME _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What phase must the Moon be in for a solar eclipse to occur?  W) NewX) Last quarter Y) CrescentZ) FullANSWER: W) NEWBONUS8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A particular material absorbs violet, blue, and green light. Which of the following colors will NOT be observed when light strikes the material?W) Blue green X) RedY) Yellow green Z) OrangeANSWER: W) BLUE GREENMiddle School Round 12APage 4TOSS-UP9) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following would be the most accurate glassware to use to measure a volume of water?W) Erlenmeyer flask X) Graduated cylinder Y) Test tubeZ) BeakerANSWER: X) GRADUATED CYLINDERBONUS9) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A population crash is most likely when which of the following occurs?W) Unlimited resources are availableX) The growth rate slowsY) The population approaches carrying capacity Z) The population overshoots carrying capacityANSWER: Z) THE POPULATION OVERSHOOTS CARRYING CAPACITY _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer The galactic center appears in which constellation? ANSWER: SAGITTARIUS (DO NOT ACCEPT: SAGITTA)BONUS10) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following describes the relationship between water particles and ocean waves?W) Waves move water particles effectively along the surface of water X) Waves have no impact on the motion of water particlesY) Water moves in vertical orbits in the direction of wavesZ) Water particles are fragmented in the white caps of wavesANSWER: Y) WATER MOVES IN VERTICAL ORBITS IN THE DIRECTION OF WAVESMiddle School Round 12APage 5TOSS-UP11) MATH Short Answer Evaluate the following expression for r = 7: ((4r-7)/3)2/7 [open parenthesis, the fraction with numerator 4 r minus 7 and denominator 3, close parenthesis, squared, divided by 7].ANSWER: 7BONUS11) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following ordered pairs is a solution to this set of inequalities: x < 0 [x is less than 0]; y < 5 [y is less than 5]; y < -2x + 4 [y is less than negative 2 x plus 4]; y > -2x [y Is greater than negative 2 x]?W) (-1,-2) X) (-1,3) Y) (3,-1) Z) (1,2)ANSWER: X) (-1,3) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP12) ENERGY Short Answer If 10 incandescent 100 watt light bulbs are replaced with 10 LED lights of equivalent lumens, approximately how many fewer watts/hour will the LED lights consume?ANSWER: 830 (ACCEPT: ANY VALUE BETWEEN 800-870)BONUS12) ENERGY Multiple Choice In order to achieve maximum power point tracking in a renewable energy source, a signal is generated and utilized via pulse width modulation. Pulses with variable duty cycle are then sent to which part of the DC/DC converter circuit in order to control it?W) The inductorsX) The capacitorsY) The input voltage source Z) The transistors/switchesANSWER: Z) THE TRANSISTORS/SWITCHESMiddle School Round 12APage 6TOSS-UP13) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice A bacterium is suddenly immersed in a high salt media. What is the MOST likely response of the cell?W) Actively transport water into the cellX) Actively transport water out of the cellY) Actively transport potassium into the cellZ) Actively transport small organic molecules out of the cellANSWER: Y) ACTIVELY TRANSPORT POTASSIUM INTO THE CELLBONUS13) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer For decades the Gram stain was the primary tool for distinguishing between broad groups of bacteria. The Gram stain exploits differences in what cellular structure between gram positive and gram negative bacteria?ANSWER: THE CELL WALL _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP14) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Vinegar is a liquid solution containing acetic acid and water. It could be accurately classified as which of the following?W) A colloidX) A compoundY) A homogeneous mixture [hoh-muh-JEE-nee-uhs] Z) A heterogeneous mixture [het-er-uh-JEE-nee-uhs]ANSWER: Y) A HOMOGENEOUS MIXTUREBONUS14) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What particle is the smallest indivisible unit of light? ANSWER: PHOTONMiddle School Round 12A Page 7TOSS-UP15) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What type of solution has a higher concentration of hydroxide ions than hydronium ions?ANSWER: BASE (ACCEPT: BASIC OR ALKALINE OR ARRHENIUS BASE)BONUS15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following would NOT be a good characteristic of an index fossil?W) The fossil has distinctive characteristicsX) The species survived for millions of years Y) The species lived in many difference places Z) The species is not a soft-bodied organismANSWER: X) THE SPECIES SURVIVED FOR MILLIONS OF YEARS _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) ENERGY Multiple Choice Why is the angle of incidence of sunlight important for solar panels?W) It helps the panel remain cooler, but decreases the power outputX) It helps the panel remain hotter, and increases the power outputY) The closer the angle is to normal, the more power produced by the panelZ) The further the angle is from normal, the more power produced by the panelANSWER: Y) THE CLOSER THE ANGLE IS TO NORMAL, THE MORE POWER PRODUCED BY THE PANELBONUS16) ENERGY Short Answer How many kilowatt-hours does a heater running at 100 watts consume per 24 hour period?ANSWER: 2.4Middle School Round 12ATOSS-UP17) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice What is the approximate mass of the largest stars?W) 1 solar massX) 10 solar masses Y) 100 solar masses Z) 1000 solar massesANSWER: Y) 100 SOLAR MASSESBONUS17) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a sedimentary rock made of microscopic fossil marine shells?W) Chalk X) Shale Y) Coal Z) LigniteANSWER: W) CHALK _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP18) MATH Multiple Choice A triangle has vertices (6, 7), (11, 9) and (3, 8). After undergoing a particular transformation, its corresponding new vertices are (8, 10), (13, 12) and (5, 11), respectively. What type of transformation did it undergo?W) DilationX) Translation Y) Reflection Z) RotationANSWER: X) TRANSLATIONBONUS18) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following angles cannot be trisected using only compass and straightedge?W) 45X) 120Y) 135Z) No angle can be trisectedANSWER: X) 120TOSS-UP19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following was a top predator during the Devonian period?W) Coelecanth [SEE-luh-kanth]X) TrilobiteY) Crinoid [KRY-noid]Z) Dunkleosteus [duhn-klee-uh-STE-uhs]ANSWER: Z) DUNKLEOSTEUSBONUS19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice A peptide sequence with the amino acid composition proline-glycine [GLY-seen]-glycine-tyrosine [TY-ruh-seen] would have what percentage of aromaticity?W) 25% X) 50% Y) 75% Z) 100%ANSWER: W) 25% _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT part of the standard model of frictional force assumptions?W) Frictional force is independent of contact areaX) Frictional force is proportional to normal forceY) Frictional coefficient is proportional to force between objects Z) Frictional force is independent of velocityANSWER: Y) FRICTIONAL COEFFICIENT IS PROPORTIONAL TO FORCE BETWEEN OBJECTS 20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer ANSWER: DARK MATTERBONUSWhat mysterious type of matter is hypothesized to comprise over 80% of the mass of our galaxy?Middle School Round 12A Page 10TOSS-UP21) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a steroid?W) CholesterolX) Triacylglycerols [try-uh-see-GLIS-uh-rohls] Y) TestosteroneZ) Estradiol [es-truh-DY-ol]ANSWER: X) TRIACYLGLYCEROLSBONUS21) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Kepler’s laws of planetary motion describe the path of two objects, one orbiting the other, as which of the following?W) Hyperbolic with the Sun at one extreme end from the objectX) Spherical with the Sun at a radial distance from the objectY) A figure eight with the Sun and the object intersecting periodically Z) Elliptical with the Sun at one of the fociANSWER: Z) ELLIPTICAL WITH THE SUN AT ONE OF THE FOCI _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP22) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice What draws the charged particles from the solar wind to the polar regions of the Earth?W) Jet stream currents in Earth’s upper atmosphere X) Earth’s magnetic fieldY) Earth’s electric fieldZ) Centrifugal forceANSWER: X) EARTH’S MAGNETIC FIELDBONUS22) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following Appalachian Mountain provinces is the eroded remnant of a folded mountain belt?W) Valley and Ridge belt X) Great ValleyY) PiedmontZ) Appalachian PlateauANSWER: W) VALLEY AND RIDGE BELTMiddle School Round 12APage 11TOSS-UP23) MATH Short Answer A rectangular box has a volume of 200 cubic inches. The length of the box is 10 inches, and the height is 4 inches. What is the ratio of the width of the box to the length of the box?ANSWER: 1:2 (ACCEPT: 1⁄2 OR 0.5)BONUS23) MATH Short Answer A group of 3 boys and 3 girls are taking a photograph, standing side- by-side in a line. If they must alternate gender, how many different arrangements are possible?ANSWER: 72Middle School Round 12A Page 12