ROUND 8A
          TOSS-UP
1) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Compressive forces that result in brittle deformation yield what formation?
W) Normal faults
X) Reverse faults
Y) Synclines [SIN-klyns]
Z) Grabens [GRAH-buhns]
ANSWER: X) REVERSE FAULTS
BONUS
1) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer In which constellation is the nearest major galaxy, M31? ANSWER: ANDROMEDA
           _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
2) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Why is coal a non-renewable fuel source?
W) It is formed from ancient fossilized biomass X) It is expensive
Y) It releases carbon dioxide into the atmosphere Z) It is used faster than it is formed
ANSWER: Z) IT IS USED FASTER THAN IT IS FORMED
BONUS
2) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Unlike prokaryotic [proh-KAR-ee-oh-tik] cells, the cytoplasm [SY-tuh-plaz-uhm] of eukaryotic [yoo-KAR-ee-oh-tik] cells is filled with a variety of membrane bound structures that enable the cell to function properly. What is the name for this group of structures?
ANSWER: ORGANELLES
Middle School Round 8A Page 1
TOSS-UP
3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The combination of two deuterium [doo-TEER-ee- uhm] atoms to form a single helium atom is known as which of the following?
W) Alpha decay X) Beta decay
Y) Nuclear fission Z) Nuclear fusion
ANSWER: Z) NUCLEAR FUSION
BONUS
3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice On the periodic table, potassium is in what family?
W) Halogen
X) Alkali metal
Y) Alkaline earth metal
Z) Chalcogen [KAL-kuh-juhn]
ANSWER: X) ALKALI METAL _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
4) MATH Short Answer After 3 tests, a student has an average score of 80%. What does the student need to score on a fourth test to increase the average score to exactly 84%?
ANSWER: 96% (ACCEPT: 96)
BONUS
4) MATH Multiple Choice If a, b and c are numbers such that a/b = 3 [a over b equals 3] and b/c = 7 [b over c equals 7] then (a+b)/ (b+c) [the quantity a plus b over the quantity b plus c] is equal to which of the following?
W) 7/2 [seven halves] X) 7/8 [seven-eighths] Y) 3/7 [three-sevenths] Z) 1/7 [one-seventh]
ANSWER: W) 7/2
Middle School Round 8A
Page 2
TOSS-UP
5) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the purpose of the lateral line in fish?
W) Seeing particular colors X) Carrying blood to the gills Y) Producing sound waves Z) Detecting vibration
ANSWER: Z) DETECTING VIBRATION

BONUS
5) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following would be an example of a mycorrhizal [my-kuh-RY-zuhl] symbiosis?
W) A parasitic wasp laying eggs on a caterpillar
X) The bacterium Rhizobium [ry-ZOH-bee-uhm] infecting the roots of a peanut plant Y) Ants living in Acacia [uh-KAY-shuh] thorns and protecting the host plant
Z) Ants that harvest honeydew from aphids [AY-fids] feeding on plants
ANSWER: X) THE BACTERIUM RHIZOBIUM INFECTING THE ROOTS OF A PEANUT PLANT
TOSS-UP
6) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following rocks is NOT metamorphic?
W) Limestone
X) Marble
Y) Gneiss [NYS] Z) Schist [SHIST]
ANSWER: W) LIMESTONE
BONUS
6) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Not including brown dwarfs, what is the second coolest class of star?
ANSWER: K
Middle School Round 8A Page 3
TOSS-UP
7) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following sources of radiation is most commonly used to irradiate food?
W) Uranium-235 X) Cobalt-60
Y) Radium-226 Z) Potassium-40
ANSWER: X) COBALT-60
BONUS
7) ENERGY Short Answer Over time, the amplitude of a swing decreases. This is because the rider�s mechanical energy is converted to what instead?
ANSWER: HEAT (ACCEPT: HEAT ENERGY, THERMAL ENERGY) _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
8) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name the method by which new genetic material can be introduced into a population.
ANSWER: MUTATION (ACCEPT: GENE FLOW; DO NOT ACCEPT: SEXUAL REPRODUCTION)
BONUS
8) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Lateritic [lat-uh-RIT-ik] soils would be found in which biome?
W) Tropical rain forest X) Temperate forest Y) Tropical dry forest Z) Taiga [TY-guh]
ANSWER: W) TROPICAL RAIN FOREST
Middle School Round 8A
Page 4
TOSS-UP
9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Central processing units have evolved heavily over the past 30 years. They are responsible for a great deal of computational research, and in addition, have changed the way many people live their lives. What basic circuit element can be found on the order of billions inside many modern CPUs?
ANSWER: TRANSISTORS
BONUS
9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements about precipitation is FALSE?
W) Can occur by converting a soluble substance into an insoluble form
X) Results in a higher purity solid if higher concentration solutions are used
Y) Can be used to remove metal ions from aqueous solutions [AK-wee-uhs]
Z) Can occur by changing the composition of a solvent to diminish the solubility of a substance in it
ANSWER: X) RESULTS IN A HIGHER PURITY SOLID IF HIGHER CONCENTRATION SOLUTIONS ARE USED
 _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
10) MATH Multiple Choice Add 8x to 2x and then subtract 5 from the sum. If x is a positive integer, the result must be an integer multiple of which of the following?
W) 2 X) 5 Y) 8 Z) 10
ANSWER: X) 5
BONUS
10) MATH Short Answer If x varies directly as the square of y and x equals 0.5 when y is 1, what is x when y = 4?
ANSWER: 8
Middle School Round 8A Page 5
TOSS-UP
11) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer In human extremities what term is used to describe the evidence that veins are weakening and valves do NOT close properly?
ANSWER: VARICOSE VEINS
BONUS
11) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which is NOT one of the essential activities that occurs in the digestive process?
W) Ingestion
X) Propulsion
Y) Mechanical digestion Z) Adsorption
ANSWER: Z) ADSORPTION _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
12) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT considered part of a beach�s foreshore environment?
W) Surf zone X) Tidal flat
Y) Berm
Z) Swash zone
ANSWER: Y) BERM
BONUS
12) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Around what two points do stars appear to rotate in the sky over the course of a day?
ANSWER: NORTH AND SOUTH CELESTIAL POLES (ACCEPT: CELESTIAL POLES; NORTH AND SOUTH POLES)
Middle School Round 8A Page 6
TOSS-UP
13) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Mendel�s experiments crossing different colored pea plants demonstrated what genetic concept?
W) Haploid and diploid variation
X) Recessive and dominant genes
Y) Gametophyte reproductive cycles [guh-MEE-tuh-fyt] Z) Mitotic division [my-TOT-ik]
ANSWER: X) RECESSIVE AND DOMINANT GENES
BONUS
13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What specific chamber of the heart is responsible for pumping blood to the lungs?
ANSWER: RIGHT VENTRICLE ______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
14) ENERGY Multiple Choice The energy stored in a candle that can be changed into heat and light energy in burning is what type of energy?
W) Potential X) Heat
Y) Light
Z) Chemical
ANSWER: Z) CHEMICAL
BONUS
14) ENERGY Multiple Choice What is the amperage in a circuit with a 14 volt power source and three 6 ohm light bulbs in parallel?
W) 3 X) 5 Y) 7 Z) 9
ANSWER: Y) 7
Middle School Round 8A
Page 7
TOSS-UP
15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The escape velocity from the event horizon of a black hole is which of the following?
W) The speed of light
X) Greater than the speed of light Y) Infinity
Z) Negative infinity
ANSWER: W) THE SPEED OF LIGHT

BONUS
15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer In what type of current do electrons frequently reverse their direction of travel?
ANSWER: ALTERNATING CURRENT (ACCEPT: AC)
TOSS-UP
16) MATH Multiple Choice What is the value of (1/2)-2 [one-half raised to the negative two power]?
W) -4 X) -1/4 Y) 1/4 Z) 4
ANSWER: Z) 4
BONUS
16) MATH Short Answer Evaluate the following: log2166 [log base two hundred sixteen of 6]. ANSWER: 1/3
Middle School Round 8A Page 8
TOSS-UP
17) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which ocean zone would coral reside?
W) Pelagic [puh-LAJ-ik] X) Benthic
Y) Neritic [nuh-RIT-ik] Z) Intertidal
ANSWER: Y) NERITIC
BONUS
17) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the correct term for a marine organism whose internal salt concentration varies with that of their environment?
W) Osmoregulator
X) Ion-concentrators Y) Osmoconformers Z) Urea-concentrators
ANSWER: Y) OSMOCONFORMERS _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
18) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the source of the helium-3 found in the lunar regolith?
ANSWER: THE SUN (ACCEPT: SOLAR WIND)
BONUS
18) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the reason that a lunar eclipse does not occur during every full moon?
W) The Moon's orbit is inclined relative to the Earth's X) Lunar eclipses only occur during an equinox
Y) Lunar eclipses only occur during a solstice
Z) Lunar eclipses only occur during a new moon
ANSWER: W) THE MOON'S ORBIT IS INCLINED RELATIVE TO THE EARTH'S
Middle School Round 8A
Page 9
TOSS-UP
19) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following does NOT contribute to eutrophication [yoo-tro-fi-KAY-shun]?
W) Excess fertilizer usage
X) Untreated sewage and waste water Y) Increased oxygen inputs
Z) Industrial animal waste
ANSWER: Y) INCREASED OXYGEN INPUTS
BONUS
19) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is true about the drifting of North America and Europe?
W) It is away from each other at approximately 2.5 centimeters per year X) It is toward each other at approximately 2.5 centimeters per year
Y) It is away from each other at approximately 2.5 millimeters per year Z) It is toward each other at approximately 2.5 millimeters per year
ANSWER: W) IT IS AWAY FROM EACH OTHER AT APPROXIMATELY 2.5 CENTIMETERS PER YEAR
           _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Two objects have the same size and shape, but one is twice as heavy as the other. They are dropped simultaneously from a building. If air resistance is negligible, which of the following is true?
W) The heavy one lands on the ground before the light one
X) They land on the ground at the same time but the heavy one has more speed upon impact Y) They land on the ground at the same time and have the same speed upon impact.
Z) The land on the ground at the same time but the heavy object has a lower acceleration
ANSWER: Y) THEY LAND ON THE GROUND AT THE SAME TIME AND HAVE THE SAME SPEED UPON IMPACT
BONUS
20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term that describes the factor by which the speed of light is decreased when traveling through a given material?
ANSWER: REFRACTIVE INDEX
Middle School Round 8A Page 10
TOSS-UP
21) MATH Short Answer If an event has a 45% chance of success in any single trial, how many successful events would one expect to have occurred after 5,000 trials?
ANSWER: 2,250
BONUS
21) MATH Multiple Choice In which quadrants do the solutions to the inequality
2x + 3 < y < -(1/2)x � 5 [two x plus three is less than y is less than negative one half x minus five] lie?
W) I and II
X) II, III and IV Y) II and III
Z) I, II and III
ANSWER: Y) II AND III _______________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
22) ENERGY Short Answer Other than a battery, what else will produce a direct current with no moving parts?
ANSWER: THERMOCOUPLES (ACCEPT: SOLAR CELLS)
BONUS
22) ENERGY Short Answer In a northern climate, what should be the orientation of windows in a passively heated solar home?
ANSWER: SOUTH
Middle School Round 8A Page 11
TOSS-UP
23) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the primary chemical constituent of the cell wall in plants?
ANSWER: CELLULOSE
BONUS
23) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice The process of nitrogen fixation is extremely energy intensive due to which of the following?
W) Atoms of free nitrogen are triply bound to other nitrogen atoms
X) Atoms of free nitrogen are highly reactive
Y) The nitrogen atom is highly unreactive
Z) Nitrogen atoms are usually found tightly bound to alkaline earth metals
ANSWER: W) ATOMS OF FREE NITROGEN ARE TRIPLY BOUND TO OTHER NITROGEN ATOMS
Middle School Round 8A Page 12
