TOSS-UP
1) Physical Science Short Answer What subatomic particles are hadrons, such as protons and neutrons, composed of?
ANSWER: QUARKS
BONUS
1) Physical Science Short Answer An alpha particle is equivalent to the nucleus of what element?
ANSWER: HELIUM

TOSS-UP
2) Energy Multiple Choice In the most common type of geothermal power plant, what rotates the turbines?
W) Steam X) Water Y) Ice
Z) Hot air
ANSWER: W) STEAM

BONUS
2) Energy Short Answer Artificial photosynthesis is being explored as a new type of renewable energy. What is the name of the second, reduction stage of photosynthesis?
ANSWER: CALVIN-BENSON CYCLE (ACCEPT LIGHT-INDEPENDENT REACTIONS)
TOSS-UP
3) Math Short Answer Solve the following equation for x: -2x2 + 2 = 0.
ANSWER: 1 AND -1 (MUST PROVIDE BOTH ANSWERS)

BONUS
3) Math Short Answer A right circular cone has volume 72 cubic inches. A second cone has half the radius and three times the height of the first cone. In cubic inches, what is the volume of the second cone?
ANSWER: 54

TOSS-UP
4) Earth and Space Multiple Choice Where on an Hertzsprung-Russel diagram would one find a red supergiant?
W) Bottom left X) Bottom right Y) Top left
Z) Top right
ANSWER: Z) TOP RIGHT
BONUS
4) Earth and Space Multiple Choice What is the term for a water-bearing layer of permeable, undergound rock?
W) Aquifer X) Aquitard Y) Fjord
Z) Clay
ANSWER: W) AQUIFER

TOSS-UP
5) General Science Multiple Choice What is the study of woody plants?
W) Botany
X) Horticulture Y) Dendrology Z) Mycology
ANSWER: Y) DENDROLOGY

BONUS
5) General Science Short Answer In photosynthesis, the energy from light is used to split what molecule?
ANSWER: WATER

TOSS-UP
6) Life Science Short Answer What term is used by biologists to describe an organism�s appearance or observable traits?
ANSWER: PHENOTYPE

BONUS
6) Life Science Short Answer What muscle is responsible for extending the arm at the elbow?
ANSWER: TRICEPS BRACHII (ACCEPT: TRICEPS)

TOSS-UP
7) Math Short Answer What is the area of the smallest possible square that contains a circle of radius 5?
ANSWER: 100

BONUS
7) Math Short Answer What is the area of a right triangle with hypotenuse 10 and one leg of length 4?
ANSWER: 4 times the square root of 21

TOSS-UP
8) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice What rock texture is characterized by broken fragments of older rocks?
W) Foliated X) Nonfoliated Y) Clastic
Z) Bioturbated
ANSWER: Y) CLASTIC


BONUS
8) Earth and Space Short Answer Identify all of the following three objects that are known to have a
dipolar magnetic field: 1) Earth; 2) Jupiter; 3) Earth's moon.
ANSWER: 1 AND 2


TOSS-UP
9) Energy Short Answer What type of nuclear reactor produces fissile fuel as a waste product?
ANSWER: BREEDER REACTORS
BONUS
9) Energy Short Answer One major trouble with using absolute ethanol as a fuel source is that ethanol forms an azeotrope with what ubiquitous liquid?
ANSWER: WATER

TOSS-UP
10) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following is the region of the body where the thyroid gland is located?
W) Neck
X) Abdomen Y) Brain
Z) Arm pit
ANSWER: W) NECK
BONUS
10) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of metamorphosis?

W) A rabbit giving birth to eight young
X) A bumble bee larva forming a puparium and emerging as a mature adult
Y) A baby bird emerging from the egg
Z) A stink bug transitioning through multiple instars eventually becoming a mature adult
ANSWER: X) A BUMBLE BEE LARVA FORMING A PUPARIUM AND EMERGING AS A MATURE ADULT


TOSS-UP
11) General Science  Multiple Choice Cell membranes are described as fluid mosaic models consisting of proteins embedded in a bilayer of phospholipids. Which of the following components of a plant cell do NOT contain two of these bilayers?
W) Chloroplast
X) Mitochondria
Y) Endoplasmic reticulum Z) Nucleus
ANSWER: Y) ENDOPLASMIC RETICULUM
BONUS
11) General Science  Short Answer Johannes Kepler�s laws of planetary motion were based upon observations of what planet?
ANSWER: MARS


TOSS-UP
12) Physical Science  Short Answer Identify all of the following three substances that are considered basic: 1) Vinegar; 2) Ammonia; 3) Milk.
ANSWER: 2

BONUS
12) Physical Science  Short Answer At what temperature do the Celsius and Fahrenheit scales have the same value?
ANSWER: NEGATIVE 40


TOSS-UP
13) Earth and Space Multiple Choice What type of fault is characterized by two tectonic plates that slide past one another horizontally?

W) Transform fault X) Normal fault
Y) Reverse fault Z) Fracture zone
ANSWER: W) TRANSFORM FAULT

BONUS
13) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice  In which of the following locations could a hurricane never develop?
W) North Pacific X) North Atlantic Y) South Pacific Z) Equator
ANSWER: Z) EQUATOR



TOSS-UP
14) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes the relationship between epiphytes and the trees they live on?
W) Mutualism
X) Commensalism Y) Amensalism
Z) Parasitism
ANSWER: X) COMMENSALISM


BONUS
14) Life Science Short Answer Identify all of the following three choices that arise, directly or indirectly, from meristematic activity: 1) Leaves; 2) Dermal tissue; 3) Xylem.
ANSWER: 1, 2, 3 (ACCEPT: ALL)

TOSS-UP
15) Physical Science Multiple Choice Which of the following standard units is defined in terms of a physical object?
W) Kilogram X) Meter
Y) Second Z) Liter
ANSWER: W) KILOGRAM

BONUS
15) Physical Science Multiple Choice Two physics students can push on a box of mass M and give it
acceleration A. How many students would be required to give a box of 0.5M an acceleration of 3A?

W) 2 X) 3 Y) 4 Z) 6
ANSWER: X) 3

TOSS-UP
16) General Science  Short Answer In many drugs, hydrogens are replaced with what element that is similar in size to hydrogen but is much more electronegative?
ANSWER: FLUORINE
BONUS
16) General Science  Multiple Choice Which of the following statements about the magnetic north pole is NOT true?
W) It is currently in the same place as the geographic north pole X) It is constantly moving to the north-west
Y) It is south of the geographic north pole
Z) It was once the magnetic south pole, and will likely be again
ANSWER: W) IT IS CURRENTLY IN THE SAME PLACE AS THE GEOGRAPHIC NORTH POLE
Round 11A ~ Page 8
17) Math Short Answer ANSWER: 12
17) Math Short Answer ANSWER: 52
TOSS-UP
What is the greatest common factor of 36 and 48?
BONUS
The base-six numeral 124 [one-two-four] is equivalent to what in base 10?
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
18) Energy Short Answer Order the following four types of coal from greatest to least in energy density: 1) Subbituminous; 2) Anthracite; 3) Lignite; 4) Bituminous.
ANSWER: 2, 4, 1, 3
BONUS
18) Energy Short Answer A 100-watt lightbulb is left on between 8:00 am and 5:00 pm. How many kilowatt-hours of energy were consumed?
ANSWER: 0.9
Round 11A ~ Page 9
TOSS-UP
19) Math Short Answer Two jokers are inserted into a standard 52-card deck. If one card is drawn at random, what is the probability that a joker is drawn?
ANSWER: 1/27
BONUS
19) Math Short Answer To the nearest whole number, what is the slant height of a right circular cone with radius 8 and a height 4?
ANSWER: 9
20) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice percentage of dissolved gas?
W) Ultramafic X) Basaltic
Y) Andesitic Z) Rhyolitic
ANSWER: Z) RHYOLITIC
20) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice
W) Corona
X) Chromosphere Y) Photosphere Z) Solar wind
ANSWER: Y) PHOTOSPHERE
TOSS-UP
Which of the following types of magmas has the greatest
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
BONUS
What layer of the Sun's atmosphere is hidden during totality?
Round 11A ~ Page 10
TOSS-UP
21) Life Science  Short Answer What is the term for the fluid inside of the chloroplast? ANSWER: STROMA
BONUS
21) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following is the causative agent for some cases of familial fatal insomnia, Creutzfeld-Jacob disease, and kuru?
W) Bacteria
X) Virus
Y) Prion [pry-on] Z) Protist
ANSWER: Y) PRION
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
22) Physical Science  Short Answer What is the momentum, in newton seconds, of a 15 kilogram object moving at 13 meters per second?
ANSWER: 195
BONUS
22) Physical Science  Short Answer Giving your answers in scientific notation to two significant figures, how many atoms of nitrogen and oxygen, respectively, are found in one mole of dinitrogen tetraoxide?
ANSWER: NITROGEN: 1.2 x 1024 OXYGEN: 2.4 x 1024
Round 11A ~ Page 11
TOSS-UP
23) General Science  Short Answer In an experiment on the effects of sugar on rat hyperactivity, rats in group 1 are given plain water, while rats in group 2 are given sugar water. What is the name for group 1?
ANSWER: CONTROL
BONUS
23) General Science  Short Answer With what celestial bodies is Hawking radiation associated? ANSWER: BLACK HOLES
Round 11A ~ Page 12
