TOSS-UP
1) Life Science Multiple Choice In the human body, the gallbladder is in immediate proximity to what organ?
W) Liver
X) Spleen
Y) Pancreas
Z) Thymus [thigh-mus]
ANSWER: W) LIVER
BONUS
1) Life Science Short Answer Flowering plants are grouped into what 2 classes named after their number of seed leaves?
ANSWER: MONOCOTS AND DICOTS (ACCEPT: MONOCOTYLEDONS AND DICOTYLEDONS )

TOSS-UP
2) Earth and Space Multiple Choice Most volcanic rocks are porous due to:
W) Erosion
X) Marine organisms
Y) Rapid cooling
Z) Gases trapped inside lava
ANSWER: Z) GASES TRAPPED INSIDE LAVA

BONUS
2) Earth and Space Multiple Choice What impurity found in coal contributes most significantly to acid rain?
W) Sulfur X) Nitrogen Y) Carbon Z) Chlorine
ANSWER: W) SULFUR

TOSS-UP
3) General Science Multiple Choice Which of the following is not considered a piece of laboratory safety equipment?
W) Goggles
X) Fume hood
Y) Eye wash station Z) Bunsen burner
ANSWER: Z) BUNSEN BURNER

BONUS
3) General Science Multiple Choice What organ, located in the ventral cavity, is identified by its four lobes?
W) Right lung X) Left lung Y) Liver
Z) Kidneys
ANSWER: Y) LIVER

TOSS-UP
4) Math Multiple Choice A right triangle has 1 angle that measures 27 degrees. In degrees, which of the following could be another angle of this triangle?
W) 63 X) 73 Y) 123 Z) 153
ANSWER: W) 63


4) Math Short Answer Solve the following equation for x: 8 to the 6 - x power = 4 to the x - 1 power?
ANSWER: 4
BONUS
  Round 1A ~ Page 2
TOSS-UP
5) Physical Science  Multiple Choice The strength of the gravitational force between the earth and an airplane flying above its surface is NOT dependent on which of the following?
W) Mass of the plane X) Mass of the earth
Y) Velocity of the plane Z) Radius of the earth
ANSWER: Y) VELOCITY OF THE PLANE
5) Physical Science  Multiple Choice
W) Positrons X) Protons Y) Electrons Z) Photons
ANSWER: Z) PHOTONS
BONUS
X-rays are composed of beams of what particles?
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
6) Energy Short Answer What is the term used to describe the medium in nuclear reactors that is used to reduce the speed of fast neutrons?
ANSWER: MODERATOR
BONUS
6) Energy Short Answer What is the term that refers to the minimum amount of Uranium-235 necessary to produce a self-sustaining nucleation fission reaction?
ANSWER: CRITICALMASS
Round 1A ~ Page 3
TOSS-UP
7) Earth and Space  Short Answer By what process does fallen precipitation trickle into the ground and become part of the groundwater?
ANSWER: INFILTRATION
BONUS
7) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice An eclipse of the moon occurs when:
W) The moon passes directly between the Earth and the sun X) The Earth passes directly between the sun and the moon Y) The moon�s dark side faces the Earth
Z) The sun passes directly between the Earth and the moon
ANSWER: X) THE EARTH PASSES DIRECTLY BETWEEN THE SUN AND THE MOON
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
8) General Science  Short Answer What chemical compound makes up the genetic material found inside of the nucleus?
ANSWER: DEOXYRIBONUCLEIC ACID (ACCEPT: DNA)
BONUS
8) General Science  Short Answer To the nearest whole number, eleven pounds is approximately equal to how many kilograms?
ANSWER: 5
Round 1A ~ Page 4
TOSS-UP
9) Life Science  Short Answer What cells consist of cell bodies, dendrites, and axons? ANSWER: NEURONS (ACCEPT: NERVE CELLS)
BONUS
9) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following has the steps of mitosis placed in the correct order?
W) Telophase, prophase, anaphase, metaphase X) Prophase, metaphase, anaphase, telophase Y) Metaphase, telophase, prophase, anaphase Z) Anaphase, metaphase, prophase, telophase
ANSWER: X) PROPHASE, METAPHASE, ANAPHASE, TELOPHASE
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
10) Math Short Answer What is the value of 23 + negative s when s = -17? ANSWER: 40
BONUS
10) Math Short Answer Sarah left home at 8:00 a.m. and arrived at 11:45 a.m. If the distance she traveled is 225 miles, what was her average speed, in miles per hour, during the trip?
ANSWER: 60
 Round 1A ~ Page 5
12) Physical Science  Short Answer an element?
ANSWER: ATOM
12) Physical Science  Short Answer longer distinct?
ANSWER: CRITICAL POINT
TOSS-UP
What is the smallest particle that retains the chemical properties of
BONUS
At what point on a pressure-volume diagram are liquid and gas no
TOSS-UP
Which of the following inventions is Alessandro Volta credited with?
BONUS
11) Energy  Multiple Choice
W) Alternating current X) Incandescent lightbulb Y) Battery
Z) Radio wave generator
ANSWER: Y) BATTERY
11) Energy Short Answer combining hydrocarbons and oxygen?
ANSWER: COMBUSTION
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
What type of chemical reaction is used in car engines and involves
Round 1A ~ Page 6
14) Math Short Answer ANSWER: 12
14) Math Short Answer calculate g of f of 2.
ANSWER: 1/3
TOSS-UP
What is the perimeter of a right triangle with legs of length 3 and 4?
BONUS
Given f(x)= x � 4 and g(x) = 1 over open parenthesis x + 5 close parenthesis,
TOSS-UP
Which of the following organisms has spines?

BONUS
13) Life Science Multiple Choice
W) Conch
X) Jellyfish Y) Limpet
Z) Sea Urchin
ANSWER: Z) SEA URCHIN

13) Life Science  Short Answer What term is used to describe rings of muscle that usually control
entry and exit from a body compartment?
ANSWER: SPHINCTER





TOSS-UP
15) Physical Science  Short Answer What term describes the bending of a wave as it moves between two mediums?
ANSWER: REFRACTION

BONUS
15) Physical Science  Multiple Choice Sodium becomes positively charged when it combines with chlorine because sodium:
W) Loses an electron
X) Gains an electron
Y) Forms a covalent bond
Z) Has more electrons than protons
ANSWER: W) LOSES AN ELECTRON

TOSS-UP
16) General Science  Short Answer The eyeball rests in a socket framed primarily by which cheekbone?
ANSWER: ZYGOMATIC

BONUS
16) General Science  Multiple Choice How many significant figures are in the number 0.000320?
W) 2 X) 3 Y) 4 Z) 5
ANSWER: X) 3

TOSS-UP
17) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice What era is also known as the Age of Mammals?
W) Mesozoic
X) Paleozoic
Y) Cenozoic [cen-uh-zoh-ik] Z) Proterozoic
ANSWER: Y) CENOZOIC

BONUS
17) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice Calving is the process that forms which of the following?
W) Icebergs X) Lakes
Y) Faults
Z) Volcanoes
ANSWER: W) ICEBERGS






TOSS-UP
18) Energy Short Answer To the nearest ten percent, what portion of the electricity produced in the United States is generated through nuclear power?
ANSWER: 20

BONUS
18) Energy  Multiple Choice Gasoline is mostly composed of which of the following?
W) Alcohols
X) Hydrocarbons Y) Aromatics
Z) Oxidants
ANSWER: X) HYDROCARBONS



TOSS-UP
19) Earth and Space  Short What is the study of the atmosphere and the weather called?
Answer ANSWER: METEOROLOGY

BONUS
19) Earth and Space  Short Answer Eventually, a meander will cut off due to erosion and create a lake. What are these lakes called?
ANSWER: OXBOW LAKES




                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
20) General Science  Short Answer Healthy humans have many bacteria living on or in them. To the nearest whole numbers, what is the ratio of human to bacterial cells in most humans?
Answer: 1 HUMAN CELL TO 10 BACTERIAL CELLS (ACCEPT: 1:10)
BONUS
20) General Science  Multiple Choice Theodor [Tee-o-door] Schwann and Matthias Schleiden [schli- den] are known for:
W) Applying the concept of cells to plants and animals
X) Coining the term "cell" from the structure of cork
Y) Applying the concept of fibers and vessels to living things Z) Identifying the double helix of DNA
ANSWER: W) APPLYING THE CONCEPT OF CELLS TO PLANTS AND ANIMALS


TOSS-UP
21) Life Science  Short Answer What is the name of the fourth and final stomach chamber in ruminants and is the location of protein digestion?
ANSWER: ABOMASUM
BONUS
21) Life Science  Short Answer What higher plant cell organelle is responsible for using sunlight to convert carbon dioxide and water into sugar and oxygen?
ANSWER: CHLOROPLAST


TOSS-UP
22) Math  Multiple Choice Abby reads 10 pages of a 150 page book on Monday. Each subsequent day, she plans to read twice as many pages than she did the previous day. On what day will she finish the book?
W) Tuesday X) Thursday Y) Friday Z) Saturday
ANSWER: X) THURSDAY
22) Math Short Answer Solve the following equation for x: open parenthesis 2x - 9 close parenthesis squared = 81.
ANSWER: x = 0 or x = 9 (MUST GIVE BOTH ANSWERS)
BONUS

TOSS-UP
23) Physical Science  Short Answer What happens to the pH of an acidic solution as pure water is added?
ANSWER: pH INCREASES


BONUS
23) Physical Science  Short Answer A rollercoaster car has a mass of 200 kilograms and a kinetic
energy of 22.5 kilojoules. What is its velocity, in meters per second?
ANSWER: 15


