          TOSS-UP
1) Physical Science  Short Answer What kind of collision conserves both kinetic energy and linear momentum?
ANSWER: ELASTIC (ACCEPT: PERFECTLY ELASTIC)
BONUS
1) Physical Science  Short Answer An object in free-fall on the Earth will eventually stop accelerating. What is the term for the speed of the object when it reaches this point?
ANSWER: TERMINAL VELOCITY (ACCEPT: TERMINAL SPEED)

TOSS-UP
2) Earth and Space  Short Answer What term is used to describe the fraction of light that is reflected by a surface?
ANSWER: ALBEDO
2) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice occurring?
W) Marianas trench X) African rift valley Y) Mid-Atlantic ridge Z) Tanna fault
ANSWER: Y) MID-ATLANTIC RIDGE
BONUS
At which of the following locations is seafloor spreading
Round 3A ~ Page 1
TOSS-UP
3) Energy Short Answer Ethanol in the US is primarily produced from what crop? ANSWER: CORN
BONUS
3) Energy  Multiple Choice Which of the following is closest to the percentage of electricity produced in the US using renewable energy sources?
W) 80% X) 50% Y) 30% Z) 10%
ANSWER: Z) 10%
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
4) General Science  Multiple Choice To guard against sparks causing a fire, mechanics aboard submarines during World War II often used tools made from which of the following:
W) Chrome plated steel X) Vanadium
Y) Cold rolled steel
Z) Bronze
ANSWER: Z) BRONZE
4) General Science  Multiple Choice
W) Oxygen X) Carbon Y) Fluorine Z) Nitrogen
ANSWER: X) CARBON
BONUS
Life on Earth is based on building blocks of what element?
Round 3A ~ Page 2
5) Life Science Multiple Choice in:
TOSS-UP
The exchange of gases between blood and the tissue occurs normally
W) Venules X) Arterioles Y) Veins
Z) Capillaries
ANSWER: Z) CAPILLARIES
5) Life Science  Short Answer ANSWER: CHORDATA
BONUS
In what phylum are all vertebrate organisms?
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
6) Math  Multiple Choice The county fair charges a $4 entrance fee. The cost of each ride is $2. Which of the following equations represents the cost (y) of getting into the fair and going on x rides?
W) y = 6 + x X) y = 2 + 4x Y) y = 4 + 2x Z) y = 6x
ANSWER: Y) y = 4 + 2x
6) Math Short Answer whole square meter?
ANSWER: 8
BONUS
If a circle has a circumference of 10 meters, what is its area, to the nearest
Round 3A ~ Page 3
TOSS-UP
7) Energy Short Answer If a transformer has an input voltage of 440 volts and an output voltage of 110 volts, what is the ratio of the number of turns in the input coil to the number of turns in the output coil?
ANSWER: 4 to 1
BONUS
7) Energy Short Answer What method is currently used to produce most of the world�s renewable energy?
ANSWER: HYDROPOWER (ACCEPT: HYDROELECTRIC)
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
8) Physical Science  Multiple Choice Which of the following provides a measure of the amount of matter in a substance?
W) Mass X) Volume Y) Density Z) Weight
ANSWER: W) MASS
8) Physical Science  Short Answer ANSWER: WATT
BONUS
What derived SI unit is used to express power?
Round 3A ~ Page 4
9) General Science  Multiple Choice slowest?
TOSS-UP
Through which of the following mediums does sound travel the
W) Air
X) Water Y) Copper Z) Ice
ANSWER: W) AIR
9) General Science  Short Answer plate boundary?
ANSWER: DIVERGENT
BONUS
Continental rifts and mid-ocean ridges are found at which type of
10) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice spots in Hawaii?
W) Felsic X) Andesitic Y) Basaltic Z) Picritic
ANSWER: Y) BASALTIC
10) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice
W) Radio telescope
X) Refracting telescope Y) Reflecting telescope Z) Hubble telescope
ANSWER: X) REFRACTING TELESCOPE
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
What type of lava flows can be observed at the volcanic hot
BONUS
What type of telescope uses convex lenses to bend light?

TOSS-UP
11) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following organisms is known to only produce a small number of offspring at a time?
W) Frog
X) Oyster
Y) Fruit fly
Z) Chimpanzee
ANSWER: Z) CHIMPANZEE

BONUS
11) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of a change in the primary
structure of a protein?
W) An amino acid substitution
X) A protein folding into a beta sheet Y) A disulfide bond exchange
Z) Subunits of a protein dimerizing
ANSWER: W) AN AMINO ACID SUBSTITUTION



TOSS-UP
12) Math Short Answer Donna rolls two standard dice. What is the most likely sum of the results of the two dice?
ANSWER: 7

BONUS
12) Math Short Answer You are given the following list of 9 numbers: 71, 80, 93, 101, 83, 19, 54, 80,
74. Calculate the difference between the median and mode.
ANSWER: 0










TOSS-UP
13) Energy Short Answer Landfills are a potential source of what kind of biofuel?
ANSWER: BIOGAS (ACCEPT: VEGETABLE OIL, COOKING OIL)
BONUS
13) Energy Short Answer Identify all of the following three units that correspond to energy: 1) Watts; 2) Joules; 3) Kilowatt-hours.
ANSWER: 2 AND 3


TOSS-UP
14) Math Short Answer How many vertices does a pentagonal prism have? ANSWER: 10
BONUS
14) Math  Multiple Choice Sherman�s car holds 20 gallons of gas. He drove 375 miles, using 3/4 of a tank. How many miles per gallon does his car get?
W) 20 X) 25 Y) 30 Z) 35
ANSWER: X) 25


TOSS-UP
15) Life Science Multiple Choice In bean and corn seeds, the food supply that is used by the seed to germinate and grow is found in the:
W) Cotyledon [kot-uhl-ee-dun]
X) Root tip
Y) Abcission zone [ab-sis-shun zone] Z) Petiole [pet-ee-ohl]
ANSWER: W) COTYLEDON


BONUS
15) Life Science  Short Answer Identify all of the following four choices that would not be visible under a standard laboratory light microscope when visualizing a plant cell:
1) DNA; 2) Ribosome; 3) Cell wall; 4) Chloroplast.
ANSWER: 1 AND 2


TOSS-UP
16) Earth and Space  Short Answer What layer of the mantle is found below the lithosphere? ANSWER: ASTHENOSPHERE
BONUS
16) Earth and Space  Short Answer Order the following four choices from lowest altitude to highest altitude: 1) Weather balloon; 2) Mesosphere; 3) Contrails; 4) Aurora Borealis.
ANSWER: 3, 1, 2, 4

TOSS-UP
17) General Science  Short Answer The movement of lithospheric plates over the asthenosphere is explained by which theory?
ANSWER: CONTINENTAL DRIFT
BONUS
17) General Science  Multiple Choice When crossing two heterozygous plants, what percentage of the offspring do you expect to be homozygous?
W) 0 X) 25 Y) 50 Z) 75
ANSWER: Y) 50

TOSS-UP
18) Physical Science  Multiple Choice A balanced chemical equation must possess which of the following?
W) The same number of molecules on both sides of the equation
X) The same kinds of molecules on both sides of the equation
Y) The same number of each kind of atom on both sides of the equation Z) The same leading coefficient on both sides of the equation
ANSWER: Y) THE SAME NUMBER OF EACH KIND OF ATOM ON BOTH SIDES OF THE EQUATION
BONUS
18) Physical Science  Short Answer What statistical law of thermodynamics states that entropy increases in a closed system?
ANSWER: SECOND LAW OF THERMODYNAMICS

TOSS-UP

19) Life Science Multiple Choice A nucleotide contains all except which of the following?
W) Phosphate group X) 5-carbon sugar Y) Nitrogenous base Z) Amino acid
ANSWER: Z)AMINOACID

BONUS
19) Life Science  Short Answer What group of plants, characterized by the presence of bundle-sheath
and mesophyll cells, is adapted to photosynthesis in arid conditions?
ANSWER: C4 PLANTS

TOSS-UP
20) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice Ar�tes [a-reets] and drumlins are formed by what agent of weathering?
W) Stream flow X) Winds
Y) Glaciers
Z) Precipitation
ANSWER: Y) GLACIERS

BONUS
20) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice An example of a source region for continental arctic air is:
W) Mexican plateau
X) Gulf of Alaska
Y) Northern Great Plains of the United States Z) Siberia
ANSWER: Z) SIBERIA

TOSS-UP
21) Physical Science  Multiple Choice An electron in the second main energy level and the second sublevel of an atom is described by which of the following orbital designations?
W) 1s X) 2s Y) 1p Z) 2p
ANSWER: Z) 2p

BONUS
21) Physical Science  Multiple Choice Which of the following is the oxidation number of fluorine gas?
W) -1 X) 0 Y) +1 Z) +2
ANSWER: X) 0

TOSS-UP
22) Math Short Answer The measure of angle B in isosceles trapezoid BIRD [B-I-R-D] is 40 degrees. What is the measure, in degrees, of angle R?
ANSWER: 140
BONUS
22) Math Short Answer Order the following three numbers from least to greatest: 1) 42%; 2) 0.402; 3) 2/5.
ANSWER: 2/5; 0.402; 42% (ACCEPT: 3, 2, 1)

TOSS-UP
23) General Science Short Answer If a microscope has an ocular lens with a magnification of 10 and an objective lens with a magnification of 40, what is the overall magnification?
ANSWER: 400
BONUS
23) General Science Short Answer What is the name of the process in which sediments compact under pressure and gradually become solid rock?
ANSWER: LITHIFICATION

