ROUND 17A
          TOSS-UP
1) Energy Short Answer What technology is designed to harvest energy from the thermal gradient in the oceans?
ANSWER: OTEC (ACCEPT: OCEAN THERMAL ENERGY CONVERSION) BONUS
1) Energy  Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT possible using a solar box cooker?
W) Boiling water
X) Sterilizing water
Y) Pasteurizing milk
Z) Purifying anhydrous ethanol
ANSWER: Z) PURIFYING ANHYDROUS ETHANOL
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
2) Physical Science  Multiple Choice
W) Linear
X) Bent
Y) Trigonal pyramidal Z) Tetrahedral
ANSWER: Z) TETRAHEDRAL
2) Physical Science  Short Answer a new wavelet?
ANSWER: HUYGEN�S PRINCIPLE
TOSS-UP
What is the molecular geometry of methane?
BONUS
What principle states that each point on a wave front is a source of
Round 17A ~ Page 1
3) Math Short Answer and denominator 25/72.
ANSWER: 2 AND 2/5
TOSS-UP
Express the following as a mixed number: the fraction with numerator 5/6
BONUS
  3) Math Short Answer
meters and 18 meters along the base and 17 meters in height.
ANSWER: 1734
Find the volume, in cubic meters, of a rectangular pyramid measuring 17
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
4) Life Science  Short Answer Identify all of the following three organisms that are considered gastropods: 1) Snails; 2) Clam; 3) Squid.
ANSWER: 1
4) Life Science Multiple Choice eukaryotes?
W) Flagella
X) Ribosomes
Y) Mitochondria
Z) Plasma membrane
ANSWER: Y) MITOCHONDRIA
BONUS
Which of the following are not found in both prokaryotes and
Round 17A ~ Page 2
TOSS-UP
5) Earth and Space  Short Answer Type IA [ONE-A] supernovas are associated with what type of star? ANSWER: WHITE DWARF
5) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice
W) Chalcocite [kal-kuh-site] X) Malachite [mal-uh-kite] Y) Sphalerite [sfah-luh-right] Z) Dolomite
ANSWER: Y) SPHALERITE
BONUS
Which of the following is an ore of zinc?
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
6) General Science  Short Answer What mechanism controls the passage of substances from the blood to the cerebrospinal fluid and is a structure composed of astrocytes?
ANSWER: BLOOD-BRAIN BARRIER
BONUS
6) General Science  Short Answer What term describes the change in displacement per unit time? ANSWER: VELOCITY (DO NOT ACCEPT: SPEED)
Round 17A ~ Page 3
7) Life Science Multiple Choice reproductive system?
TOSS-UP
Which of the following hormones plays a major role in the male
W) Androgens
X) Estrogens
Y) Mineralocorticoids Z) Glucocorticoids
ANSWER: W) ANDROGENS
7) Life Science  Short Answer ANSWER: SPORES
BONUS
What reproductive cells do ferns release into the air?
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
Oil components are separated using what process?
8) Energy  Multiple Choice
W) Evaporation
X) Fractional distillation Y) Fracking
Z) Chromatography
ANSWER: X) FRACTIONAL DISTILLATION
BONUS
8) Energy Short Answer The U.S. Department of Energy has created safety measures for the disposal of compact fluorescent lightbulbs because they contain what hazardous element?
ANSWER: MERCURY
Round 17A ~ Page 4
9) Physical Science  Multiple Choice visible light range with:
W) One color line X) Two color lines Y) Three color lines Z) Four color lines
ANSWER: Z) FOUR COLOR LINES
9) Physical Science  Multiple Choice
W) Only in sound waves
X) Only in longitudinal waves Y) Only in transverse waves Z) In all types of waves
TOSS-UP
Hydrogen, with its one electron, produces a line spectrum in the
BONUS
The Doppler effect occurs:
ANSWER: Z) IN ALL TYPES OF WAVES
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
10) Earth and Space  Short Answer ANSWER: SOLAR WIND
10) Earth and Space  Short Answer ANSWER: DESERT
TOSS-UP
A bowshock is found where a planet's magnetic field deflects what?
BONUS
Xerophytes are plants most likely to be found in what biome?
Round 17A ~ Page 5
TOSS-UP
11) Math Short Answer Points A, B, and C all lie on circle O. What is the measure of Angle ABC in degrees if it intercepts an arc of 112�?
ANSWER: 56
BONUS
11) Math Short Answer Convert 102 in base 10 to base 7. ANSWER: 204
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
TOSS-UP
12) General Science  Multiple Choice Which of the following terms is used to describe substances that reduce pain without causing unconsciousness?
W) Analgesic [an-uhl-jee-sik] X) Anesthetic
Y) Astringent
Z) Anaboloid
ANSWER: W) ANALGESIC
12) General Science  Short Answer
lower the activation energy, thus making it proceed faster?
ANSWER: CATALYST
BONUS
Which general type of material is added to a reaction in order to
TOSS-UP
13) Math Short Answer What fraction is halfway between 1/5th and 1/3rd on the number line? ANSWER: 4/15th
BONUS
13)Math Short Answer If b and c satisfy the system of equations 6b+7=12c and 3b-9c=4,what is c?
ANSWER: -5/2 (ACCEPT: -2.5, -2 1/2)

TOSS-UP
14) Life Science  Short Answer What genomic elements are capable of moving randomly throughout the genome?
ANSWER: TRANSPOSONS (ACCEPT: JUMPING GENES)
BONUS
14) Life Science  Short Answer What type of virus solely infects bacteria? ANSWER: BACTERIOPHAGES (ACCEPT: PHAGES)
Round 17A ~ Page 7
15) Energy Short Answer ANSWER: CRACKING
15) Energy Short Answer what?
TOSS-UP
What process breaks down heavy hydrocarbons into smaller ones?
BONUS
The Fischer-Tropsch process converts hydrogen and carbon dioxide into
ANSWER: HYDROCARBONS
                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
16) Physical Science  Multiple Choice most chemically stable?
W) [He]2s1 [H-E-2-S-1]
X) [He]2s2 [H-E-2-S-2]
Y) [He]2s22p5 [H-E-2-S-2-P-5]
Z) [He] 2s22p6 [H-E-2-S-2-2-P-6]
ANSWER: Z) [He]2s22p6
16) Physical Science  Multiple Choice the following?
TOSS-UP
Which of the following electron configurations would be the
BONUS
A permanent magnet has magnetic properties due to which of
W) The magnetic fields of its electrons are balanced X) Magnetic monopoles accumulate at the ends
Y) The magnetic domains have parallel magnetizations Z) Its magnetic dipole moment is zero
ANSWER: Y) THE MAGNETIC DOMAINS HAVE PARALLEL MAGNETIZATIONS

TOSS-UP

17) General Science  Multiple Choice Taxol is a drug used to treat which of the following disorders?
W) Malaria
X) Cystic fibrosis Y) Tuberculosis Z) Cancer
ANSWER: Z) CANCER
BONUS
17) General Science  Short Answer A Hall-Heroult cell is used industrially for the extraction of what metal?
ANSWER: ALUMINUM
TOSS-UP
18) Earth and Space  Short Answer What interstellar clouds consist of neutral hydrogen?
ANSWER: HI REGIONS
BONUS
18) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice Which of the following correctly explains why liquid fuel rockets are preferred over solid fuel rockets for long term space missions?
W) Liquid fuel rockets can store more fuel
X) The use of liquid fuel rockets can be stopped and restarted Y) Liquid fuel is safer than solid fuel
Z) Liquid fuel is less volatile than solid fuel
ANSWER: X) THE USE OF LIQUID FUEL ROCKETS CAN BE STOPPED AND RESTARTED


19) Math Short Answer What is the greatest common factor of the terms in the polynomial 3x^2*y^2 + 12yz^2 + 6x(y^3)z?
ANSWER: 3y
TOSS-UP

BONUS
19) Math Short Answer Jason needs to buy 2 pairs of jeans and 4 shirts. Jeans costs $15.24 and shirts
cost $12.56. He gave the cashier $100 and received his change. If he also wants to buy a coat that costs $30.75, how much more money does he need?
ANSWER: $11.47


TOSS-UP
20) Physical Science  Short Answer Identify all of the following units that are considered SI units: 1) Kilogram; 2) Metric ton; 3) Fahrenheit.
ANSWER: 1
BONUS
20) Physical Science  Short Answer You are standing 100 meters from a concrete wall and your friend Billy is 200 meters farther away, on the same side of the wall. When you make a loud, barbaric yelling sound, Billy hears both the original sound and the echo. If the speed of sound in air is taken to be 300 meters per second, what is the difference in time, in seconds as a decimal rounded to the hundredths place, between when Billy hears the original yell versus the echoed yell off of the concrete building?
ANSWER: 0.67

TOSS-UP
21) General Science  Multiple Choice In the brain, the occipital lobe is primarily involved in which bodily function?
W) Movement
X) Vision
Y) Body sensation Z) Hearing
ANSWER: X) VISION


BONUS
21) General Science  Short Answer What extract from red seaweed is used as a gelling agent in
microbiology labs for making bacterial cell cultures?
ANSWER: AGAR

TOSS-UP
22) Earth and Space  Short Answer What type of optical aberration occurs because different wavelengths of light have slightly different indices of refraction?
ANSWER: CHROMATIC ABERRATION
BONUS
22) Earth and Space  Short Answer What kind of particles will be detected in a massive surge just before a supernova?
ANSWER: NEUTRINOS


TOSS-UP
23) Life Science  Short Answer Sharks are in the class Chondricthyes [kon-drik-theez], because they have a skeleton made of what substance?
ANSWER: CARTILAGE
BONUS
23) Life Science  Short Answer What type of plant cells have thin, flexible primary walls and perform most of the metabolic functions of the plant?
ANSWER: PARENCHYMA
Round 17A ~ Page 12
