TOSS-UP
1) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice Which of the following is a scale of earthquake intensity?
W) Saffir-Simpson
X) Fujita
Y) EF-scale
Z) Moment magnitude
ANSWER: Z) MOMENT MAGNITUDE

BONUS
1) Earth and Space  Short Answer What is the term for subsoil that remains frozen year round?
ANSWER: PERMAFROST

TOSS-UP
2) General Science  Multiple Choice Which of the following is the study of spiders?
W) Arachnology [air-ack-nol-oh-gee]
X) Dendrochronology [den-dro-chron-ol-oh-gee] Y) Planktology
Z) Lepidopterology [lep-uh-dop-ter-ol-oh-gee]
ANSWER: W) ARACHNOLOGY

BONUS
2) General Science  Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of a high-altitude cloud type?
W) Altostratus X) Stratocumulus Y) Stratus
Z) Cirrocumulus
ANSWER: Z) CIRROCUMULUS


TOSS-UP
3) Physical Science  Multiple Choice Which of the following is formed when three atoms combine to produce a single unit of a larger substance?
W) Nucleus X) Mixture Y) Solution Z) Molecule
ANSWER:Z) MOLECULE

BONUS
3) Physical Science  Short Answer Identify all of the following four quantities that are considered
vector quantities: 1) Mass; 2) Velocity; 3) Speed; 4) Acceleration.
ANSWER: 2 AND 4


TOSS-UP
4) Life Science  Short Answer What infectious particles consist of nucleic acids packaged into a protein coat?
ANSWER: VIRUS

BONUS
4) Life Science Multiple Choice Eukaryotic and prokaryotic cells both contain:
W) Cytoplasmic organelles X) Nuclear membrane
Y) Cell membrane
Z) Chromosomal proteins
ANSWER: Y) CELL MEMBRANE


TOSS-UP
5) Energy Short Answer What are the two gases used to power the first generation fuel cell cars? ANSWER: HYDROGENANDOXYGEN
BONUS
5) Energy Short Answer To the nearest ten percent, what percent of the sun�s energy that hits the Earth is reflected back into space?
ANSWER: 30

TOSS-UP
6) Math  Multiple Choice What is the distance of the point (2, 3) from the origin?
W) Square root of 5 X) Square root of 13 Y) 5
Z) 13
ANSWER: X) SQUARE ROOT OF 13

BONUS
6) Math Short Answer Given the linear function f(x) = 3x + b, if f(-1) = 7, what is f(5)?
ANSWER: 25


TOSS-UP
7) Earth and Space  Short Answer Scientists were able to determine that the outer core of the Earth is a liquid because what seismic waves cannot pass through it?
ANSWER: SECONDARY WAVES (ACCEPT: S-WAVES)

BONUS
7) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice Which of the following features is created by a volcano?
W) Fjord X) Caldera Y) Moraine Z) Esker
ANSWER: X) CALDERA

TOSS-UP
8) Physical Science  Multiple Choice In a vacuum, all photons have the same:
W) Speed
X) Frequency Y) Wavelength Z) Energy
ANSWER: W) SPEED

BONUS
8) Physical Science  Short Answer What is the efficiency of an engine that consumes 7500 Joules of
energy to load a box that requires 4500 Joules of work?
ANSWER: 60%

TOSS-UP
9) General Science  Multiple Choice What astronomical measurement is analogous to latitude?
W) Declination
X) Right ascension Y) Conjunction
Z) Superposition
ANSWER: W) DECLINATION

BONUS
9) General Science  Short Answer Halite is composed of what two elements?
ANSWER: SODIUM AND CHLORINE (Accept: Na AND Cl)

TOSS-UP
10) Math Short Answer A father's age is twice that of his son. Expressed as a fraction, what is the ratio of the son's age to the father's age?
ANSWER: 1/2
BONUS
10) Math Short Answer If x and y are positive, simplify the following expression: the fraction with numerator 4x5y�1 and denominator 3x�4y2.
ANSWER: (4x9)/(3y3)


TOSS-UP
11) Energy Short Answer Most gasoline in the United States is E10, meaning that 10% of its content is made up of what?
ANSWER: ETHANOL

BONUS
11) Energy  Multiple Choice Which of the following countries generates the highest percentage of its electricity by nuclear power?
W) Japan
X) France
Y) United States Z) Russia
ANSWER: X) FRANCE

TOSS-UP
12) Life Science  Short Answer By what process does a mother cell split into two genetically identical daughter cells?
ANSWER: MITOSIS

BONUS
12) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following types of plant cell tissue is considered most important for structural support?
W) Mesophyll
X) Parenchyma [pahr-ehn-ky-muh] Y) Collenchyma [cohl-ehn-ky-muh] Z) Sclerenchyma [skleh-rehn-ky-muh]
ANSWER: Z) SCLERENCHYMA

TOSS-UP
13) Math Short Answer For what value of x does the graph of the function y = -5x + 15 cross the x-axis?
ANSWER: 3

BONUS
13) Math Short Answer What two numbers have a sum of 36 and a product of 323?
ANSWER: 17 AND 19

TOSS-UP
14) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following pairs of structures both contain linear DNA?
W) Animal cell nucleus and chloroplast
X) Animal cell nucleus and plant cell nucleus Y) Fungal cell nucleus and mitochondria
Z) Mitochondria and bacteria
ANSWER: X) ANIMAL CELL NUCLEUS AND PLANT CELL NUCLEUS

BONUS
14) Life Science  Short Answer What green pigment gives plants their color? ANSWER: CHLOROPHYLL

TOSS-UP
15) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice Which of the following variables is most responsible for lake stratification?
W) Wind
X) Biological activity Y) Temperature
Z) Current
ANSWER: Y) TEMPERATURE

BONUS
15) Earth and Space  Short Answer What is the term for the days during which the Sun is furthest south or north of the equator?
ANSWER: SOLSTICES

TOSS-UP
16) General Science  Multiple Choice Which of the following causes the Coriolis Effect?
W) Mesospheric winds
X) Strong electric field gradients Y) Tidal forces
Z) The Earth�s easterly rotation
ANSWER: Z) THE EARTH�S EASTERLY ROTATION

BONUS
16) General Science  Short Answer What term is used to describe the ever-increasing amount of �disorder� in the universe?
ANSWER: ENTROPY

TOSS-UP
17) Physical Science  Multiple Choice A cubic centimeter of water has a mass of almost exactly one of which of the following?
W) Milliliter X) Kilogram Y) Gram
Z) Fluid ounce
ANSWER: Y) GRAM

BONUS
17) Physical Science  Short Answer What is the chemical formula of magnesium nitrate? ANSWER: Mg(NO3)2

TOSS-UP
18) Energy  Multiple Choice Which of the following materials yields the greatest percentage reduction in energy to manufacture when it is made from recycled material rather than from raw materials?
W) Aluminum X) Glass
Y) Newsprint Z) Plastics
ANSWER: W)ALUMINUM

BONUS
18) Energy Short Answer What is the term for the total energy used to manufacture a finished product, including the energy to extract raw materials from nature, plus the energy used in primary and secondary manufacturing activities?
ANSWER: EMBODIED ENERGY (ACCEPT: EMBEDDED ENERGY)
TOSS-UP
19) Physical Science  Multiple Choice Water is formed when oxygen and hydrogen undergo what process?
W) Homogeneous mixture X) Hydrophobic reaction
Y) Chemical reaction
Z) Spontaneous condensation
ANSWER: Y) CHEMICAL REACTION
BONUS
19) Physical Science  Short Answer How many bonds exists between two nitrogen atoms in dinitrogen gas?
ANSWER: THREE
TOSS-UP
20) Math Short Answer In how many different orders can you play 5 songs once each?
ANSWER: 120

BONUS
20) Math  Multiple Choice Which of the following equations represents a line with slope of 7/5?
W) 5x + 7y - 11 = 0
X) 7x = -5y - 12
Y) 7x - 5y = 14
Z) 7y/5 = x + 4
ANSWER: Y) 7x - 5y = 14

TOSS-UP
21) Life Science Short Answer Sand dollars, sea stars, sea cucumbers, and sea urchins all belong to what phyla?
ANSWER: ECHINODERMATA

BONUS
21) Life Science Short Answer Rubisco can use oxygen as a substrate in a process known as what?
ANSWER: PHOTORESPIRATION

TOSS-UP
22) General Science Multiple Choice A lunar eclipse occurs when:
W) The moon casts a shadow on the earth
X) The earth casts a shadow on the moon
Y) The earth, sun, and moon form a 90o angle Z) The moon casts a shadow on the sun
ANSWER: X) THE EARTH CASTS A SHADOW ON THE MOON

BONUS
22) General Science  Short Answer Alfred Wegener proposed what theory, which suggested that 200 million years ago, a supercontinent named Pangaea existed?
ANSWER: CONTINENTAL DRIFT

TOSS-UP
23) Earth and Space  Short Answer What is the term for exceptionally bright stars that are up to 1000 times the sun�s diameter?
ANSWER: SUPERGIANTS

BONUS
23) Earth and Space  Short Answer Most of the convection that occurs in the Earth occurs in what layer?
ANSWER: MANTLE


