TOSS-UP

1) Life Science Multiple Choice The difference between eukaryotic and prokaryotic cells, is that prokaryotic cells lack what organelle?
W) Cell membrane X) DNA
Y) Nucleus
Z) Ribosomes
ANSWER: Y) NUCLEUS

BONUS
1) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following biological molecules make up the main part
of the bilayer and hydrophobic region of the plasma cell membrane?
W) Oligosaccharides X) Carbohydrates Y) Phospholipids
Z) Proteins
ANSWER: Y) PHOSPHOLIPIDS



TOSS-UP
2) Math Short Answer Two to the 4th power divided by 2 to the 3rd power equals 2 to what power? ANSWER: 1st (ACCEPT: 1)
BONUS
2) Math  Multiple Choice Nick, Anna, and Sherry go on a vacation and agree to split the costs evenly. During the trip, Nick paid $105, Anna paid $125, and Sherry paid $175. In order to share the costs evenly, Nick gave Sherry x dollars and Anna gave Sherry y dollars. What is x + y?
W) 20 X) 30 Y) 40 Z) 50
ANSWER: Y) 40

TOSS-UP
3) Physical Science  Multiple Choice Which of the following defines a pure substance that cannot be broken down by any chemical means?
W) Compound X) Element
Y) Solid
Z) Solution
ANSWER: X) ELEMENT

BONUS
3) Physical Science  Short Answer How many lone pairs of electrons exist in a single water molecule?
ANSWER: TWO

TOSS-UP
4) Earth and Space  Short Answer In what two seasons do lakes undergo turnovers?
ANSWER: SPRING AND FALL (ACCEPT: AUTUMN IN PLACE OF FALL)

BONUS
4) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice The deepest known point of the oceans is found in which of the following?
W) Atlantic Ocean X) Pacific Ocean Y) Dead Sea
Z) North Sea
ANSWER: X) PACIFIC OCEAN

TOSS-UP
5) General Science  Multiple Choice A keystone species is:
W) Required for maintaining the health of an ecosystem X) Necessary for the survival of another species
Y) The last to go extinct after a disturbance
Z) The hardiest species in an ecosystem
ANSWER: W) REQUIRED FOR MAINTAINING THE HEALTH OF AN ECOSYSTEM

BONUS
5) General Science  Multiple Choice The property of metalloids which makes them useful in computer chips is their:
W) Brittle structure
X) Varying ability to conduct electricity Y) Somewhat reactive nature
Z) Hardness
ANSWER: X) VARYING ABILITY TO CONDUCT ELECTRICITY


TOSS-UP
6) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice Which of the following is true about spiral galaxies?
W) They emit mainly in the ultraviolet range of energy X) They are usually similar to our galaxy
Y) They originate from supernova explosions
Z) They typically contain a few thousand stars
ANSWER: X) THEY ARE USUALLY SIMILAR TO OUR GALAXY

BONUS
6) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice Which of the following stars can someone in North America see year-round?
W) Sirius
X) Rigel
Y) Betelgeuse Z) Polaris
ANSWER: Z) POLARIS

TOSS-UP
7) General Science  Multiple Choice Which of the following is a group of organic compounds that is often added to foods to enhance flavors such as strawberry or banana and are also found in sweet- smelling flowers?
W) Amines
X) Esters
Y) Alcohols
Z) Halogenated hydrocarbons
ANSWER: X) ESTERS

BONUS
7) General Science  Short Answer To the nearest whole number, how many minutes does it take for the earth to rotate through one degree of longitude?
ANSWER: 4

TOSS-UP
8) Energy  Multiple Choice Approximately what percent of global energy production currently comes from renewable sources?
W) 1% X) 5% Y) 16% Z) 20%
ANSWER: Y) 16%

BONUS
8) Energy Short Answer What greenhouse gas is the simplest hydrocarbon?
ANSWER: METHANE

TOSS-UP
9) Physical Science  Multiple Choice What is the process of comparing a property of an object to a well-defined and agreed-upon referent?
W) Generalizing
X) Measurement
Y) Graphing
Z) Scientific Investigation
ANSWER: X) MEASUREMENT


BONUS
9) Physical Science  Short Answer What law or principle relates the applied force to the amount of
 elongation in a spring when these quantities are linearly related?
ANSWER: HOOKE'S LAW

TOSS-UP
10) Math Short Answer You spend a total of $21.43 at the store, but want to return an item with marked price $5.00. If the sales tax is 7%, how much will you receive back for the item?
ANSWER: $5.35
BONUS
10) Math Short Answer From a 7-cup package, a cat eats 1 and 3/5 cups of food on Tuesday and 23�4 cups on Wednesday. How many cups are left in the package?
ANSWER: 2 and 13/20 (ACCEPT: 2.65)

TOSS-UP
11) Life Science  Short Answer Female members of what order of animals contain pouches used to complete development of their young?
ANSWER: MARSUPIALIA
BONUS
11) Life Science  Short Answer What structures, composed of flexible tissue, connect two or more bones together at joints?
ANSWER: LIGAMENTS


TOSS-UP
12) General Science  Multiple Choice What type of map or chart is commonly used in navigation
 to eliminate distortion?
W) Sextant
X) Latitudinal Chart Y) North-up Map
Z) Mercator Projection
ANSWER: Z) MERCATOR PROJECTION

BONUS
12) General Science  Short Answer What is the SI base unit for measuring temperature? ANSWER: KELVIN (DO NOT ACCEPT: ANY ANSWER WITH �DEGREE� IN IT)

TOSS-UP
13) Earth and Space  Short Answer When a group of living organisms and non-living components in an environment interact as a system, what is the system called?
ANSWER: ECOSYSTEM
BONUS
13) Earth and Space  Short Answer What dark areas occur on the Sun due to intense magnetic activity? ANSWER: SUNSPOTS

TOSS-UP
14) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following is common to both bacteria and viruses?
W) Metabolism X) Ribosomes Y) Nucleic acids Z) Cell division
ANSWER: Y) NUCLEIC ACIDS

BONUS
14) Life Science  Short Answer What molecule is released from muscles as a waste product,
transported to the lungs in blood, and exhaled as a gas?
ANSWER: CARBON DIOXIDE (ACCEPT: CO2)

TOSS-UP
15) Physical Science  Multiple Choice Under what conditions does the behavior of real gases deviate most from that predicted by the ideal gas law?
W) Low Pressure, Low Temperature X) High Pressure, Low Temperature Y) Low Pressure, High Temperature Z) High Pressure, High Temperature
ANSWER: X) HIGH PRESSURE, LOW TEMPERATURE

BONUS
15) Physical Science  Multiple Choice A cubic meter is a measure of which of the following?
W) Weight X) Mass
Y) Distance Z) Volume
ANSWER: Z) VOLUME

TOSS-UP
16) Math Short Answer The sum of two numbers is 16. Their difference is 2. What are the numbers? ANSWER: 7, 9
BONUS
16) Math Short Answer Given that x represents a number for which the denominator is defined, simplify the following expression completely: the fraction with numerator x2 + 4x + 4 and denominator x2 � x � 6.
ANSWER: (x + 2)/(x � 3)


TOSS-UP
17) Energy Short Answer When creating electric current using steam, the electric generator is attached to what type of equipment that catches the steam to rotate the generator?
ANSWER: TURBINE
BONUS
17) Energy Short Answer What type of alternative energy production relies on energy provided by the Moon rather than energy provided by the Sun?
ANSWER: TIDAL (ACCEPT: TIDAL POWER, TIDAL ENERGY)


TOSS-UP
18) Math Short Answer Place the following 3 polyhedra in increasing order of the number of faces: 1) tetrahedron; 2) dodecahedron; 3) octahedron.
ANSWER: 1, 3, 2 (ACCEPT: TETRAHEDRON, OCTAHEDRON, DODECAHEDRON)
BONUS
18) Math Short Answer Triangle ABC is similar to Triangle DEF. If AB = 4, DE = 10, and EF = 15, what is the length of BC?
ANSWER: 6

TOSS-UP
19) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice the: The region of the atmosphere closest to the Earth's surface is
W) Thermosphere X) Ionosphere
Y) Troposphere Z) Stratosphere
ANSWER: Y) TROPOSPHERE

BONUS
19) Earth and Space Multiple Choice The temperature in the stratosphere increases with altitude due to absorption of what type of radiation?
W) Microwave X) Infrared
Y) Visible
Z) Ultraviolet
ANSWER: Z) ULTRAVIOLET

TOSS-UP
20) Life Science  Short Answer To what class do humans belong?
ANSWER: MAMMALIA

BONUS
20) Life Science Multiple Choice Imagine that you conducted an experiment where you tested the effects of different fertilizers on plant growth over the course of one month. You have to present your data in a graph. What variable would you plot on the y-axis?
W) Time of year
X) Type of fertilizer Y) Day of experiment Z) Plant Height
ANSWER: Z) PLANT HEIGHT

TOSS-UP
21) General Science  Short Answer How many nodes are found in a 1s orbital? ANSWER: ZERO
BONUS
21) General Science  Multiple Choice To the nearest degree, how many degrees Fahrenheit is equivalent to 283 Kelvin?
W) 25 X) 46 Y) 50 Z) 58
ANSWER: Y) 50

TOSS-UP
22) Physical Science  Short Answer What is the term for the time required for a vibrating object to complete one full cycle?
ANSWER: PERIOD

BONUS
22) Physical Science  Multiple Choice The ejection of an alpha particle from a nucleus results in which of the following?
W) An increase in the atomic number by one X) An increase in the mass number by four Y) A decrease in the atomic number by two Z) A decrease in the mass number by two
ANSWER: Y) A DECREASE IN THE ATOMIC NUMBER BY TWO

TOSS-UP
23) Energy Multiple Choice Clean coal research is currently NOT focused on which of the following?
W) Improving the purity of coal ore
X) Increasing efficiency of power plants using coal
Y) Capturing carbon generated when burning coal
Z) Reusing carbon dioxide generated when burning coal
ANSWER: W) IMPROVING THE PURITY OF COAL ORE

BONUS
23) Energy Multiple Choice As an energy source, fuel cells have all of the following advantages over conventional sources except for which one?
W) Virtually pollution free X) Operate very quietly Y) Highly efficient
Z) Low cost
ANSWER: Z) LOW COST

