ROUND 9A
TOSS-UP
1) Life Science Multiple Choice In the process of meiosis, which of the following is the end product?
W) One parent cell becomes two daughter cells X) One parent cell becomes four daughter cells Y) Two parent cells become one daughter cell Z) Two parent cells become two daughter cells
ANSWER: X) ONE PARENT CELL BECOMES FOUR DAUGHTER CELLS

BONUS
1) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following terms is used to describe a change in cell structure and function from generalized to specialized?
W) Differentiation X) Development Y) Morphogenesis Z) Growth
ANSWER: W) DIFFERENTIATION


TOSS-UP
2) Math Short Answer Simplify the following expression: open parenthesis 2x^2 close parenthesis squared.
ANSWER: 4x^4
BONUS


2) Math Short Answer Identify all of the following three statements regarding quadratic equations
with real coefficients that are universally true: 1) When the discriminant is zero, the roots are real; 2) When the discriminant is positive, the roots are equal; 3) When the discriminant is positive, the roots are imaginary.
ANSWER: 1

TOSS-UP
3) Physical Science  Multiple Choice An electrical generator converts:
W) Solar energy to electric energy
X) Thermal energy to electric energy
Y) Chemical energy to electric energy
Z) Mechanical energy to electric energy
ANSWER: Z) MECHANICAL ENERGY TO ELECTRIC ENERGY

BONUS
3) Physical Science  Short Answer Identify all of the following three processes that are considered phase changes: 1) Sodium reacting with water and producing hydrogen gas; 2) Gold melting at high temperatures; 3) Carbon dioxide depositing to dry ice at low temperatures.
ANSWER: 2 AND 3

TOSS-UP
4) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice The objects that Carl Seyfert [say-fert] observed are examples of what?
W) Variable stars X) Galaxies
Y) Filaments
Z) Clusters
ANSWER: X) GALAXIES

BONUS
4) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice Ablation by sunlight would primarily affect which of the following objects?
W) Pluton
X) Volcano
Y) Glacier
Z) Thunderstorm
ANSWER: Y) GLACIER

TOSS-UP
5) General Science  Short Answer What is the term used to describe the dark, smooth areas of the moon, previously thought to be bodies of water?
ANSWER: MARIA (ACCEPT: MARE)
BONUS
5) General Science  Short Answer Magnetrons are generally found in which home device?
ANSWER: MICROWAVE OVENS

TOSS-UP
6) Math Short Answer Identify all of the following three numbers that are rational: 1) 6/9; 2) (�8) divided by (�2); 3) (�81) divided by 5
ANSWER: ALL OF THEM
BONUS
6) Math  Multiple Choice Anna buys used books for x dollars per dozen and sells them for x/9 dollars per book. If she buys the books for $72 per dozen, what is her profit per book?
W) 1 dollar X) 2 dollars Y) 3 dollars Z) 4 dollars
Answer: X) 2 DOLLARS


TOSS-UP
7) Physical Science  Short Answer A high-speed electron ejected from a nucleus during radioactive decay is referred to as what?
ANSWER: BETA PARTICLE (ACCEPT: BETA MINUS PARTICLE)
BONUS
7) Physical Science  Short Answer A coin weighs 3.5 grams and when placed in water, displaces a volume of 0.50 milliliters. To two significant figures, what is the density of the coin in grams per milliliter?
ANSWER: 7.0

TOSS-UP
8) Energy  Multiple Choice What state produces the most coal in the U.S.?
W) California X) Wyoming Y) Texas
Z) Iowa
ANSWER: X) WYOMING

BONUS
8) Energy Short Answer What type of energy generation involves the usage of radioactive actinides?
ANSWER: NUCLEAR

TOSS-UP
9) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice What is the term for igneous activity that occurs below the Earth's surface?
W) Plutonic
X) Extrusive
Y) Unconformed Z) Conformed
ANSWER: W) PLUTONIC

BONUS
9) Earth and Space  Short Answer What is the term for a catastrophic explosion of a massive star?
ANSWER: SUPERNOVA

TOSS-UP
10) Life Science Multiple Choice Which of the following is a vascular plant?
W) Spanish moss X) Oak tree
Y) Green algae Z) Fern lichen
ANWER: X) OAK TREE

BONUS
10) Life Science  Short Answer What structural polysaccharide is found in fungal cell walls and the exoskeletons of insects?
ANSWER: CHITIN

TOSS-UP
11) General Science  Multiple Choice While there are over 300 species of sharks in the ocean, approximately what percentage are "vicious" or are known to attack unprovoked?
W) 2 X) 5 Y) 10 Z) 25
ANSWER: W) 2

BONUS
11) General Science  Short Answer To the nearest whole foot, how many feet does light travel in one nanosecond?
ANSWER: ONE

TOSS-UP
12) Earth and Space  Short Answer What two planets in the Solar System do not have any moons? ANSWER: MERCURY AND VENUS

BONUS
12) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice Which of the following types of rocks hosts the best-preserved fossils?
W) Conglomerate
X) Sandstone
Y) Breccia [brech-ee-uh] Z) Black shale
ANSWER: Z) BLACK SHALE

TOSS-UP
13) General Science  Multiple Choice Growth of plants in the ocean is generally limited by which of the following?
W) Salt and sunlight
X) Oxygen and carbon
Y) Nitrogen and phosphorus
Z) Hydrogen and sulfur
ANSWER: Y) NITROGEN AND PHOSPHORUS
BONUS
13) General Science  Short Answer Rectification is the conversion of alternating current to direct current. What process converts direct current to alternating current?
ANSWER: INVERSION

TOSS-UP
14) Life Science  Short Answer Identify all of the following organisms that are considered autotrophs: 1) plants; 2) cyanobacteria; 3) humans.
ANSWER: 1 AND 2 (ACCEPT: PLANTS AND CYANOBACTERIA)
BONUS
14) Life Science  Short Answer What type of molecules are secreted by the endocrine system? ANSWER: HORMONES
Round 9A ~ Page 7
TOSS-UP
15) Physical Science  Short Answer What is the molar volume, to the nearest tenth of a liter, of an ideal gas at standard pressure?
ANSWER: 22.4

BONUS
15) Physical Science  Multiple Choice The chemical behavior of an atom is determined by its:
W) Atomic number
X) Nuclear binding energy Y) Mass number
Z) Number of isotopes
ANSWER: W) ATOMIC NUMBER

TOSS-UP
16) Math Short Answer A circle has a circumference of 6pi. What is its radius?
ANSWER: 3

BONUS
16)Math Short Answer  Given that f=-1,g=7,and h=-10,what is h^2 +fgh?
ANSWER: 170






Round 9A ~ Page 8
TOSS-UP
17) Energy Short Answer Coal can be burned to produce energy. It can also be chemically combined with oxygen or air in a more controlled way that yields lower harmful gas emissions. What is this alternative method of processing coal for energy called?
ANSWER: COAL GASIFICATION (ACCEPT: GASIFICATION)
BONUS
17) Energy Short Answer In geologic sequestration, carbon dioxide is often pumped back into the ground to replace other substances that are being removed. Identify all of the following replacements that are currently taking place: 1) CO2 replaces methane gas; 2) CO2 replaces crude oil; 3) CO2 replaces potable water.
ANSWER: 1 and 2

TOSS-UP
18) Math  Multiple Choice Laura wants to find the distance between two cities. The distance on a map is 18 inches. The scale on the map is 3 inches to 5 miles. How many miles is it between the two cities?
W) 5 miles X) 15 miles Y) 30 miles Z) 40 miles
ANSWER: Y) 30 MILES

BONUS
18) Math Short Answer What is the area of a trapezoid with the following properties: its altitude is 12,
and it has parallel sides of length 25 and 50, with nonparallel opposite sides of length 15 and 20?
ANSWER: 450


TOSS-UP
19) Physical Science  Multiple Choice A chemical change occurs when a substance:
W) Changes state
X) Gains or loses electrons Y) Reaches its boiling point Z) Is ground into a powder
ANSWER: X) GAINS OR LOSES ELECTRONS

BONUS
19) Physical Science  Short Answer The energy associated with a photon is related to its frequency by what fundamental physical constant?
ANSWER: PLANCK'S CONSTANT

TOSS-UP
20) Life Science  Short Answer What fluid fills the spaces between cells in animals?
ANSWER: INTERSTITIAL FLUID (ACCEPT: EXTRACELLULAR FLUID)
BONUS
20) Life Science Short Answer What parts of plants, located at the tips of the roots and shoots, contain cells that are actively growing in length?
ANSWER: MERISTEMS

TOSS-UP
21) General Science  Short Answer What graduated piece of glassware is used for delivering known volume of a liquid, especially during titrations?
ANSWER: BURETTE
BONUS
21) General Science  Short Answer What country is the world's leading overall emitter of greenhouse gas?
ANSWER: CHINA

TOSS-UP
22) Earth and Space  Multiple Choice Which of the following cannot be classified as an igneous rock?
W) Granite X) Rhyolite Y) Coal
Z) Obsidian
Answer: Y) COAL

BONUS
22) Earth and Space  Short Answer What layer of the atmosphere is the transition between atmosphere and space?
ANSWER: EXOSPHERE

TOSS-UP
23) Energy Short Answer What is the source of most of the energy on Earth?
ANSWER: SUN

BONUS
23) Energy Short Answer The Advanced Light Source at the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory produces bright electromagnetic radiation in the ultraviolet range and what other range?
ANSWER: X-RAYS


