ROUND 2 TOSS-UP1) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common scientific term for a change in velocity over time?ANSWER: ACCELERATIONBONUS1) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the mass, in grams, of a 1 kilogram object on a planet with a gravitational force of 3 meters per second squared?ANSWER: 1,000TOSS-UP2) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What molecular substance is primarily responsible for moderating wide changes in temperatures on Earth?ANSWER: WATERBONUS2) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the process by which water vapor changes directly into rain:W) sublimation X) evaporation Y) transpiration Z) condensationANSWER: Z) CONDENSATION 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2Page 1
TOSS-UP3) MATH Short Answer What are the multiplicative inverse and additive inverse of ! 53 , respectively?ANSWER: MULTIPLICATIVE INVERSE = ! 53 ; ADDITIVE INVERSE = 53BONUS3) MATH Short Answer If 12 gallons of gasoline costs $36.00, what would 1 quart cost, in cents? ANSWER: 75 CENTSTOSS-UP4) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a coniferous tree:    W) poplar X) oakY) elmZ) firANSWER: Z) FIRBONUS4) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following pieces of laboratory glassware would be used to MOST accurately measure 1000 milliliters of water:W) 1000 milliliter volumetric flaskX) 1000 milliliter beakerY) 1000 milliliter Erlenmeyer flaskZ) two, 500 milliliter Erlenmeyer flasksANSWER: W) 1000 MILLILITER VOLUMETRIC FLASK2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2Page 2
TOSS-UP5) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Found in humans and quite prominent in dogs, what is the name of the conical-shaped tooth used in tearing muscle and other foods and assisting in cutting?ANSWER: CANINEBONUS5) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer How many canine teeth do humans typically have in early adulthood?ANSWER: 4TOSS-UP6) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following atomic properties most directly determines that elements in the same group of the Periodic Table have similar chemical properties:W) number of protonsX) number of valence electrons Y) charge of protonsZ) stability of neutronsANSWER: X) NUMBER OF VALENCE ELECTRONSBONUS6) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the atomic mass rounded to the nearest whole number and the net charge of an ion with 7 protons, 6 neutrons, and 8 electrons?ANSWER: ATOMIC MASS = 13; NET CHARGE = –1 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2 Page 3
TOSS-UP7) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is believed to be the process that causes Earth’s tectonic plates to move:W) convection currents in the crustX) convection currents in the mantleY) gravitational influence of the Sun and Moon directly on continental plates Z) volcanic activity along subduction zonesANSWER: X) CONVECTION CURRENTS IN THE MANTLEBONUS7) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which of the following locations would you typically expect the average salinity of surface sea water to be the LOWEST:W) in the Dead SeaX) in the waters off AntarcticaY) in the Chesapeake BayZ) at the mouth of the Mississippi RiverANSWER: Z) AT THE MOUTH OF THE MISSISSIPPI RIVERTOSS-UP8) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true: W) 23 – 3 × 2 = 17 X) 72 ÷ 9 – 3 = 5Y) 0.3 + 0.4 × 2 = 1.4 Z) 6 + 6 × 2 = 18ANSWER: Y) 0.3 + 0.4 × 2 = 1.4BONUS8) MATH Short Answer If on average 6 people drink two-thirds of a gallon of lemonade, how many people will drink 4 gallons?ANSWER: 362007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2 Page 4
TOSS-UP9) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What molecular substance is typically considered the most critical for life to exist on another planet?ANSWER: WATERBONUS9) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 organisms that are typically filter feeders in an aquatic environment: barnacles; corals; frogs; kelpANSWER: BARNACLES; CORALSTOSS-UP10) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer If the 4 main classes of biological molecules are protein, lipid, carbohydrate, and nucleic acid, which would butter be classified as?ANSWER: LIPIDBONUS10) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Cellulose is a polymer of what 6-carbon sugar? ANSWER: GLUCOSE 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2 Page 5
TOSS-UP11) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Order the following 3 liquids from the one with the LOWEST viscosity to the one with the HIGHEST viscosity at room temperature: pure olive oil; water; pure honeyANSWER: WATER; PURE OLIVE OIL; PURE HONEYBONUS11) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 choices that are compounds: water; antimony; carbon dioxide; mercuryANSWER: WATER AND CARBON DIOXIDETOSS-UP12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Rocks that are produced when magma cools and solidifies deep below the Earth’s crust are called: W) extrusive igneousX) intrusive igneousY) extrusive metamorphic Z) intrusive sedimentaryANSWER: X) INTRUSIVE IGNEOUSBONUS12) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Of the following 5 choices, name 2 that are igneous rocks: rock salt; granite; basalt; sandstone; gypsumANSWER: GRANITE AND BASALT2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2 Page 6
TOSS-UP13) MATH Short Answer Change the following mixed number into an improper fraction: 3 5 18ANSWER: 59 18BONUS13) MATH Short Answer Evaluate the following expression: –6 × 3 + –16 ÷ 4 ANSWER: –22TOSS-UP14) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Convert the following value into standard scientific notation: 0.00634 × 108ANSWER: 6.34 × 105BONUS14) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Multiply the following 2 values, giving your answer in the correct number of significant figures: 10.1 × 1.201ANSWER: 12.1   2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2 Page 7
TOSS-UP15) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Geotropism is a response of plants to what external force? ANSWER: GRAVITYBONUS15) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Flowering plants are grouped into what 2 classes named after their number of seed leaves?ANSWER: MONOCOTS AND DICOTS (ACCEPT: MONOCOTYLEDONS AND DICOTYLEDONS )TOSS-UP16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the scientific term for a drink that settles and needs to be shaken to redistribute the particles throughout the drink: W) homogenous X) solventY) suspension Z) colloidANSWER: Y) SUSPENSIONBONUS16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the ideal mechanical advantage of a single fixed pulley?ANSWER: 12007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2 Page 8
TOSS-UP17) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer The lithosphere is made up of the uppermost mantle and what other layer?ANSWER: CRUST (ACCEPT: CONTINENTAL AND/OR OCEANIC CRUST)BONUS17) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Volcanoes and earthquakes occur primarily in which of the following locations:W) along plate boundariesX) along continental shelvesY) at the North and South Poles Z) around the Hawaiian IslandsANSWER: W) ALONG PLATE BOUNDARIESTOSS-UP18) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:W) two numbers are reciprocals if their product is 1X) one-half of three quarters is three eighthsY) a whole number is divisible by 5 if the ‘ones’ digit is 0 or 5Z) an example of a proper fraction is 64ANSWER: Z) AN EXAMPLE OF A PROPER FRACTION IS 64BONUS18) MATH Short Answer What is the sum of all odd one-digit prime positive numbers? ANSWER: 15   2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2Page 9
TOSS-UP19) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following are sometimes called “big dirty snowballs” because of their composition:W) cometsX) asteroidsY) meteorites Z) dwarf planetsANSWER: W) COMETSBONUS19) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true about comets:W) to Earth-bound observers, comets glow because they are nearing Earth’s atmosphere X) they typically have elliptical orbitsY) the Deep Impact probe recently struck a cometZ) the solid part of a comet is called the nucleusANSWER: W) TO EARTH-BOUND OBSERVERS, COMETS GLOW BECAUSE THEY ARE NEARING EARTH’S ATMOSPHERETOSS-UP20) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the location of the biceps humoris muscle: W) chestX) legY) abdomen Z) armANSWER: Z) ARMBONUS20) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What general type of human blood vessel returns blood to the heart?ANSWER: VEIN2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2 Page 10
TOSS-UP21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer How many protons does the heaviest isotope of hydrogen have?ANSWER: 1BONUS21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Distillation depends mostly upon what physical property?ANSWER: BOILING POINT (ACCEPT: CONDENSATION POINT)TOSS-UP22) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Chalk is a type of: W) limestone X) coalY) rock salt Z) basaltANSWER: W) LIMESTONEBONUS22) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer On which of the terrestrial planets does the Sun rise in the west?ANSWER: VENUS2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) MATH Short Answer How many U.S. quarters equal 750 U.S. nickels? ANSWER: 150BONUS23) MATH Short Answer Name all of the following 5 numbers that are composite numbers: 3, 11, 33, 53, 63ANSWER: 33; 63TOSS-UP24) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Convert 100 milliliters into cubic centimeters: ANSWER: 100BONUS24) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer At standard temperature and pressure, how many grams, rounded to the nearest whole number, does the contents in a 12 ounce or 355 milliliter water bottle weigh?ANSWER: 355 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2 Page 12
TOSS-UP25) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common name for the polymers of DNA and associated proteins that are found in the eukaryotic nucleus?ANSWER: CHROMOSOMEBONUS25) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following characteristics is MOST typical of bacteria:W) numerous mitochondria X) no nucleusY) numerous ciliaZ) reproduction by buddingANSWER: X) NO NUCLEUS2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 2Page 13