ROUND 6 TOSS-UP1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the MOST common manner for transmission of beef tapeworms to humans:W) drinking contaminated waterX) swimming in contaminated water Y) eating uncooked beefZ) stepping in cow manureANSWER: Y) EATING UNCOOKED BEEFBONUS1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a segmented worm:W) hook worm X) earthworm Y) round worm Z) nematodeANSWER: X) EARTHWORM TOSS-UP2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Specific gravity compares the density of various substances to that of what reference substance?ANSWER: WATERBONUS2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the BEST example of a chemical reaction:W) an acid is added to a clear solution in a test tube and a white substance appears and falls to the bottom of the test tubeX) milk is added to water and the water turns a milky colorY) molten metal hardens upon coolingZ) salt is dissolved in waterANSWER: W) AN ACID IS ADDED TO A CLEAR SOLUTION IN A TEST TUBE AND A WHITE SUBSTANCE APPEARS AND FALLS TO THE BOTTOM OF THE TEST TUBE2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6 Page 1TOSS-UP3) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the internal ring within a hurricane where the most intense squalls occur?ANSWER: EYEWALLBONUS3) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice As the eyewall of hurricane Katrina approached Louisiana, on which of the following sides of the hurricane were the highest speeds clocked:W) north X) south Y) east Z) westANSWER: W) NORTH 4) MATH Short Answer Evaluate the following radical: – 160,000 ANSWER: –400BONUS4) MATH Short Answer Arrange the following 4 fractions from the LARGEST to the SMALLEST: 13 ; 7 ;10 ; 218 12 4 12ANSWER: 10;13; 7 ; 2 4 181212TOSS-UP         2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6Page 2TOSS-UP5) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is closest to average barometric pressure at sea level, in millibars:W) 1013 X) 760 Y) 10Z) 1ANSWER: W) 1013BONUS5) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 units of the international system of units that are considered base units and NOT considered derived: Newton, kilogram, second, hertzANSWER: KILOGRAM AND SECONDTOSS-UP6) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Arachnids have how many pairs of appendages? ANSWER: 6BONUS6) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Arachnids have 4 pairs of walking legs and a single pair of pedipalps. What is the name of the last pair of appendages?ANSWER: CHELICERA 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6 Page 3TOSS-UP7) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Doing a given amount of work at different rates always involves a different amount of:W) massX) efficiencyY) potential energy Z) powerANSWER: Z) POWERBONUS7) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer If a force of 200 newtons is required to accelerate an object at 25 meters per second squared on a horizontal frictionless surface, what is the mass of the object, in grams?ANSWER: 8,000(Solution: F/a = m = 200/25 = 8 kg = 8,000 g)TOSS-UP8) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the actual location where slippage of rock masses first occurs in an earthquake: W) seismic front X) focusY) Richter point Z) foreshockANSWER: X) FOCUSBONUS8) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the location on the Earth’s surface directly above an earthquake focus?ANSWER: EPICENTER2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6 Page 4TOSS-UP9) MATH Short Answer What is the percentage decrease when a stock price drops from $55.00 per share to $44.00 per share?ANSWER: 20%BONUS9) MATH Short Answer A cell phone company charges 25 cents per minute for the first 10 minutes of usage and 10 cents per minute for usage greater than 10 minutes. If you talked for 11⁄2 hours, what is your total airtime charge?ANSWER: $10.50(Solution: 0.25 × 10 = $2.50; 80 min × 0.1 = $8.00; $8 + $2.5 = $10.50)TOSS-UP10) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is closest to the height of the typical standard 12-ounce soda can: W) 6 centimeters X) 12 centimeters Y) 18 centimeters Z) 24 centimetersANSWER: X) 12 CENTIMETERS10) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following BEST describes the composition of the Proton Exchange Membrane in fuel cells used to power automobiles:W) polymer plastic X) metal foilY) organic fiberZ) biofilmANSWER: W) POLYMER PLASTICBONUS2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6Page 5TOSS-UP11) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is closest to the length of time it takes for a typical human cell to complete mitosis:W) 1 second X) 1 minute Y) 1 hour Z) 1 dayANSWER: Z) 1 DAYBONUS11) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Order the following 4 stages of mitosis from the EARLIEST to that LATEST: metaphase; prophase; telophase; anaphaseANSWER: PROPHASE; METAPHASE; ANAPHASE; TELOPHASETOSS-UP12) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of laboratory equipment that is specifically designed to mix fluids without spilling: W) pipetteX) centrifugeY) Erlenmeyer flask Z) graduated cylinderANSWER: Y) ERLENMEYER FLASKBONUS12) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following elements is NOT a gas in its standard state:W) fluorine X) nitrogen Y) bromine Z) neonANSWER: Y) BROMINE2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6Page 6TOSS-UP13) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following fossils is the oldest:W) fossil of the earliest flowering plant X) fossilized frog’s eggY) trilobiteZ) mastodonANSWER: Y) TRILOBITEBONUS13) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a layer of the Earth that is primarily characterized as rock with the properties of being hot, weak and plastic:W) lithosphere X) asthenosphere Y) inner coreZ) outer coreANSWER: X) ASTHENOSPHERE TOSS-UP14) MATH Short Answer What is the degree measure of the vertex angle in an isosceles triangle if each base angle measures 48o?ANSWER: 84BONUS14) MATH Short Answer What is the surface area of a cube, in square feet, if one edge measures 5 feet?ANSWER: 1502007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6 Page 7TOSS-UP15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice You wake up in the morning and your eyelids are stuck together with a thin or thick discharge caused by inflammation of the clear membrane that covers the white part of your eyes. Which of the following is MOST likely your problem:W) sinusitisX) cellulitisY) osteomyelitis Z) conjunctivitisANSWER: Z) CONJUNCTIVITISBONUS15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true about nicotine:W) chewing or smokeless tobaccos are safe when used properly because nicotine cannot be absorbed through the mucous membraneX) nicotine and cyanide have been found in cigarettesY) during pregnancy, nicotine concentrates in breast milk and fetal bloodZ) nicotine is a plant alkaloid that is poisonous to most animalsANSWER: W) CHEWING OR SMOKELESS TOBACCOS ARE SAFE WHEN USED PROPERLY BECAUSE NICOTINE CANNOT BE ABSORBED THROUGH THE MUCOUS MEMBRANETOSS-UP16) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What are the scientific terms for the two general types of tissues that conduct fluids in higher plants?ANSWER: XYLEM AND PHLOEMBONUS16) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the scientific name for the basic cell type in higher plants that is relatively unspecialized, has a thin cell wall, and carries out most of the metabolism of the plant?ANSWER: PARENCHYMA 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6 Page 8TOSS-UP17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Of the 4 states of matter, which one is the most common in the universe?ANSWER: PLASMABONUS17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the scientific term for the energy needed to transform a given quantity of a substance from a liquid to a gas at standard pressure:W) heat of boilingX) heat of fusionY) heat of transition Z) heat of vaporizationANSWER: Z) HEAT OF VAPORIZATIONTOSS-UP18) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Calcite belongs to which of the following mineral groups: W) oxideX) carbonate Y) sulfateZ) silicateANSWER: X) CARBONATEBONUS18) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer During what phase of the Moon can a solar eclipse occur? ANSWER: NEW MOON2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6 Page 9TOSS-UP19) MATH Short Answer If two sides of a parallelogram are 8 and 9 centimeters, respectively, find the perimeter, in centimeters:ANSWER: 34BONUS19) MATH Short Answer Rounded to the nearest meter, if side A of a right triangle measures 6 meters and side B measures 9 meters, what is the length of the hypotenuse?ANSWER: 11(Solution: 62 + 92 = c2; c = 11)TOSS-UP20) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Earth’s seasons are primarily caused by:W) Earth’s distance from the SunX) the tilt of Earth’s axis with respect to the Sun Y) Earth’s elliptical orbit around the SunZ) Earth’s rotational periodANSWER: X) THE TILT OF EARTH’S AXIS WITH RESPECT TO THE SUNBONUS20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the muscle that contracts when you inhale and causes your chest cavity to expand?ANSWER: DIAPHRAGM 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6 Page 10TOSS-UP21) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the common name for the vector of Eastern Equine Encephalitis and malaria?ANSWER: MOSQUITOBONUS21) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice What biome is dominant in sub-Saharan Africa and characterized by the dominant plants being fire resistant:W) chaparral X) tundraY) savanna Z) temperateANSWER: Y) SAVANNA TOSS-UP22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the BEST example of a suspension:W) water with 10% ethanol added to itX) olive oil in waterY) table sugar completely dissolved in water Z) orange juice with pulpANSWER: Z) ORANGE JUICE WITH PULPBONUS22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice According to thermodynamics, whenever energy is converted from one form to another then:W) the net useful energy remains the same X) the net useful energy must decreaseY) the total energy of the system increases Z) the total energy of the system decreasesANSWER: X) THE NET USEFUL ENERGY MUST DECREASE2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6Page 11TOSS-UP23) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice A caldera is:W) a huge depression formed after a magma chamber collapses X) a long tube where magma pours out onto the surfaceY) a lateral vent that spews only gasesZ) another name for a fumaroleANSWER: W) A HUGE DEPRESSION FORMED AFTER A MAGMA CHAMBER COLLAPSESBONUS23) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What most commonly happens to the speed of ocean and lake waves as they approach the shallow waters of a shore?ANSWER: SLOW DOWNTOSS-UP24) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is a quadrilateral with only one pair of parallel lines: W) trapezoid X) rhombus Y) rectangle Z) hexagonANSWER: W) TRAPEZOIDBONUS24) MATH Short Answer What are the median, mean and mode, respectively, of the following set of 5 numbers, respectively: 35, 25, 10, 25, 45ANSWER: MEDIAN = 25; MEAN = 28; MODE = 252007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6 Page 12TOSS-UP25) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following elements acts as a catalyst for destroying ozone in the upper atmosphere:W) sulfur X) chlorine Y) nitrogen Z) heliumANSWER: X) CHLORINEBONUS25) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Today, most semiconductors and transistors are made mostly with what element?ANSWER: SILICON2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 6 Page 13