ROUND 11 TOSS-UP
1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of earthworms reproduction:
W) earthworms are hermaphrodites
X) earthworms cross-fertilize
Y) the clitellum secretes a cocoon that picks up eggs and stored sperm
Z) earthworm embryos develop inside the nephrostome (read as: neff-ro-stome) of the male
ANSWER: Z) EARTHWORM EMBRYOS DEVELOP INSIDE THE NEPHROSTOME OF THE MALE
BONUS
1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice If a pea plant with white flowers is crossed with a pea plant with red flowers and all 100 seedlings from this cross are white, then which of the following statements is most likely true:
W) white is dominant to red
X) white is recessive to red
Y) white flowers are dominant in all flowering plants Z) red flowers are recessive in all flowering plants
ANSWER: W) WHITE IS DOMINANT TO RED
TOSS-UP
2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following do ideal machines MOST directly assume:
W) work input equals work output
X) efficiency is over 100%
Y) power is independent of efficiency
Z) energy input is less than energy output
ANSWER: W) WORK INPUT EQUALS WORK OUTPUT
BONUS
2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Which one of the following 5 elements is the LEAST likely to react with any other element: neon; fluorine; iron; oxygen; sodium
ANSWER: NEON
 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11 Page 1
TOSS-UP
3) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following will typically be BEST preserved as a fossil:
W) mountain or forest organisms X) animals with light, thin bones Y) desert or marine organisms Z) soft-shelled organisms
ANSWER: Y) DESERT OR MARINE ORGANISMS
BONUS
3) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is considered a living fossil because, although fossils of it have been dated to 360 million years ago, these arthropods are still alive today:
W) trilobite
X) horseshoe crab Y) ammonite
Z) lobster
ANSWER: X) HORSESHOE CRAB

TOSS-UP
4) MATH Short Answer When 2 fair dice are rolled simultaneously and the face values added, which of the following five numbers is the most common roll: 5, 6, 7, 9, 11
ANSWER: 7

BONUS
4) MATH Short Answer Solve the following equation for x: (x + 4)/(x - 2) = 10/6
ANSWER: 11

  2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11
Page 2
TOSS-UP
5) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following types of scientists would most likely use a Secchi (read as: sek-key) disk in their experiments:
W) geneticist
X) astronomer
Y) physicist
Z) fresh water biologist
ANSWER: Z) FRESH WATER BIOLOGIST
BONUS
5) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Doppler radar is BEST used in which of the following applications:
W) forecasting weather
X) searching for extraterrestrial life Y) mapping the ocean floor
Z) tracking marine life
ANSWER: W) FORECASTING WEATHER
TOSS-UP
6) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What are the letter abbreviations for the four base nucleotides found in mRNA?
 ANSWER: A, U, C, G (any order)
6) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What gland of the human body located in the throat is responsible for regulating metabolic rate and requires a halogen for normal function?
ANSWER: THYROID
BONUS
2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11
Page 3
TOSS-UP
7) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is TRUE about chemical elements:
W) fluorine is a very reactive element
X) rare earth metals are also known as alkaline earth metals
Y) catalysts are typically consumed in chemical reactions
Z) metalloids are some of the best-known conductors of heat and electricity
ANSWER: W) FLUORINE IS A VERY REACTIVE ELEMENT
BONUS
7) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What 2 general products are formed by the reaction of hydrochloric acid and sodium hydroxide?
ANSWER: SALT AND WATER (ACCEPT: NaCl AND H2O or SODIUM CHLORIDE AND WATER)
TOSS-UP
8) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the most common term for the small particles of salt, dust or smoke from which cloud formation begins:
W) precipitation nuclei X) condensation nuclei Y) maturation nuclei Z) saturation nuclei
ANSWER: X) CONDENSATION NUCLEI
BONUS
8) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a location of typically calm and cloudy weather and where daily rains are very common:
W) Hawaii
X) the Sub-Saharan desert
Y) the Pacific northwest
Z) the intertropical convergence zone
ANSWER: Z) THE INTERTROPICAL CONVERGENCE ZONE
 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11
Page 4
TOSS-UP
9) MATH Short Answer Give the slope of the following: 3x � 4y = 12 ANSWER: 43
BONUS
9) MATH Short Answer What is the slope of a line passing through the points (16, �10) and (11, 0)?
ANSWER: �2
(Solution: m = y2 � y1/x2 � x1 = (0 + 10)/(11 � 16) = �2)
TOSS-UP
10) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the BEST example of a turbine:
  W) solar panel
X) wind mill
Y) fuel cell
Z) diesel generator
ANSWER: X) WIND MILL
BONUS
10) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice An ecosystem is BEST classified by which of the following parameters:
W) its predominant vegetation, soil, and living organisms
X) its food web
Y) its living organisms and how they interact with their nonliving environment Z) its species that live in the biome
ANSWER: Y) ITS LIVING ORGANISMS AND HOW THEY INTERACT WITH THEIR NONLIVING ENVIRONMENT
2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11 Page 5
TOSS-UP
11) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the primary function of vascular tissue in plants:
W) transport of fluids
X) storage of solids
Y) photosynthesis
Z) carbon dioxide absorption
ANSWER: W) TRANSPORT OF FLUIDS
BONUS
11) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the plant hormone MOST directly responsible for plants growing towards a light source:
W) photozyme
X) lipin
Y) gibberellin (read as: jib-er-ELL-in) Z) auxin
ANSWER: Z) AUXIN
 TOSS-UP
12) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements regarding electricity is LEAST accurate:
W) resistance generally increases with increasing temperatures
X) superconductors have essentially no resistance to current
Y) resistance is often likened to electrical friction
Z) the heater wires in an electric heater or toaster are designed to have very low resistance
ANSWER: Z) THE HEATER WIRES IN AN ELECTRIC HEATER OR TOASTER ARE DESIGNED TO HAVE VERY LOW RESISTANCE
BONUS
12) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer If a flask contains 500 milliliters of a 2 molar NaCl solution, how many moles of salt are in the beaker?
ANSWER: 1
(Solution: moles = (2 moles/L)(0.5L) = 1.0 mole)
2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11 Page 6
TOSS-UP
13) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a mudflow that moves rapidly down the side of a volcano because of the rapid mixing of melted snow and pyroclastic material:
W) avalanche
X) lahar (read as: lah-HAR)
Y) pahoehoe (read as: pa-HO-ee-ho-ee) lava Z) dike lava
ANSWER: X) LAHAR
BONUS
13) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Of the 3 basic types of volcanoes, what type is large, broad with a low slope, and formed by relatively quiet eruptions, an example of which is Mount Kilauea in Hawaii?
ANSWER: SHIELD
TOSS-UP
14) MATH Short Answer What is the total number of unique subsets of a set with 5 elements? ANSWER: 32
(Solution: 25 = 32)
BONUS
14) MATH Short Answer Rounded to the nearest whole number, find the distance between two points whose coordinates are (7, 5) and (9, 15)?
ANSWER: 10
 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11 Page 7
TOSS-UP
15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:
W) a robotic spacecraft recently landed on the surface of a near-Earth asteroid
X) a team of researchers plan to build a neutrino observatory at the bottom of the Mediterranean Sea Y) skin cancer is becoming more common and appearing at younger ages
Z) solar activity is currently at an 11-year cyclical high point
ANSWER: Z) SOLAR ACTIVITY IS CURRENTLY AT AN 11-YEAR CYCLICAL HIGH POINT
BONUS
15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice If 2 identical latex balloons are filled to the same size, one with air and the other with helium and left for 2 days, why would the helium balloon most likely decrease in size at a faster rate than the air balloon:
W) helium molecules are smaller than air molecules and they leak through the balloon faster X) helium is always warmer when first introduced into a balloon
Y) helium is lighter than air and moves faster
Z) helium reacts with water inside the balloon and condenses
ANSWER: W) HELIUM MOLECULES ARE SMALLER THAN AIR MOLECULES AND THEY LEAK THROUGH THE BALLOON FASTER
TOSS-UP
16) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Of the 4 general types of biological molecules, proteins, carbohydrates, lipids and nucleic acids, which one is MOST directly effected by mutations?
ANSWER: NUCLEIC ACIDS
BONUS
16) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Of the 4 general types of biological molecules, proteins, carbohydrates, lipids and nucleic acids, which one will typically release the MOST energy per gram when metabolized by a normal healthy human?
ANSWER: LIPIDS
 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11 Page 8
TOSS-UP
17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer If the knob of a door knob is 8 centimeters in diameter and the rod that the door knob turns to allow the door to be opened is 2 centimeters in diameter, what is the ideal mechanical advantage of this simple machine?
ANSWER: 4
BONUS
17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Giving your answer in numeral form, how many complete vibrations per second are in an 890 kilohertz radio broadcast?
ANSWER: 890,000
TOSS-UP
18) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Erratics are rocks or boulders that were moved to their current location by:
 W) rivers
X) tides
Y) glaciers Z) volcanoes
ANSWER: Y) GLACIERS
BONUS
18) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Of the following 4 layers of the Earth, name the one which is LEAST dense and the one that is MOST dense, respectively: oceanic crust; continental crust; inner core; mantle
ANSWER: LEAST = CONTINENTAL CRUST; MOST = INNER CORE
2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11 Page 9
TOSS-UP
19) MATH Short Answer In how many different ways can 5 different puppets be ordered across a shelf?
ANSWER: 120 (Solution: 5! = 120)
BONUS
19) MATH Short Answer Expand the following expression, giving your answer in standard binomial form: (5x � 25)2
ANSWER: 25x2 � 250x + 625
TOSS-UP
20) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Although lichens can be found in many locations, in which of the following biomes will lichens grow and thrive the best:
 W) coniferous forest X) tundra
Y) grassland
Z) rain forest
ANSWER: X) TUNDRA
20) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A parsec is equal to about:
W) 5 Astronomical Units X) 1 million kilometers Y) 3 and 1�4 light years
Z) 158,000 klicks
ANSWER: Y) 3 AND 1�4 LIGHT YEARS
BONUS
2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11
Page 10
TOSS-UP
21) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer In what specific tissue of the common adult house cat are red blood cells primarily produced?
ANSWER: BONE MARROW (ACCEPT: RED MARROW)
BONUS
21) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What element is most directly involved with the binding of oxygen in the hemoglobin molecule?
ANSWER: IRON
TOSS-UP
22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following does water possess that most directly allows it to absorb large amounts of energy with a relatively small change in temperature:
 W) high thermal expansion X) high specific heat
Y) high heat of vaporization Z) high latency
ANSWER: X) HIGH SPECIFIC HEAT
BONUS
22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Consider a jet engine that is 10,000-times as loud as a certain locomotive. If the jet engine is operating at 100 decibels, how loud is the locomotive, in decibels?
ANSWER: 60
2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11 Page 11
TOSS-UP
23) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the era of the geological time scale that occurs after the Mesozoic and continues to present day?
ANSWER: CENOZOIC
BONUS
23) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What era of the geological time scale ended with the largest extinction event in Earth�s history?
ANSWER: PALEOZOIC
TOSS-UP
24) MATH Short Answer Solve the following logarithmic equation for x: log 2(x + 1) = log 8 ANSWER: 2
BONUS
24) MATH Short Answer Give the following sum as a single logarithm: log3 10 + log3 3 ANSWER: log3 30
 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11 Page 12
TOSS-UP
25) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Of the following 4 choices, name all that are vitamins: lysine; lactose; cholesterol; riboflavin
ANSWER: RIBOFLAVIN
BONUS
25) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the specific name for the type of solar eclipse of the Sun in which the Moon is positioned to block nearly all of the Sun, causing a symmetrical ring of sunlight at maximum eclipse?
ANSWER: ANNULAR
2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl - Round 11 Page 13
