ROUND 4 TOSS-UP1) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following BEST describes the number property used in the following equation: (3 × 2) × 5 = 3 × (2 × 5)W) associative property of multiplication X) commutative property of multiplication Y) distributive property of multiplication Z) multiplicative property of oneANSWER: W) ASSOCIATIVE PROPERTY OF MULTIPLICATIONBONUS1) MATH Short Answer Arrange the following in increasing order: (–3)2; –(4)2; (–1)4; –(–3)3 ANSWER: –(4)2; (–1)4; (–3)2; –(–3)3TOSS-UP2) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer To the nearest whole number, convert 53oC into kelvin: ANSWER: 326BONUS2) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer To the nearest whole number, convert 60oC into degrees Fahrenheit:ANSWER: 140(Solution: 60 × 1.8 + 32 = 140o) 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 1
TOSS-UP3) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a rodent:W) rabbitX) chipmunk Y) prairie dog Z) squirrelANSWER: W) RABBITBONUS3) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Order the following 4 groups from the LARGEST taxonomical group to the SMALLEST taxonomical group: family; class; order; phylumANSWER: PHYLUM; CLASS; ORDER; FAMILYTOSS-UP4) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In a modern optimally functioning internal combustion engine, most of the energy is lost as: W) heatX) unburnt fuelY) CO2Z) carbon monoxideANSWER: W) HEATBONUS4) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is LEAST accurate regarding states of matter:W) solids when heated typically expandX) gases can be made of a single element Y) matter on Earth is never in a plasma state Z) gases condense to form liquidsANSWER: Y) MATTER ON EARTH IS NEVER IN A PLASMA STATE2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 2
TOSS-UP5) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer At its maximum brightness, which planet of our solar system appears brighter than any other planet in the sky?ANSWER: VENUSBONUS5) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which of the following locations are you MOST likely to find a well-preserved dinosaur fossil:W) within key beds of the Devonian PeriodX) within metamorphic rocks of the Cretaceous PeriodY) within sedimentary rocks laid down during the Mesozoic Era Z) within volcanic casts of the Jurassic PeriodANSWER: Y) WITHIN SEDIMENTARY ROCKS LAID DOWN DURING THE MESOZOIC ERATOSS-UP6) MATH Short Answer Giving your answer as a proper fraction in its simplest form, multiply the following two fractions: (! 5) " (! 6 )   ANSWER: 5 116 11 BONUS6) MATH Short Answer Giving your answer as a mixed fraction reduced to its lowest terms, subtract the following fractions: (8 ! 1) ! (5 ! 12)ANSWER: 195    9999 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 3
TOSS-UP7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of metric volumes:W) a liter is larger than a centiliterX) a milliliter is smaller than a picoliter Y) a deciliter is smaller than a literZ) a microliter is smaller than a milliliterANSWER: X) A MILLILITER IS SMALLER THAN A PICOLITERBONUS7) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Giving your answer in proper scientific notation with the correct number of significant digits, convert 800 kilometers per hour into meters per hour:ANSWER: 8 × 105TOSS-UP8) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 organisms that molt: nematode; clam; lobster; molluskANSWER: LOBSTERBONUS8) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the scientific term for the type of circulatory system found in lobsters in which blood empties into spaces in the body that are not contained in vessels?ANSWER: OPEN 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 4
TOSS-UP9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a Group 1 metal that gives off a persistent yellow color when burned in a flame test, and is also used in commercial and highway vapor lamps that have a yellow glow:W) neonX) potassium Y) sodium Z) zincANSWER: Y) SODIUMBONUS9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Consider an atom that has an original atomic mass of 33 and has 17 neutrons. If it then loses one proton, what is the resultant atomic number of the atom?ANSWER: 15(Solution: atomic mass – 17 N = 16 protons = atomic # of 16 loss of 1 is 16 – 1 = 15)TOSS-UP10) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice A psychrometer (read as: sigh-KROM-meter) is used to measure: W) salinityX) humidityY) wind direction Z) pressureANSWER: X) HUMIDITYBONUS10) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common scientific name of the instrument used to measure wind speed?ANSWER: ANEMOMETER2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 5
TOSS-UP11) MATH Short Answer If the mileage scale on a road map is 1centimeter per 2.5 miles, an 80-mile trip would be represented by how many centimeters on the same map?ANSWER: 32BONUS11) MATH Short Answer Of the following five quantities, which is the LEAST and which is the GREATEST, respectively: : 0.425; 1⁄4; 2 ; – 9 ; 4/3ANSWER: LEAST = – 9 ; GREATEST = 2 TOSS-UP12) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A dog has a difficult time locating a stick at the bottom of a clear, shallow pool because he perceives it to be in a slightly different spot. This is BEST explained by which of the following properties of light:     W) diffraction X) reflection Y) refraction Z) polarizationANSWER: Y) REFRACTIONBONUS12) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following typically accounts for the greatest amount of magnification in a compound light microscope:W) condenser lens X) objective lens Y) ocular lensZ) diaphragmANSWER: X) OBJECTIVE LENS2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 6
TOSS-UP13) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common simple sugar or monosaccharide that makes up most of the carbohydrates of the typical American’s diet?ANSWER: GLUCOSEBONUS13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Which one of the following 5 molecules is a disaccharide that is present in high levels in milk: maltose; fructose; glucose; lactose; hexoseANSWER: LACTOSETOSS-UP14) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following choices is NOT an example of a chemical change:W) shiny new copper tarnishing to a green colorX) bubbles forming in a solution of vinegar following the addition of baking soda Y) steel turning red upon heatingZ) iron rustingANSWER: Y) STEEL TURNING RED UPON HEATINGBONUS14) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Rusting of iron is a chemical combination of what two chemical elements?ANSWER: OXYGEN AND IRON 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 7
TOSS-UP15) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the gas found primarily in the stratosphere that absorbs UV radiation and ultimately protects life on Earth?ANSWER: OZONEBONUS15) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is immediately released when an earthquake occurs:W) convection currents within the mantleX) radiation energy originating from the mantle Y) stored heat energy from the SunZ) elastic energy stored in rocksANSWER: Z) ELASTIC ENERGY STORED IN ROCKSTOSS-UP16) MATH Short Answer If a fair die is tossed once, what is the probability that an odd number or a number less than 3 is thrown expressed as a fraction in lowest terms?ANSWER: 2316) MATH Short Answer If the time is 1:15 PM, what time will it be, given as hours, minutes andAM or PM, in 630 minutes? ANSWER: 11:45 PM  BONUS2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 8
TOSS-UP17) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following gases was most likely LEAST abundant in Earth’s early atmosphere:W) carbon dioxide X) ammoniaY) waterZ) oxygenANSWER: Z) OXYGENBONUS17) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Arrange the following 4 organisms from the first to appear on Earth to the most recent to appear on Earth: fish; invertebrates; reptiles; mammalsANSWER: INVERTEBRATES; FISH; REPTILES; MAMMALSTOSS-UP18) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What type of nucleic acid has codons for matching with anticodons?ANSWER: MESSENGER RNA (ACCEPT: mRNA)BONUS18) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer How many nucleotide bases make up an anticodon? ANSWER: 3 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 9
TOSS-UP19) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What are the most common SI units used for the acceleration of an object?ANSWER: METERS PER SECOND SQUAREDBONUS19) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Neglecting friction, what is the acceleration, in meters per second squared, of a 20-kilogram iron block across a horizontal surface if 700 newtons is applied to the block?ANSWER: 35(Solution: A = F/M; A = 700/20; A = 35 m/sec2)TOSS-UP20) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true about Earth’s water:W) the Antarctic ice sheet holds most of the world’s fresh waterX) an estuary is a place where a fresh water river is mixed with ocean water Y) rivers and lakes make up less than 1% of all fresh waterZ) the global ocean conveyor system is powered mostly by surface windsANSWER: Z) THE GLOBAL OCEAN CONVEYOR SYSTEM IS POWERED MOSTLY BY SURFACE WINDSBONUS20) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the layer of the Earth that is nearly 1,800 miles thick and represents about 68% of the Earth’s mass?ANSWER: MANTLE 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 10
TOSS-UP21) MATH Short Answer If side A of a right triangle measures 4 meters and the hypotenuse measures 5 meters, what is the length of side B, in meters?ANSWER: 3(Solution: 3:4:5 triangle)BONUS21) MATH Short Answer What is the area of a square, in square meters, if its perimeter is 28 meters?ANSWER: 49TOSS-UP22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What gaseous molecule is produced from the burning of fossil fuels and is believed to be the primary cause of the greenhouse warming effect on Earth?ANSWER: CARBON DIOXIDE (ACCEPT: CO2)BONUS22) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT typically considered an alternative energy source:W) hot springs X) natural gas Y) wind energy Z) sun energyANSWER: X) NATURAL GAS 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common term for the arrangement of veins in the leaves of most monocots?ANSWER: PARALLELBONUS23) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer How many cotyledons are found in seedlings of plants that develop into adult plants with parallel veins in their leaves and flower parts usually in multiples of three?ANSWER: 1TOSS-UP24) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Solutions with a pH less than about 6 typically have what distinctive taste?ANSWER: SOURBONUS24) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the SI the unit for frequency? ANSWER: HERTZ 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 12
TOSS-UP25) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT directly or indirectly a result of a large earthquake:W) firesX) tsunamiY) mass wasting Z) lightningANSWER: Z) LIGHTNINGBONUS25) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The area known as the ‘ring of fire’ is prone to intense earthquake and volcanic activity because this is where:W) the oceanic crust is the thinnestX) the oceanic crust is the densestY) density differences between the lithosphere and the mantle are most pronounced Z) most convergent plate boundaries are foundANSWER: Z) MOST CONVERGENT PLATE BOUNDARIES ARE FOUND2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl – Round 4 Page 13