ROUND 3 TOSS-UP1) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The temperature outside is 85o F and the air is holding a maximum amount of moisture. If the temperature drops rapidly to 65oF, which of the following will MOST likely happen:W) it will rainX) it will become sunnyY) humidity is relatively unchangedZ) the relative humidity is lowered by about 25%ANSWER: W) IT WILL RAINBONUS1) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer The summit of Mount McKinley or Denali at about 6,200 meters is found in what layer of the Earth’s atmosphere?ANSWER: TROPOSPHERETOSS-UP2) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:W) 5 × 0 = 0X) 2 × 1⁄2 = 5 ÷ 5Y) 0/5 = 0Z) 5/0 = 5ANSWER:Z) 5/0=5BONUS2) MATH Short Answer Simplify the following: (x3y4z2) × (2y3)0 ANSWER: x3y4z22007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3Page 1TOSS-UP3) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Convert 10 square feet into square inches: ANSWER: 1440BONUS3) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice If you are 5 feet 10 inches tall, which of the following is closest to your height, in meters:W) 1.8 X) 1.7 Y) 1.6 Z) 1.5ANSWER: W) 1.8 TOSS-UP4) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is MOST commonly noted as the most diverse class of life on Earth?ANSWER: INSECT (ACCEPT: INSECTA)BONUS4) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Which one of the following 5 organisms is LEAST related to the others: centipede; beetle; fly; bed bug; waspANSWER: CENTIPEDE(Solution: centipedes are chilopods; all others are insects)2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3 Page 2TOSS-UP5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer The bubbles in boiling water are composed of what molecules?ANSWER: WATER (ACCEPT: H2O)BONUS5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer How much work is done in holding a steel block in place by applying a force of 800 newtons for 5 seconds?ANSWER: 0 (ACCEPT: NONE)TOSS-UP6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a likely impact of continued global warming:W) volcanic activity will increaseX) polar ice could melt enough to raise the sea levels Y) coral bleachingZ) major changes in weather patternsANSWER: W) VOLCANIC ACTIVITY WILL INCREASEBONUS6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true about ocean water:W) cool, salty water is more dense that warm, less salty waterX) about 97% of Earth’s surface water is salt waterY) about 3.5% of sea water consists of dissolved substancesZ) the proportions of dissolved gases in the ocean are nearly the same as in the atmosphereANSWER: Z) THE PROPORTIONS OF DISSOLVED GASES IN THE OCEAN ARE NEARLY THE SAME AS IN THE ATMOSPHERE 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3 Page 3TOSS-UP7) MATH Short Answer If 10% of a certain number is 240, what is 25% of the original number? ANSWER: 600BONUS7) MATH Short Answer Giving your answer as a proper fraction in its simplest form, subtract the following two fractions: 4/8 - 14/12 ANSWER: -2/3TOSS-UP8) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer If a circle’s circumference is divided by its radius, what is the resulting value to the nearest whole number?ANSWER: 6BONUS8) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a number with 3 significant digits:W) 0.003 X) 0.03030 Y) 0.033 Z) 0.0300ANSWER: Z) 0.0300    2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3Page 4TOSS-UP9) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following do clams use as an anchor to fix themselves into the sand:W) mantle X) footY) siphon Z) gangliaANSWER: X) FOOTBONUS9) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 organisms that are bivalve mollusks: octopus; oyster; snail; clamANSWER: OYSTER; CLAMTOSS-UP10) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What property of sound is most directly responsible for it bending around objects?ANSWER: DIFFRACTIONBONUS10) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the basic unit of energy:W) degree X) joule Y) voltZ) pascalANSWER: X) JOULE 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3Page 5TOSS-UP11) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following BEST describes earthquake aftershocks:W) all tremors under magnitude 4 on the Richter scaleX) a series of smaller tremors that follow a large earthquake within days or weeks Y) any tremors that originate from the epicenter within a 1 year periodZ) the tremor that occurs at the initial point of ruptureANSWER: X) A SERIES OF SMALLER TREMORS THAT FOLLOW A LARGE EARTHQUAKE WITHIN DAYS OR WEEKSBONUS11) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is closest to the maximum wavelength of an open ocean tsunami:W) 2000 feet X) 3 miles Y) 30 miles Z) 125 milesANSWER: Z) 125 MILES TOSS-UP12) MATH Short Answer What is the greatest common factor of the numbers 14 and 49? ANSWER: 7BONUS12) MATH Short Answer What is the Roman numeral equivalent of the year 2006? ANSWER: MMVI2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3 Page 6TOSS-UP13) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which of the following biomes does MOST of Earth’s photosynthesis take place:W) tundraX) tropical forests Y) oceansZ) taigaANSWER: Y) OCEANSBONUS13) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a property of carbon that makes it most effective as a polymer building block:W) it is in period 2 of the Periodic Table X) it is a non-metalY) it has a valence of 4Z) it is highly electronegativeANSWER: Y) IT HAS A VALENCE OF 4TOSS-UP14) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the location of the patella bone: W) shoulder X) kneeY) abdomen Z) armANSWER: X) KNEEBONUS14) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer When blood leaves the human lung through the pulmonary vein, to what organ will it first go?ANSWER: HEART2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3 Page 7TOSS-UP15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer How many protons does an atom have if it is in group two, period three and is the 12th element of the of the periodic table?ANSWER: 12BONUS15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer If selenium has an atomic mass of 79, and an atomic number of 34, how many neutrons does it have?ANSWER: 45 (Solution: 79 – 34 = 45)TOSS-UP16) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Recently, Pluto was de-listed as a planet. To what category does it now belong?ANSWER: DWARF PLANET(S) (ACCEPT: KUIPER BELT OBJECT)BONUS16) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Studies using which of the following processes is BEST used for calculating the age of Earth:W) radioisotope half-lifeX) heat loss from the SunY) principal of superposition Z) ice core samplingANSWER: W) RADIOISOTOPE HALF-LIFE 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3Page 8TOSS-UP17) MATH Multiple Choice The number 3,101 is evenly divisible by which of the following numbers:W) 3 X) 7 Y) 9 Z) 11ANSWER: X) 717) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is the product of 3.14 and 93:W) 27.14 X) 729.14 Y) 2289.06 Z) 2742.04ANSWER: Y) 2289.06BONUS TOSS-UP18) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Vinegar reacts with which of the following kitchen ingredients to release bubbles of CO2:W) baking soda X) sugarY) flourZ) saltANSWER: W) BAKING SODABONUS18) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The finer a coffee bean is ground, the stronger the coffee will taste after brewing. This is BEST explained by an increase in the ground coffee beans:W) massX) volumeY) surface area Z) densityANSWER: Y) SURFACE AREA2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3Page 9TOSS-UP19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following are the 3 basic organs of higher plants:W) plastids, cell walls, and golgi X) xylem, phloem, and cambium Y) roots, stems, and leavesZ) cork, bark, and woodANSWER: Y) ROOTS, STEMS, AND LEAVESBONUS19) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What group of modified epidermal cells in the roots of higher plants is responsible for MOST water absorption?ANSWER: ROOT HAIRSTOSS-UP20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Water beading up on a cold glass on a humid day is an example of what phase change?ANSWER: CONDENSATIONBONUS20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The product of mass and velocity would most commonly be described as:W) forceX) joulesY) momentum Z) accelerationANSWER: Y) MOMENTUM 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3Page 10TOSS-UP21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice A mineral that splits along planes of weakness into even sheets is BEST described as having:W) good cleavageX) silky lusterY) conchoidal fracture Z) crystalline shapeANSWER: W) GOOD CLEAVAGEBONUS21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true about minerals:W) cinnabar is the most important mercury ore mineral X) pyrite is a common sulfide mineralY) galena is the most important ore of leadZ) granite is a widespread mineral used in cementANSWER: Z) GRANITE IS A WIDESPREAD MINERAL USED IN CEMENTTOSS-UP22) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:W) 30% × 60% = 18%X) the square of an odd number is always oddY) the reciprocal of the smallest prime number is 1⁄2 Z) the number 27 is a perfect squareANSWER: Z) THE NUMBER 27 IS A PERFECT SQUAREBONUS22) MATH Short Answer What is the price of a $15.00 item that is marked up 25%? ANSWER: $18.75 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3Page 11TOSS-UP23) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Entomology is the study of what class of organisms? ANSWER: INSECTSBONUS23) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is MOST closely related to the wasp:W) flyX) mosquito Y) fleaZ) beeANSWER: Z) BEE TOSS-UP24) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What are the common names, respectively, for the 2 types of lenses of a compound light microscope that function first to magnify the light just after the light passes through the specimen on the slide and then just before the light enter the observers eyes?ANSWER: OBJECTIVE LENS AND OCULAR LENS (THE ORDER IN WHICH THE ANSWERS ARE GIVEN MATTERS UNLESS THE STUDENT SAYS WHICH LENS GOES WITH WHICH PART OF THE QUESTION)(ACCEPT: OBJECTIVE AND OCULAR)BONUS24) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the scientific term scientists use to describe the rod-like shape of most Anthrax bacteria?ANSWER: BACILLUS (ACCEPT: BACILLI) 2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3 Page 12TOSS-UP25) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the MOST appropriate term for a mixture of two liquids that is uniformly distributed and does not separate:W) substance X) solventY) solution Z) suspensionANSWER: Y) SOLUTIONBONUS25) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which of the following organizational sections of the Periodic Table are lithium, beryllium, boron and carbon all sequentially located:W) gases X) periods Y) halogens Z) groupsANSWER: X) PERIODS2007 Middle School Regional Science Bowl –Round 3Page 13