ROUND 4          TOSS-UP1) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Which element derives its symbol from the Latin word Aurum?ANSWER: GOLDBONUS1) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term for a chemical species having two ionizable hydrogen atoms?ANSWER: DIPROTIC________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP2) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What are animals that eat other animals known as? ANSWER: CARNIVORES (ACCEPT: PREDATORS)BONUS2) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Sea stars, velvet worms and northern shrike birds – all three are examples of:W) OmnivoresX) Detritivores (read as: di-TRI-ti-vohrs) Y) ScavengersZ) PredatorsANSWER: Z) PREDATORSRound 4Page 1TOSS-UP3) MATH Short Answer Simplify completely the fraction 11 . 23ANSWER: 1 1 23BONUS3) MATH Multiple Choice If you were to graph the inequality x < -7 (read as: x is less than negative 7) on a number line, what would it look like?W) It would have an open circle at -7 and a ray extending from -7 on the right to negative infinity on the leftX) It would have a closed circle at -7 and a ray extending from -7 on the right to negative infinity on the leftY) It would have an open circle at 7 and a ray extending from 7 on the right to negative infinity on the leftZ) It would have open circles at -7 and 7 and be shaded in between themANSWER: W) IT WOULD HAVE AN OPEN CIRCLE AT -7 AND A RAY EXTENDING FROM -7 ON THE RIGHT TO NEGATIVE INFINITY ON THE LEFT________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP4) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following resulted in petroleum?W) Meteors that fell from spaceX) Water combined with sediment depositsY) Dead organisms packed together for millions of years Z) Saltwater combined with sandANSWER: Y) DEAD ORGANISMS PACKED TOGETHER FOR MILLIONS OF YEARSBONUS4) ENERGY Short Answer Put the following countries in order from least to greatest current annual oil consumption: Brazil, France, India, and China.ANSWER: FRANCE, BRAZIL, INDIA, AND CHINA  Round 4 Page 2TOSS-UP5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT characteristic of an atom?W) It is positively charged X) It has electronsY) It has protonsZ) It has a nucleusANSWER: W) IT IS POSITIVELY CHARGEDBONUS5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the smallest non-divisible unit of a covalent compound?ANSWER: MOLECULE________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP6) MATH Short Answer How many 4 inch square tiles will be needed to cover a rectangular surface 8 inches by 24 inches?ANSWER: 12BONUS6) MATH Short Answer How many triangular pieces with side lengths of 3 inches, 4 inches, and 5 inches can be cut from a rectangular sheet measuring 8 inches by 6 inches?ANSWER: 8Round 4 Page 3TOSS-UP7) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the general name given to a scientist who studies microorganisms?ANSWER: MICROBIOLOGISTBONUS7) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice A plasmid is a circular DNA molecule that is separate from chromosomal DNA, usually occurring in bacteria. Which of the following do plasmids usually contain?W) Single-stranded DNA X) Cell membraneY) High osmotic pressure Z) One or two genesANSWER: Z) ONE OR TWO GENES________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP8) ENERGY Short Answer Name the form of energy used to transmit and receive signals from radios, cell phones, and televisions.ANSWER: ELECTROMAGNETIC (ACCEPT: ELECTROMAGNETIC WAVE)BONUS8) ENERGY Short Answer What is the main difference between the electromagnetic waves used by a radio and those used by a cell phone?ANSWER: THEIR WAVELENGTH (ALSO ACCEPT: FREQUENCY OR PERIOD)Round 4 Page 4TOSS-UP9) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer Lake Vostok, thought to be a good analogue for an under-ice ocean environment on Europa, can be found underneath glacial ice on which continent?ANSWER: ANTARCTICABONUS9) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Approximately what percent of Earth’s water is in the form of ice?W) 1.6 % X) 6.6 % Y) 11.6 % Z) 16.6 %ANSWER: W) 1.6 %________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) MATH Multiple Choice A spool of ribbon has 500 yards of ribbon. If one fancy bow takes 1.3 yards of continuous ribbon, how many bows can you make from one spool?W) 46 X) 384 Y) 462 Z) 650ANSWER: X) 38410)MATH Short Answer Ifx+y=5and3x–4y=15,solve for x and y. ANSWER: x=5 AND y=0BONUSRound 4Page 5TOSS-UP11) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Rabbits eat grass and foxes eat rabbits. What role do foxes play in the food chain?W) Primary producerX) Primary consumerY) Secondary consumer Z) Tertiary consumerANSWER: Y) SECONDARY CONSUMERBONUS11) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer In a given ecosystem, there are 1 million kilojoules of energy contained in the primary producer biomass. How much energy is available, in kilojoules, to secondary consumers if primary consumers are 10% efficient at converting energy to biomass?ANSWER: 100,000________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP12) MATH Short Answer Mike’s bill for texting last month was $10. This month it was $15. What was the percentage increase in the bill?ANSWER: 50%BONUS12) MATH Short Answer Ira puts 20% of his paycheck in savings. If his check is $60 per week, how much money will he save in four weeks?ANSWER: $48Round 4 Page 6TOSS-UP13) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer The Mohorovičić (read as: mōe-HOH-rōe-vi- tsik) discontinuity, commonly referred to as the Moho discontinuity, defines a contrast in seismic velocity that is widely accepted to be the boundary between the mantle and what layer?ANSWER: CRUSTBONUS13) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer The Earth's core is believed to be composed primarily of what element?ANSWER: IRON________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP14) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Gary and Paul were conducting a science experiment to determine how far an egg could drop before it broke. Gary tested 20 total eggs: 4 cracked at 2 feet, 6 cracked at 3 feet, and the rest did not break after dropping. The data that he collected represents which of the following parts of the scientific method?W) ResultsX) Conclusions Y) Hypothesis Z) VariablesANSWER: W) RESULTSBONUS14) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer The intersection between the femur and the hipbone can be described as what kind of joint?ANSWER: BALL AND SOCKETRound 4 Page 7TOSS-UP15) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer Due to the construction of the Hoover Dam, the delta of what river has been affected by changes in water flow?ANSWER: COLORADO RIVERBONUS15) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What are the ecosystems called that are located around rivers and streams, linking water to dry land?ANSWER: RIPARIAN ZONES (ACCEPT: RIPARIAN AREAS, FLOODPLAIN)________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following compounds is most soluble in water of 25° Celsius at 1 atmosphere of pressure?W) Aluminum chlorideX) Zinc oxideY) Magnesium phosphate Z) Calcium oxideANSWER: W) ALUMINUM CHLORIDEBONUS16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer For solid and liquid solutes, changes in pressure have practically no effect on solubility. For gaseous solutes, what happens to solubility with an increase in pressure?ANSWER: SOLUBILITY INCREASESRound 4 Page 8TOSS-UP17) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What body organ destroys and recycles old and damaged red blood cells?ANSWER: SPLEENBONUS17) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name the enzyme present in saliva that is responsible for breaking down starches into sugars.ANSWER: AMYLASE (ALSO ACCEPT: PTYALIN)________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP18) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT part of a prokaryotic (read as: prōe-kahr-ee-AH-tik) cell?W) Cell membrane X) Cell wallY) NucleusZ) CytoplasmANSWER: Y) NUCLEUSBONUS18) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice ATP is commonly called the energy molecule of the cell. Where in the cell would you find ATP made by substrate phosphorylation?W) Cell membraneX) CytoplasmY) Mitochondria (read as: my-toh-KOHN-dree-ah) Z) VesicleANSWER: X) CYTOPLASMRound 4Page 9TOSS-UP19) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following oceanic currents prevents the climate of Northern Europe from being much colder?W) Circumpolar Current X) Kuroshio CurrentY) North Pacific Current Z) Gulf StreamANSWER: Z) GULF STREAMBONUS19) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true about weather or climate?W) The terms weather is used to describe atmospheric conditions over a short period of time in a particular areaX) Climate is the average weather pattern over many years in a particular areaY) Climate causes weatherZ) Climate variability can be related to periodic changes such as El Niño or La NiñaANSWER: Y) CLIMATE CAUSES WEATHER________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the vertical distance from the undisturbed position of the medium to the top of a crest of a wave called?ANSWER: AMPLITUDEBONUS20) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following types of radiation has the shortest wavelength?W) Gamma raysX) X-raysY) Infrared radiation Z) Ultraviolet radiationANSWER: W) GAMMA RAYSRound 4Page 10TOSS-UP21) ENERGY Multiple Choice What is the approximate minimum temperature difference in degrees Celsius required between deep and shallow waters for an Ocean Thermal Energy Conversion (OTEC) system to be commercially viable?W) 5 X)Y)Z) 50ANSWER: Y) 0   BONUS21) ENERGY Multiple Choice About what percentage of efficiency can an OTEC system currently achieve?W) 1% X) 3% Y) 10% Z) 20%ANSWER: X) 3%________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the force that determines the shape of planets, stars, and the Solar System?ANSWER: GRAVITYBONUS22) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which two features determine the force of gravity between two planets?W) Their masses and distance apartX) Their atmospheric compositions and masses Y) Their rotational motions and shapesZ) Their masses and shapesANSWER: W) THEIR MASSES AND DISTANCE APARTRound 4Page 11TOSS-UP23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Although snowflakes can have many forms, generally, snow crystals have what basic shape?ANSWER: HEXAGONAL (ALSO ACCEPT: SIX-SIDED)BONUS23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Of the following choices, which one best describes the way snowflakes form?W) Raindrops freezeX) Water vapor freezes onto ice crystals inside clouds Y) Ice attaches to dust particles in the airZ) Sleet freezesANSWER: X) WATER VAPOR FREEZES ONTO ICE CRYSTALS INSIDE CLOUDS________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP24) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is true about the Moon?W) It crosses our sky along the same path every nightX) It always rises in the westY) It changes size in our sky as it passes from horizon to zenith to the other horizon Z) It gives off no light of its ownANSWER: Z) IT GIVES OFF NO LIGHT OF ITS OWNBONUS24) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer A large portion of the bottom of the Great Salt Lake is covered by smooth, soft and rounded sand, often used in home aquaria. What kind of sand is it?ANSWER: OOLITIC (ACCEPT: OOLITE)Round 4 Page 12TOSS-UP25) MATH Short Answer How many modes does the following list of seven numbers have: 1, 4, 4, 7, 8, 14, 14?ANSWER: 2BONUS25) MATH Short Answer If you have a data set of the following seven values: 1, 2, 547, 550, 560, 580, 540, what is the name given to values such as 1 and 2?ANSWER: OUTLIERSRound 4 Page 13