ROUND 1          TOSS-UP1) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What process do autotrophs (read as: AW-toh-trōefs) use to make their own food from sunlight?ANSWER: PHOTOSYNTHESISBONUS1) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What gas essential to human life do plants give off when they photosynthesize?ANSWER: OXYGEN________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a chemical reaction?W) Evaporating rubbing alcohol X) Burning lamp oilY) Dissolving table salt in water Z) Forming frostANSWER: X) BURNING LAMP OILBONUS2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A person applies for a patent on an engine that is 100% efficient. This application would be rejected because the engine would violate the:W) Law of conservation of momentum X) Law of frictionY) Law of gravityZ) Laws of thermodynamicsANSWER: Z) LAWS OF THERMODYNAMICSRound 1Page 1
TOSS-UP3) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the preserved remains, traces, or evidence of organisms that were formerly alive, often found in rocks and other geologic deposits?ANSWER: FOSSILBONUS3) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Fossils are most often found in what type of rock?W) Igneous (read as: IG-nee-us) X) MetamorphicY) SedimentaryZ) GraniticANSWER: Y) SEDIMENTARY________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP4) MATH Short Answer Rounding your answer to the nearest whole number, what is 732.15 + 641.43?ANSWER: 1374BONUS4) MATH Short Answer Round 63,159.456 to the hundreds’ (read as: hun-DREDS) place. ANSWER: 63,200Round 1 Page 2
TOSS-UP5) MATH Short Answer What is the additive inverse of 3? ANSWER: -3BONUS5) MATH Short Answer What is the sum of the multiplicative inverse of 2 and the multiplicative inverse of 5 as a fraction in simplest form?ANSWER: 7/10________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Sometimes brightly-colored signs advertising objects or places use a noble gas. Which noble gas is most commonly used to make these signs?ANSWER: NEONBONUS6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following elements is NOT a noble gas?W) Xenon X) Radon Y) Krypton Z) BromineANSWER: Z) BROMINERound 1Page 3
TOSS-UP7) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer While brushing your hair, you scrape electrons from your hair. This results in what type of charge for your hair?ANSWER: POSITIVE CHARGEBONUS7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What type of energy production does NOT require a turbine with a shaft to spin a generator in order to create electricity?W) Geothermal powerX) HydropowerY) Hydrogen fuel cellsZ) Nuclear (fission) reactorsANSWER: Y) HYDROGEN FUEL CELLS________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP8) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer In a symbiotic relationship, what is the minimum number of organisms that benefits from the relationship?ANSWER: 0BONUS8) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice For an environment where a long-lasting toxin has been introduced, in which organism of a food chain will you expect to find the least accumulation of the toxin?W) ProducerX) Herbivore (read as: (H)URR-bi-vohr) Y) Primary predatorZ) Secondary predatorANSWER: W) PRODUCERRound 1Page 4
TOSS-UP9) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer The three components required for an oil reservoir to form are a source rock, a porous and permeable reservoir rock, and:ANSWER: A CAP ROCK (ACCEPT: SEAL, TRAP)BONUS9) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer Deposition of primarily which compound leads to the formation of stalactites and stalagmites in caves?ANSWER: CALCIUM CARBONATE________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following types of weathering is caused by acid rain?W) Chemical X) Mechanical Y) BioticZ) TropicalANSWER: W) CHEMICALBONUS10) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following can cause an increase in the amount of acid rain?W) Decrease in the ozone layerX) Increase in oil spillsY) Increased burning of fossil fuels Z) Decrease in pesticide useANSWER: Y) INCREASED BURNING OF FOSSIL FUELSRound 1Page 5
TOSS-UP11) ENERGY Multiple Choice Ethanol is being used as a way to reduce dependence on fossil fuels. Which of the following best describes the production of ethanol?W) Distilling gases available in waste, such as methanol X) Exposing batteries to sunlightY) Fermenting crops like corn and sugar caneZ) Using broken parts from cars as they get rustyANSWER: Y) FERMENTING CROPS LIKE CORN AND SUGAR CANEBONUS11) ENERGY Multiple Choice Biodiesel, which is another form of biomass energy, is obtained from:W) Food products, including vegetable oils and animal fatsX) Refining the available dieselY) Combining diesel with extractions from mineral bedsZ) Using a plant's photosynthesis (read as: fōe-tōe-SIN-teh-sis) processANSWER: W) FOOD PRODUCTS, INCLUDING VEGETABLE OILS AND ANIMAL FATS________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP12) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer How many hours of daylight does the South Pole receive on June 21?ANSWER: 0BONUS12) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Changes in length of daylight are primarily a result of:W) Change in the distance Earth is from the SunX) Change in the direction the Earth tilts relative to the Sun Y) Change in the Moon’s position relative to the SunZ) Change in how fast the Earth turns on its axisANSWER: X) CHANGE IN THE DIRECTION THE EARTH TILTS RELATIVE TO THE SUNRound 1 Page 6
TOSS-UP13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Neutrons are approximately the mass of:W) Protons X) Positrons Y) Electrons Z) NeutrinosANSWER: W) PROTONSBONUS13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Imagine if you could weigh electrons and protons on a simple balance. How many electrons do you need to balance a single proton?W) 18 hundredX) 18 thousandY) 18 millionZ) More than a billionANSWER: W) 18 hundred________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP14) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What type of boundary is described as two lithospheric plates moving toward one another and colliding?ANSWER: CONVERGENTBONUS14) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer The largest volcano on Mars is about 15 miles above the surrounding planes. What is the name of this volcano?ANSWER: OLYMPUS MONSRound 1 Page 7
TOSS-UP15) MATH Short Answer Evaluate (8 × 5 × 3 + 1) (read as: the square root of open parenthesis 8 times 5 times 3 plus 1 close parenthesis).ANSWER: 11BONUS15) MATH Short Answer Providing your answer as a decimal to the nearest tenth, evaluate 6x + 3 (read as: open absolute value, open parenthesis 6x + 3 close parenthesis divided by−5x-5x, close absolute value) for x = 6 .ANSWER: 1.3________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A yellow ball has a mass of 5 grams and a volume of 2 cubic centimeters. What is the density of the yellow ball in grams per cubic centimeter?ANSWER: 2.5BONUS16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A red ball has a mass of 2 grams and a volume of 8 cubic centimeters. A yellow ball has a mass of 5 grams and a volume of 2 cubic centimeters. When both balls are placed into a bucket of water, which of the following is true?W) The yellow ball floats and the red ball sinks X) The red ball floats and the yellow ball sinks Y) Both the red and yellow ball floatZ) Both the red and yellow ball sinkANSWER: X) THE RED BALL FLOATS AND THE YELLOW BALL SINKS    Round 1Page 8
TOSS-UP17) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice You find a new creature measuring over 4 millimeters in size in your bedroom. You notice that it has 6 legs so you know it is some type of:W) Arachnid (read as: ah-RAHK-nid)X) LarvaY) InsectZ) Echinoderm (read as: i-KY-neh-dehrm)ANSWER: Y) INSECT 17) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the scientific class to which spider belong?W) VertebrateX) Echinoderm (read as: i-KY-neh-dehrm) Y) Arachnid (read as: ah-RAHK-nid)Z) Amphibian (read as: ahm-FI-bee-ehn)ANSWER: Y) ARACHNIDBONUS________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP18) MATH Short Answer Simplify 8/52 to a fraction in simplest terms. ANSWER: 2/13BONUS18) MATH Short Answer Express (1/5 + 3.4) (read as: open parenthesis one fifth plus 3.4 close 2parenthesis divided by two) as a fraction in lowest terms. ANSWER: 9/5 Round 1 Page 9
TOSS-UP19) ENERGY Short Answer What is the general name for material that is used to block the flow of heat?ANSWER: INSULATORBONUS19) ENERGY Multiple Choice A metal coin and a plastic coin are heated to the same temperature. The two coins have the same size and shape, are dropped into the same tub of cold water at the same time, and are left for 30 seconds. Which coin will have the lower temperature?W) Metal coinX) Plastic coinY) Both coins will have the same temperature Z) Cannot be determinedANSWER: W) METAL COIN________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the metric unit for mass?W) The pound X) StonesY) The kilogram Z) The micronANSWER: Y) THE KILOGRAM20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the SI unit of force? ANSWER: NEWTONBONUSRound 1Page 10
TOSS-UP21) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following distances is longest?W) Half a kilometer X) Half a decimeter Y) 600 metersZ) 40 decametersANSWER: Y) 600 METERSBONUS21) MATH Short Answer What is the name of a line that intersects two or more coplanar lines in different points?ANSWER: TRANSVERSALTOSS-UP22) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What are the basic units of heredity? ANSWER: GENES (ACCEPT: DNA)BONUS22) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Which structural component of the cell cytoskeleton has alpha and beta subunits and is involved with intracellular transport?ANSWER: MICROTUBULES Round 1 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a fossil fuel? W) CoalX) Natural gasY) PetroleumZ) UraniumANSWER: Z) URANIUMBONUS23) ENERGY Multiple Choice Using current technologies, which of the following sources of energy is nonrenewable?W) SolarX) WindY) NuclearZ) GeothermalANSWER: Y) NUCLEAR________________________________________________________________________ TOSS-UP24) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT something a river can do to rock?W) Cut down through hundreds of meters of rock X) Polish rockY) Transport rock hundreds of milesZ) Melt rockANSWER: Z) MELT ROCKBONUS24) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer Thousands of rivers drain the continental United States. These rivers primarily drain into which three bodies of water?ANSWER: GULF OF MEXICO, ATLANTIC OCEAN (ACCEPT: GULF OF ST. LAWRENCE), PACIFIC OCEAN (ACCEPT: SEA OF CORTEZ, GULF OF CALIFORNIA)Round 1 Page 12
TOSS-UP25) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following describes how sea ice is different from continental ice?W) Continental ice is denser than sea iceX) Sea ice is saline while continental ice is freshY) Sea ice floats on the water while continental ice sits on landZ) Sea ice is constantly changing while continental ice remains the sameANSWER: Y) SEA ICE FLOATS ON THE WATER WHILE CONTINENTAL ICE SITS ON LANDBONUS25) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Sea ice floating on the oceans is the first to melt as the Earth’s climate warms. Which of the following most accurately models the impact melting sea ice has on global sea level?W) Like the water level in a basin when you pour a glass of water into it, sea level will rise significantlyX) The ocean floor rocks and sediments are porous like sponges. They will absorb the additional water from the ice and sea level will not rise significantlyY) Like a melting ice cube sitting in a glass of water, the water and the melted cube will evaporate and sea level will dropZ) Like ice cubes in a glass of water, the ice has already displaced the water so as the ice melts, sea level will not rise significantlyANSWER: Z) LIKE ICE CUBES IN A GLASS OF WATER, THE ICE HAS ALREADY DISPLACED THE WATER SO AS THE ICE MELTS, SEA LEVEL WILL NOT RISE SIGNIFICANTLYRound 1 Page 13