ROUND 6          W) Only heightX) Only height and length Y) Only length and width Z) Height, width and lengthANSWER: W) ONLY HEIGHTTOSS-UP1) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following methods of dissemination of bacterial genetic material is mismatched to its description?W) Transduction: viral transfer of one cell’s DNA to anotherX) Binary fission: cellular divisionY) Conjugation: through physical interaction, a donor cell transfers genetic material to a recipient cellZ) Transformation: one bacteria engulfs another to integrate its DNAANSWER: Z) TRANSFORMATION: ONE BACTERIA ENGULFS ANOTHER TO INTEGRATE ITS DNABONUS1) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In one form of epigenetics called genomic imprinting, DNA is silenced by what mechanism?W) MethylationX) Acetylation [uh-SET-l-ay-shuhn]Y) Phosphorylation [FOS-for-uh-lay-shuhn] Z) Ubiquitylation [yoo-bi-kwi-ty-LAY-shuhn]ANSWER W) METHYLATIONTOSS-UP2) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A box of proper length l, proper width w, and proper height h is falling right-side up without tumbling toward the ground. The Lorentz contraction predicts that which of the following dimensions will be contracted? BONUS2) PHYSICS Short Answer A curve banked at 45° has a radius of 62.5 meters. Assuming g = 10 meters per second squared, if a car is to navigate through the curve with no friction needed, with what speed, in meters per second, should the car travel?ANSWER: 25High School Round 6 A Page 1
TOSS-UP3) MATH Short Answer A cube painted red on all sides has an edge length of 4 inches. If the cube is then cut into 64 cubes of edge length 1 inch, how many of the 1 inch cubes have exactly one face painted red?ANSWER: 24ANSWER: Z) (3√2, 𝜋/4)TOSS-UPBONUS3) MATH Multiple Choice A point has rectangular coordinates (3, 3). What are its equivalent polar coordinates?W) (3, 𝜋/6) X) (3, 𝜋/4) Y) (3√2, 𝜋/6) Z) (3√2, 𝜋/4)    4) ENERGY Multiple Choice What percentage of the world’s geothermally produced electricity is produced in the United States?W) 11% X) 17% Y) 24% Z) 30%ANSWER: Z) 30%4) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a type of vacuum pump?W) Scroll pumpX) Roots blowerY) Diaphragm compressor Z) Turbomolecular pumpANSWER: Y) DIAPHRAGM COMPRESSORBONUSHigh School Round 6 A Page 2
TOSS-UP5) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following are the latitudes most favorable for tornadogenesis [tohr-nuh-doh-JEN-uh-sis]?W) 30 – 50 degrees north and south X) 45 – 60 degrees northY) 0 – 10 degrees north and south Z) 0 – 60 degrees northANSWER: W) 30- 50 DEGREES NORTH AND SOUTHBONUS5) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The rest frame lifetime of a muon is 2.2 microseconds. Muons are produced in the upper atmosphere by collisions with cosmic rays. The light travel time from the upper atmosphere to the ground is about 150 microseconds. Nevertheless, a substantial fraction of muons produced in the upper atmosphere are observed on the ground. For an observer on the ground, which of the following principles best explains this phenomenon?W) Length contractionX) Atmospheric scintillation Y) Time dilationZ) Pair productionANSWER: Y) TIME DILATION TOSS-UP6) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following molecules can NOT be isolated as an optically pure sample?W) Valine [VAL-een]X) Tartaric acidY) Epichlorohydrin [ep-i-klawr-uh-HY-drin]Z) Trans-4-chlorocyclohexanol [klohr-oh-SY-kloh-HEK-suh-nol]ANSWER: Z) TRANS-4-CHLOROCYCLOHEXANOLBONUS6) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What two chemists, in 2001, were awarded half the Nobel Prize for their work on asymmetric hydrogenation?ANSWER: KNOWLES AND NOYORIHigh School Round 6 A Page 3
TOSS-UP7) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following infectious agents should a human be least concerned about contracting?W) PrionX) ViroidY) Retrovirus Z) RNA virusANSWER: X) VIROIDW) Protease X) Ribosome Y) PepsinZ) KinaseANSWER: X) RIBOSOMEBONUS7) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following molecules catalyzes the formation of peptide bonds between amino acids? TOSS-UP8) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true?W) Electrons, protons, and neutrons obey the Pauli exclusion principle X) The Pauli exclusion principle applies to all fermionsY) All fermions have a spin of 1/2Z) Electrons, protons, and neutrons obey Fermi-Dirac distributionANSWER: Y) ALL FERMIONS HAVE A SPIN OF 1/2BONUS8) PHYSICS Short Answer Two light waves travel the same distance of 6 × 10-7 meters but in mediums of refractive indices 1.54 and 1.00. Providing your answer in scientific notation to one significant figure, what is the time delay in seconds between waves?ANSWER: 1 × 10-15High School Round 6 A Page 4
TOSS-UP9) MATH Multiple Choice The price of an item is discounted by 10% and then the new price is further discounted by 20%. What single discount is equivalent to this double discount?W) 15% X) 28% Y) 30% Z) 72%ANSWER: X) 28%9) MATH Short Answer Let g(x) = (x − 1)2 [g of x equal the square of the quantity x minus1]. What is the set of all real values of x for which g(x) > 4 [g of x is greater than 4]? ANSWER: x < -1 OR x > 3 (MUST GIVE BOTH ANSWERS)TOSS-UP10) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following metals reacts violently with water?BONUS W) Gold X) Lithium Y) IronZ) MercuryANSWER: X) LITHIUM10) ENERGY Multiple Choice How many electrons are transferred for the complete electrochemical oxidation of one hydrogen molecule in a fuel cell?W) 1 X) 2 Y) 4 Z) 6ANSWER: X) 2BONUSHigh School Round 6 A Page 5
TOSS-UP11) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following factors is most important in controlling the density of seawater?W) TemperatureX) SalinityY) PressureZ) Amount of oxygen in waterANSWER: W) TEMPERATUREBONUS11) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer The Palmer Drought Severity Index is based on five factors: precipitation, evapotranspiration, the amount of water needed for soil recharge, the amount of runoff needed to keep bodies of water at normal levels and what other factor?ANSWER: STORED SOIL MOISTURE (ACCEPT: SOIL MOISTURE)TOSS-UP12) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true of polyunsaturated fatty acids?W) They are highly concentrated in cell membranes of the nervous system X) They are the most prevalent fatty acid found in the human bodyY) They contain two or more double bondsZ) They play a crucial role in brain functionANSWER: X) THEY ARE THE MOST PREVALENT FATTY ACID FOUND IN THE HUMAN BODYBONUS12) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of conjugated dienes [DY- eens]?W) Increasing conjugation is proportional to increased UV wavelength absorption X) Heats of formation are lower than unconjugated dienesY) s-trans dienes participate in Diels-Alder cyclizationZ) At lower temperatures, 1, 2-addition products predominateANSWER: Y) s-TRANS DIENES PARTICIPATE IN DIELS-ALDER CYCLIZATION High School Round 6 A Page 6
TOSS-UP13) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following portions of a gene could ultimately be translated to protein?W) ExonX) Terminator Y) IntronZ) PromoterANSWER: W) EXONwhat length in meters do you measure the spaceship?2T.AtW) 50 X) 50 √3 Y) 100 Z) 200BONUS13) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice What is the reason why many modern crop-producing plants, such as wheat, have much larger cell volumes than the ancestral wild plants from which they were derived?W) Plants can tolerate trisomy [TRY-soh-mee]X) Plants can tolerate polyploidy [pol-ee-PLOI-dee] Y) Plants have been genetically engineeredZ) Plants tolerate gene duplicationsANSWER X) PLANTS CAN TOLERATE POLYPLOIDYTOSS-UP14) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A projectile is launched tangentially to the Earth's surface with a speed such that it will neither collide with the Earth nor escape its gravity. Ignoring air resistance, this projectile's trajectory will have what shape?W) Parabolic X) CircularY) Elliptical X) HyperbolicANSWER: Y) ELLIPTICAL14) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A 100 meter spaceship moves past you with speed √3𝑐/2 BONUS  ANSWER: W) 50High School Round 6 A Page 7
TOSS-UP15) MATH Multiple Choice In the mid-state football conference, each team plays every other team exactly once during a calendar year. If a total of 45 conference games were played in 2012, how many teams were in the conference?W) 8 X) 9 Y) 10 Z) 11ANSWER: Y) 1015) MATH Short Answer Given 𝑓(𝑥) = √2 − 𝑥 [f of x equals the square root of the quantity 2BONUSminus x], for what value or values of x does f(x+2) = 1 [f of the quantity x plus 2 equals 1]? ANSWER: x = -1TOSS-UP16) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following will generally cause the kinetics of a reaction to increase?W) Decreasing surface areaX) Decreasing concentrationY) Increasing temperatureZ) Increasing number of side reactionsANSWER: Y) INCREASING TEMPERATUREBONUS16) ENERGY Short Answer In megajoules, how much energy does a 2.5 kilowatt stove use if turned on for two hours?ANSWER: 18  High School Round 6 A Page 8
TOSS-UP17) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The Coriolis effect causes objects moving in the Northern Hemisphere to veer in which of the following ways?W) To the right, or clockwise when viewed from aboveX) To the left, or counterclockwise when viewed from above Y) In an upward directionZ) In a downward directionANSWER: W) TO THE RIGHT, OR CLOCKWISE WHEN VIEWED FROM ABOVEBONUS17) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer The average kinetic energy of ions in the solar core is too low to overcome the Coulomb barrier between the ions. What phenomenon allows nuclear fusion to take place nevertheless?ANSWER: QUANTUM TUNNELINGTOSS-UP18) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is generally NOT considered to be an appropriate SN2 electrophile? W) Benzyl bromide X) Allyl bromideY) Propargyl bromide Z) Vinyl bromideANSWER: Z) VINYL BROMIDEBONUS18) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the major organic product formed when 1-butanol is treated with the Collins reagent?ANSWER: BUTANALHigh School Round 6 A Page 9
TOSS-UP19) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In a landmark 1958 study by researchers Meselson and Stahl involving nitrogen isotope labeling, which of the following important DNA replication mechanisms was supported by their data?W) Semiconservative X) DispersiveY) ConservativeZ) TransformativeANSWER: W) SEMICONSERVATIVEW) CalculusX) CariesY) CarbuncleZ) Cachexia [kuh-KEK-see-uh]ANSWER: W) CALCULUSBONUS19) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice What is the term for deposition of solid matter composed of mineral substances and salts, formed in any portion of the human body, such as kidney stones? TOSS-UP20) PHYSICS Short Answer Ryan, who weighs 150 pounds, and Kate, who weighs 50 pounds, are standing on slippery ice and push off from each other. Ignoring friction, if Ryan moves off at 1 meter per second, Kate moves off with what speed in meters per second?ANSWER: 3BONUS20) PHYSICS Multiple Choice The orbit of Mercury has a semi major axis of 0.4 AU and an eccentricity of 0.2. At which of the following distances from the Sun in AU will Mercury move the slowest?W) 0.3 X) 0.4 Y) 0.5 Z) 0.8ANSWER: Y) 0.5High School Round 6 A Page 10
TOSS-UP21) MATH Short Answer The IQ of a Martian varies directly with the square of the number of tentacles it has. If a Martian with 5 tentacles has an IQ of 75, what is the IQ of a Martian having 8 tentacles?ANSWER: 19221) MATH Multiple Choice If y = 2cos2x [y equals 2 cosine squared of x], what is dy/dx atx = 𝜋/4?BONUSW) -2 X) -1 Y) 1 Z) 2ANSWER: W) -2 TOSS-UP22) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What two underwater events can cause tsunamis? ANSWER: EARTHQUAKES AND VOLCANIC ERUPTIONS (ACCEPT: SUBMARINELANDSLIDES, MASS WASTING EVENTS, LANDSLIDES)BONUS22) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Even if nothing was done to clean up the 2010 Deepwater Horizon oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico, which of the following areas would likely remain unaffected by the oil floating on the surface?W) BrazilX) FloridaY) Cape HatterasZ) Yucatan PeninsulaANSWER: W) BRAZILHigh School Round 6 A Page 11
TOSS-UP23) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice According to the integrated form of the Clausius [KLOU-zee- uhs]-Clapeyron equation solved for the natural logarithm of vapor pressure, vapor pressure and absolute temperature data can be plotted to give a straight line. Which of the following corresponds to the slope?W) –∆Hvap/R [negative delta H of vaporization over R] X) ∆Hvap/R [delta H of vaporization over R]Y) –R/∆Hvap [negative R over delta H of vaporization] Z) R/∆Hvap [R over delta H of vaporization]ANSWER: W) –∆Hvap/R23) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Place the following four substances in order from lowest tohighest boiling point: 1) carbon tetrachloride, 2) ethane, 3) propane, 4) water.ANSWER: 2, 3, 1, 4 (ACCEPT: ETHANE, PROPANE, CARBON TETRACHLORIDE, WATER)TOSS-UP24) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the one type of infectious agent that contains no nucleic acid?ANSWER: PRIONBONUS24) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Loss of the retinoblastoma gene product, Rb, causes cancer by affecting which of the following portions of the cell cycle?W) G1/S checkpoint X) S/G2 checkpoint Y) G2/M checkpoint Z) M/G1 checkpointANSWER: W) G1/S CHECKPOINTBONUS High School Round 6 A Page 12
TOSS-UP25) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following quantities has an inverse-cubic relationship with distance?W) The magnitude of the gravitational force between two point massesX) The electric potential energy for a point chargeY) The magnetic field strength at an axial point from the center of a current loop Z) The speed of a satellite in circular orbit around the EarthANSWER: Y) THE MAGNETIC FIELD STRENGTH AT AN AXIAL POINT FROM THE CENTER OF A CURRENT LOOPBONUS25) PHYSICS Short Answer A horizontal water pipe tapers so that the cross-sectional area of the pipe decreases. If the water moves at 3 meters per second in the larger portion of the pipe and at 15 meters per second in the smaller portion, what is the change in pressure, in pascals, as the water moves from the larger portion to the smaller portion of the pipe? Assume the density of water is 1000 kilograms per cubic meter and incompressible.ANSWER: -108000 (DO NOT ACCEPT: 108000)High School Round 6 A Page 13