ROUND 16          W) 10X) 100 Y) 1000 Z) 10000ANSWER: X) 100TOSS-UP1) BIOLOGY Short Answer Name the taxonomic order in which the gharial [GUHR-ee-uhl] or gavial [GAY-vee-uhl], Gavialis gangeticus [ga-vee-AL-is gan-JET-uh-kuhs], is found.ANSWER: CROCODILIABONUS1) BIOLOGY Short Answer Identify all of the following four cranial nerves that have a purely somatic motor function: 1) Trigeminal [try-JEM-uh-nl], 2) Trochlear [TROK-lee-er], 3) Hypoglossal, 4) Glossopharyngeal [glos-oh-fuh-RIN-jee-uhl].ANSWER: 2 AND 3 (ACCEPT: TROCHLEAR, HYPOGLOSSAL)TOSS-UP2) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Assuming g = 10 meters per second squared and the density of freshwater is 1000 kilograms per cubic meter, what is the buoyancy force in newtons exerted on a rock with mass of 100 kilograms and a volume of 10,000 cubic centimeters sitting at the bottom of a freshwater lake? BONUS2) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following best estimates the momentum carried by an electromagnetic wave with energy of 30 joules?W) 10-7X) 10-5Y) 3 x 10-7 Z) 9 x 10-5ANSWER: W) 10-7High School Round 16 A Page 1
TOSS-UP3) MATH Multiple Choice The points on a scatter plot are extremely close to their least-squares regression line, which is expressed by the equation y = -2x + 3. The correlation coefficient r between x and y is closest to which of the following?W) -2 X) -1 Y) 1/2 Z) 1ANSWER: X) -1BONUSTOSS-UP3) MATH Short Answer For the implicit function xy2 + x3y = 2, what is the slope of its tangent line at the point (1, 1)?ANSWER: -4/34) ENERGY Multiple Choice Why do solid oxide fuel cells not require a precious metal catalyst or fuel reformer?W) They do not rely on the hydrogen-oxygen redox couple X) They have a high operating temperatureY) They have a very fast startup timeZ) They have a low operating temperatureANSWER: X) THEY HAVE A HIGH OPERATING TEMPERATUREBONUS4) ENERGY Short Answer Graphene sheets, often used in solar cells and capacitors, have carbon rings with which type of lattice?ANSWER: HEXAGONAL (ACCEPT: HONEYCOMB) High School Round 16 A Page 2
TOSS-UP5) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The Burgess Shale, in the Canadian Rockies, is best known for which of the following fossils?W) Proterozoic terrestrial plant [prot-er-uh-ZOH-ik] X) Cambrian marineY) K/T boundary dinosaurZ) Peat bog humanANSWER: X) CAMBRIAN MARINEBONUS5) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer To the nearest 10, how many times has the Sun orbited the galaxy since the Sun formed?ANSWER: 20TOSS-UP6) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Organolithium [ohr-guh-noh-LITH-ee-uhm] reagents can be reacted with salts made from which element to form a Gilman reagent? Specify both the element and its oxidation state.ANSWER: COPPER 1+ (ACCEPT: COPPER, 1)BONUS6) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Catalytic cracking is the most commonly used process in the manufacture of olefins. Different products can be produced from different reactants. If you want to produce an aromatic through cracking followed by dehydration, with what reactant should you begin?ANSWER: NAPHTHENE(S) (ACCEPT: CYCLOALKANE(S)) High School Round 16 A Page 3
TOSS-UP7) BIOLOGY Short Answer Of the 20 amino acids encoded by the universal genetic code, only one is technically an imino acid, as the R-group is covalently bonded to the amino terminus to form a nitrogen-containing ring. Unless it is modified, this amino acid also tends to disrupt secondary structures such as alpha-helices and beta sheets if it is found in the middle of them. What is this amino acid?ANSWER: PROLINEBONUS7) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice What is the predicted size in billions of base pairs of the woolly- mammoth genome?W) 1 X) 4 Y) 33 Z) 100ANSWER: X) 4 TOSS-UP8) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Given R = 1.097 × 107 inverse meters, which of the following represents the wavelength of the longest wavelength Lyman line of the hydrogen spectrum in meters and the region of the electromagnetic spectrum in which it lies?W) 1.22 × 10-7; ultraviolet X) 1.22 × 10-7; visibleY) 1.22 × 10-6; infrared Z) 1.22 × 10-6; visibleANSWER: W) 1.22 × 10-7; ULTRAVIOLETBONUS8) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Assuming a metabolic rate of 500 watts, how much energy in joules is transformed by a 70 kilogram person while exercising for 1 hour?W) 1500X) 1.8 million Y) 5 .4 million Z) 6.3 trillionANSWER: X) 1.8 MILLIONHigh School Round 16 A Page 4
with numerator sine of x and denominator x minus pi]?W) -1X) 0Y) 1Z) UndefinedANSWER: W) -1W) aX) 2a Y) a + b Z) b/aANSWER: W) aTOSS-UP9) MATH Multiple Choice What is lim𝑥→𝜋 sin 𝑥 [the limit as x approaches pi of the fraction 𝑥− 𝜋 BONUS9) MATH Multiple Choice The line determined by points (0, 2b) and (2a, 0) intersects the line determined by points (0, b) and (a, b). What represents the x-value of the point where the two lines intersect? W) 80 X) 160 Y) 240 Z) 320ANSWER: W) 80TOSS-UP10) ENERGY Multiple Choice What is the typical hub height in meters of a utility-scale wind turbine?BONUS10) ENERGY Short Answer By number, rank the thermal resistance of the following four insulation materials from greatest to least: 1) Glass, 2) Closed-cell polyurethane [pol-ee-YOOR- uh-thayn] spray foam, 3) Polystyrene [pol-ee-STY-reen] board, 4) Fiberglass batts.ANSWER: 2, 3, 4, 1High School Round 16 A Page 5
TOSS-UP11) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Scientists currently believe that modern birds descended from what organisms?W) Pterosaurs [TER-uh-sawrs] X) OrnithopodsY) TherapodsZ) SauropodsANSWER: Y) THERAPODSBONUS11) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice When the Milky Way and Andromeda galaxies merge, which of the following is closest to the number of pairs of stars that are expected to collide?W) 1X) 100Y) 10,000Z) 1,000,000ANSWER: W) 1 TOSS-UP12) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following spectral series has a final energy level of 4?W) Paschen [PA-shen] X) BrackettY) Pfund [PFOONT]Z) LymanANSWER: X) BRACKETT12) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Place the following four solvents in order of fastest to slowestreaction rate for SN2: 1) water, 2) DMSO, 3) methanol, 4) acetonitrile [as-i-toh-NY-tril]. ANSWER: 4, 2, 1, 3 (ACCEPT: ACETONITRILE, DMSO, WATER, METHANOL)BONUSHigh School Round 16 A Page 6
TOSS-UP13) BIOLOGY Short Answer In segmented animals, a specific family of genes is particularly important for directing the orientation and placement of structures and segments. These genes encode transcription factors that are able to bind a regulatory region of DNA called the homeobox. Name this gene family.ANSWER: HOXBONUS13) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is true about reverse phase chromatography?W) The stationary phase is hydrophilic [hy-druh-FIL-ik] X) The stationary phase is acidicY) It is typically used for separation of proteinsZ) The stationary phase is hydrophobicANSWER: Z) THE STATIONARY PHASE IS HYDROPHOBICTOSS-UP 14) PHYSICS Multiple Choice What is the speed of a particle that has a Lorentz factor of 3.0?W) 2𝑐√3X) (3𝑐√2)/2 Y) (2𝑐 √2)/3 Z) (𝑐√2 )⁄3    ANSWER: Y) (2𝑐√2)/3BONUS 14) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A sports car driver slams the brakes and the car slows from 90 miles per hour to a complete stop in 4 seconds. In terms of g, which of the following is closest to the car’s acceleration?W) -0.5 g X) -gY) -2gZ) -5gANSWER: X) -gHigh School Round 16 A Page 7
TOSS-UP15) MATH Short Answer Find an antiderivative for 𝑙𝑙(𝑒−𝑥2) [the natural log of the quantity e to the power of negative x squared].ANSWER: -(1/3)x3 (ACCEPT: GIVEN ANSWER PLUS ANY CONSTANT) BONUS15) MATH Short Answer A curve is defined parametrically by x = cost [x equals cosine of t] and y = tant [y equals tangent of t]. What is dy/dx when t = π/6?ANSWER: -8/3TOSS-UP16) ENERGY Multiple Choice As you turn on your flashlight, its lithium-ion battery begins to discharge. What happens to the electrons and ions inside the battery?W) Both the electrons and the lithium ions move towards the cathodeX) Both the electrons and the lithium ions move towards the anodeY) The electrons move towards the cathode while the lithium ions move towards the anode Z) The electrons move towards the anode while the lithium ions move towards the cathodeANSWER: W) BOTH THE ELECTRONS AND THE LITHIUM IONS MOVE TOWARDS THE CATHODEBONUS16) ENERGY Short Answer If a city had a yearly load of 438,000 megawatt hours and built a power plant with a capacity factor of 50%, what would the nameplate capacity have to be in megawatts in order to meet total load?ANSWER: 100 High School Round 16 A Page 8
TOSS-UP17) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice In which of the following ways does the mineral biotite [BY-uh-tyt] differ from the mineral muscovite [MUHS-kuh-vyt]?W) Biotite contains silica while muscovite does notX) Muscovite contains potassium while biotite does notY) While both contain aluminum, only biotite contains magnesium Z) While both contain sodium, only muscovite contains aluminumANSWER: Y) WHILE BOTH CONTAIN ALUMINUM, ONLY BIOTITE CONTAINS MAGNESIUMBONUS17) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Arrange the following four Big Bang events in chronological order: 1) nucleosynthesis, 2) reionization, 3) recombination, 4) inflation.ANSWER: 4, 1, 3, 2 (ACCEPT: INFLATION, NUCLEOSYNTHESIS, RECOMBINATION, REIONIZATION)TOSS-UP18) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following protein purification techniques coats proteins with a negative charge after they are denatured? W) Affinity chromatographyX) Isoelectric focusingY) SDS-PAGEZ) Ion exchange chromatographyANSWER: Y) SDS-PAGEBONUS18) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice You are studying a material that has started to undergo thermal fatigue. Which of the following would be a good action to take to reduce this fatigue?W) Eliminate loading by designX) Add protective surface coatingY) Decrease corrosiveness of medium Z) Add residual compressive stressesANSWER: W) ELIMINATE LOADING BY DESIGNHigh School Round 16 A Page 9
TOSS-UP19) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In which of the following cell processes would caspase activity most likely occur?W) Mitosis [my-TOH-sis]X) ApoptosisY) DNA replicationZ) Phagocytosis [fag-uh-sy-TOH-sis]ANSWER: X) APOPTOSISX) T = 𝜏/λ [Half-life equals tau over lambda]Y) T 1/2= 𝜏 log e [Half-life equals tau log base 2 of e] 1/2 2Z) T1/2 = 𝜏 ln (2) [Half-life equals tau natural log of 2] 1/2BONUS19) BIOLOGY Short Answer By number, identify all of the following four phrases that would NOT be indicative of a healthy stream ecosystem: 1) woody riparian zone that is equal to or greater than stream width; 2) abundant algal mats in stream channel; 3) stream channel with abundant large rocks and old logs; 4) banks unstable with easily disturbed loose soil.ANSWER: 2, 4TOSS-UP 20) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following is the correct relationship of half-life T1/2 and mean life 𝜏 [tau] of an unstable particle, if λ [lambda] is the decay constant?W) T = λ/𝜏 [Half-life equals lambda over tau]= 𝜏 ln (2)20) PHYSICS Multiple Choice What is the image position in centimeters of a narrow objectplaced 100 centimeters from a 50 centimeter focal length lens?W) 20 X) 25 Y) 50 Z) 100ANSWER: Z) 100ANSWER: Z) T1/2BONUSHigh School Round 16 A Page 10
ANSWER: X) (−∞, −3) ∪ (3, ∞)21) MATH Short Answer Solve the following equation for x over the interval 0 ≤ x < 2π:2sin2x − sinx – 1 = 0 [2 sine squared of x minus sine of x minus 1 equals 0]. ANSWER: π/2 , 7π/6, AND 11π/6TOSS-UP21) MATH Multiple Choice What is the largest possible real domain of the function h(x) = ln(x2 – 9) [h of x equals the natural log of the quantity x squared minus 9]?W) (−∞, ∞)X) (−∞, −3) ∪ (3, ∞) [the open interval from negative infinity to negative 3 union the open interval from 3 to positive infinity]Y) (−3, 3)Z) (3, ∞)BONUS TOSS-UP22) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The interstellar medium is primarily composed of two components, a warm ionized phase and a cool neutral phase. Which of the following is approximately the temperature in Kelvin of the cool phase?W) 1X) 10 Y) 100 Z) 1000ANSWER: Y) 100BONUS22) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following geometries is inconsistent with a flat universe?W) InfiniteX) Toroidal [toh-ROID-l] Y) HornZ) ConicalANSWER: Y) HORNHigh School Round 16 A Page 11
TOSS-UP23) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice A variety of manufacturing processes may be employed in nanotechnology. Which of the following processes can coat almost anything by transferring material from its source to the substrate without changing chemical composition?W) E-beamX) Nanoscale printing Y) Vapor deposition Z) Soft lithographyANSWER: Y) VAPOR DEPOSITIONBONUS23) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Arrange the following three methods of solvent degassing in order from least effective to most effective: 1) atmosphere exchange under sonication, 2) purging, 3) freeze-pump-thaw.ANSWER: 2, 1, 3 (ACCEPT: PURGING, ATMOSPHERE EXCHANGE UNDER SONICATION, FREEZE-PUMP-THAW)TOSS-UP24) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Lysosomes [LY-suh-sohms] are membrane-enclosed organelles in a cell containing an array of enzymes. Which of the following is closest to the pH of these vesicles? W) 5 X) 6 Y) 7 Z) 8ANSWER: W) 5BONUS24) BIOLOGY Short Answer With regard to the maturation of an erythrocyte [ih-RITH-ruh-syt], arrange the following four choices in correct sequence starting with the cell type after the proerythroblast [proh-i-RITH-ruh-blast] and ending with the mature erythrocyte: 1) Basophilic [bay-suh-FIL-ik] erythroblast, 2) Reticulocyte [ri-TIK-yoo-luh-syt], 3) Orthochromatic [ohr- thuh-kroh-MAT-ik] normoblast, 4) Polychromatophilic [poh-lee-kroh-muh-tuh-fil-ik] erythroblast.ANSWER: 1, 4, 3, 2 (ACCEPT: BASOPHILIC ERYTHROBLAST, POLYCHROMATOPHILIC ERYTHROBLAST, ORTHOCHROMATIC NORMOBLAST, RETICULOCYTE)High School Round 16 A Page 12
TOSS-UP25) PHYSICS Multiple Choice In a nuclear plant, 1 kilogram of mass is converted to energy. Given c = 3 x 108 meters per second, how much energy would be produced?W) 9 megajoules X) 9 gigajoules Y) 3 terajoules Z) 90 petajoulesANSWER: Z) 90 PETAJOULESBONUS25) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Bats find their prey in the dark via echolocation [ek-oh-loh-KAY- shuhn]. Given that the speed of sound is 300 meters per second, if a bat emits a chirp at a frequency of 66 kilohertz, what is the smallest size of insect in millimeters it is able to detect?W) 0.2 X) 1 Y) 5 Z) 16ANSWER: Y) 5High School Round 16 A Page 13