ROUND 4          TOSS-UP1) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Mammals first evolved during what geologic period?W) PermianX) TriassicY) Cretaceous [kri-TAY-shuhs] Z) Paleocene [pay-lee-uh-SEEN]ANSWER: X) TRIASSICBONUS1) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the series used in igneous [IG-nee-uhs] petrology that explains why certain types of minerals tend to be found together while others are almost never associated with one another?ANSWER: BOWEN’S REACTION SERIESTOSS-UP2) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In DNA replication, which of the following molecules is synthesized in the same direction that the replication fork is moving? W) Leading strand X) Okazaki fragment Y) PrimerZ) Lagging strandANSWER: W) LEADING STRANDBONUS2) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes the type of RNA that codes for a complete gene on the sense strand of a DNA molecule?W) Ribosomal RNA [ry-BUH-soh-muhl]X) Mitochondrial RNA [my-tuh-KON-dree-uhl] Y) Pre-messenger RNAZ) Transfer RNAANSWER: Y) PRE-MESSENGER RNAHigh School Round 4 A Page 1
TOSS-UP3) MATH Short Answer The average of a and b is x. The average of b and x equals the average of a and (b + 1). Find a – b.ANSWER: -23) MATH Short Answer What is the reciprocal of the complex number 2 + i?ANSWER: (2/5) – (1/5)i (ACCEPT: 0.4 – 0.2i) TOSS-UPBONUS 4) ENERGY Multiple Choice The majority of moth species forage for food energy during what stage of their life cycle?W) Egg X) Larva Y) Pupa Z) AdultANSWER: X) LARVABONUS4) ENERGY Short Answer The electrical resistance of a semiconducting wire is least likely to be reduced by a decrease in which two of the following four wire characteristics?(1) melting point, (2) radius, (3) length, (4) temperatureANSWER: 1 and 2 (ACCEPT: MELTING POINT AND RADIUS)High School Round 4 A Page 2
TOSS-UP5) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice With regard to the Rosenmund reduction, which of the following functional group pairs corresponds to the reactant and product, respectively?W) Ester and alcoholX) Acyl [AS-il] chloride and aldehyde [AL-duh-hyd] Y) Amide and amine [uh-MEEN]Z) Ketone and alkane [AL-kayn]ANSWER: X) ACYL CHLORIDE AND ALDEHYDEBONUS5) CHEMISTRY Short Answer In the industrially important water-gas shift reaction, carbon monoxide and water vapor react to form carbon dioxide gas and hydrogen gas as products. If the system is closed and the reaction has reached equilibrium [ee-kwuh-LIB-ree-uhm], how would the equilibrium shift if the volume is decreased?ANSWER: UNCHANGED (ACCEPT: THERE IS NO SHIFT)TOSS-UP6) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A human eye has three layers with refractive indices n1 , n2 , and n3, where n1 < n2 and n1 = n3 . Which of the following properties of a light ray is the same in all layers? W) Frequency onlyX) Speed onlyY) Wavelength onlyZ) Frequency and speedANSWER: W) FREQUENCY ONLYBONUS6) PHYSICS Short Answer A door of area 3 square meters and thickness 4 centimeters is composed of a material whose thermal conductivity is 0.10 watts per meter Kelvin. What is the heat flow, in watts, through the door when the temperature difference is 10 Kelvin?ANSWER: 75High School Round 4 A Page 3
TOSS-UP7) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following volcanoes form in ocean- continent and ocean-ocean convergent plate boundaries?W) ShieldX) StratovolcanoesY) Hot spot volcanoes Z) Basaltic volcanoesANSWER: X) STRATOVOLCANOESBONUS7) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of a negative feedback cycle?W) The polar climate warms, permafrost melts, microbes digest vegetation and release methane, the methane further warms polar climateX) The polar climate warms, sea ice melts, albedo lowers, and polar climate further warms Y) Global warming causes more water to evaporate from the surface, which condenses into clouds that then reflect more sunlight back to space, which cools the EarthZ) Global warming causes the southwestern U.S. to become even drier, reduced evaporation leads to fewer clouds so the Earth's albedo remains low, thus warming the climateANSWER: Y) GLOBAL WARMING CAUSES MORE WATER TO EVAPORATE FROM THE SURFACE, WHICH CONDENSES INTO CLOUDS THAT THEN REFLECT MORE SUNLIGHT BACK TO SPACE, WHICH COOLS THE EARTHTOSS-UP8) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the term for the type of plant that is adapted to living in a saline environment?ANSWER: HALOPHYTEBONUS8) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Carbohydrates are best defined as which of the following?W) Inorganic compounds containing carbon, hydrogen, and oxygen in a ratio of 1:2:1 X) Organic compounds containing carbon, hydrogen, and oxygen in a ratio of 1:2:1 Y) Organic compounds containing carbon, hydrogen, and oxygen in a ratio of 2:1:2 Z) Inorganic compounds containing carbon, hydrogen, and oxygen in a ratio of 2:1:2ANSWER: X) ORGANIC COMPOUNDS CONTAINING CARBON, HYDROGEN, AND OXYGEN IN A RATIO OF 1:2:1 High School Round 4 A Page 4
TOSS-UPBONUS9) MATH Short Answer Four consecutive odd integers are added. If the smallest integer is 2m – 1, then what is their sum in terms of m?ANSWER: 8m + 89) MATH Short Answer Given (2x)(3y)(5z) = 2700 [2 to the power of x times 3 to the power ofy times 5 to the power of z equals 2700], find the product xyz. ANSWER: 12TOSS-UP10) ENERGY Multiple Choice In which of the following types of electrical equipment is high resistance most undesirable?W) Superconducting magnet X) HeaterY) StoveZ) Incandescent light bulbANSWER: W) SUPERCONDUCTING MAGNETBONUS10) ENERGY Multiple Choice Why are natural gas-fired plants typically used for peaking production?W) They are built to have high efficiencyX) Fuel costs are very stable over timeY) Natural gas is more abundant than coal Z) They have relatively fast response timesANSWER: Z) THEY HAVE RELATIVELY FAST RESPONSE TIMES High School Round 4 A Page 5
TOSS-UP11) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following pairs of compounds, when placed in water, would be expected to yield a precipitate?W) Ammonium chloride and sodium nitrate X) Sodium acetate and lithium hydroxide Y) Potassium sulfide and copper (II) sulfate Z) Nitric acid and ammoniaANSWER: Y) POTASSIUM SULFIDE AND COPPER (II) SULFATEBONUS11) CHEMISTRY Short Answer There are two elements whose ground state electron configurations contain exactly two half-filled subshells. What are these two elements?ANSWER: CHROMIUM AND MOLYBDENUMTOSS-UP12) PHYSICS Short Answer A cheetah has an ability to accelerate from 0 to 30 meters per second in three seconds. Assuming constant acceleration, what distance in meters can the cheetah cover in this time interval?ANSWER: 45BONUS12) PHYSICS Short Answer A pilot in training is placed into a human centrifuge where she will experience 5 g of force pulling her inward, the acceleration at which most people will begin to lose consciousness. Given g as 10 meters per second squared, if the centrifuge has a mechanical arm that holds her at a radius of 8 meters, how fast will the pilot be traveling in meters per second?ANSWER: 20 High School Round 4 A Page 6
TOSS-UP13) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Tsunamis are most likely to be generated in which of the following oceans?W) ArcticX) Atlantic Y) Pacific Z) SouthernANSWER: Y) PACIFICW) Barchan [bahr-KAHN] X) TraverseY) ParabolicZ) LongitudinalANSWER: W) BARCHANBONUS13) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice What is the term for a crescent-shaped sand dune with horns pointed downwind? TOSS-UP14) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of a negative chemotactic response in bacteria?W) Marine bacteria that use carbon dioxide as a nutrient are able to sense the concentration and move toward more highly-concentrated areasX) Bacteria being viewed under a microscope move away from the lightY) In a petri dish, E. coli will move away from concentrated areas of acetateZ) Photosynthetic bacteria will move towards the light in a gradientANSWER: Y) IN A PETRI DISH, E. COLI WILL MOVE AWAY FROM CONCENTRATED AREAS OF ACETATEBONUS14) BIOLOGY Short Answer What are the five major steps in Holozoic nutrition? ANSWER: INGESTION, DIGESTION, ABSORPTION, ASSIMILATION, EGESTIONHigh School Round 4 A Page 7
TOSS-UP15) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A chunk of gold with a density of 19,300 kilograms per cubic meter and volume of 0.3 cubic meters is completely submerged in water. Assuming g = 10 meters per second squared and the density of water is 1000 kilograms per cubic meter, what is the apparent weight of the gold in newtons?W) 54,900 X) 64,900 Y) 183,000 Z) 193,000ANSWER: W) 54,900BONUS15) PHYSICS Short Answer At the bottom of a loop-the-loop on a roller coaster, Mike’s apparent weight is three times his weight. Assuming g = 10 meters per second squared and the diameter of the loop-the-loop is 20 meters, what is Mike’s speed as a whole number in meters per second?ANSWER: 14TOSS-UP16) MATH Multiple Choice If an arc of 60° on circle 1 has the same length as an arc of 45° on circle 2, what is the ratio of the area of circle 1 to the area of circle 2? W) 16:9 X) 9:16 Y) 4:3 Z) 3:4ANSWER: X) 9:16BONUS16) MATH Multiple Choice A tourist begins a city stroll at an intersection. He walks north one block and then flips a coin. If the coin shows heads, he turns right; if it is tails, he turns left. In all, he walks a total of four blocks, flipping the coin at each corner to decide which way to turn. What is the probability that he ends at the starting point?W) 1/8 X) 1/4 Y) 1/3 Z) 1/2ANSWER: X) 1/4High School Round 4 A Page 8
TOSS-UP17) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes the difference between gas diffusion and gas effusion?W) Diffusion occurs at constant temperature while effusion occurs at variable temperatures X) Diffusion can occur with any gas while effusion occurs only with certain gasesY) Diffusion involves gas molecules at the same total pressure while effusion involves gases moving from high pressure to low pressureZ) Diffusion is mass dependent while effusion is mass independentANSWER: Y) DIFFUSION INVOLVES GAS MOLECULES AT THE SAME TOTAL PRESSURE WHILE EFFUSION INVOLVES GASES MOVING FROM HIGH PRESSURE TO LOW PRESSUREBONUS17) CHEMISTRY Short Answer According to kinetic-molecular theory, what is the mathematical relationship between molar mass and average gas phase speed?ANSWER: INVERSE SQUARETOSS-UP18) PHYSICS Short Answer By number, rank from greatest to least the moments of inertia for a golf club rotated about the following axes: 1) through the center of mass and parallel to the long axis of the club; 2) through the end of the handle and perpendicular to the long axis of the club; 3) through the center of mass and perpendicular to the long axis of the club.ANSWER: 2, 3, 1BONUS18) PHYSICS Short Answer Properly match the type of energy transfer with the following four situations described: A) mechanical work; B) matter transfer; C) electromagnetic radiation; D) mechanical waves; with 1) pushing a box across the floor; 2) listening to music; 3) seeing a bright light bulb; 4) filling a gas tank with fuel.ANSWER: A = 1 (ACCEPT: MECHANICAL WORK = PUSHING A BOX ACROSS THE FLOOR); B = 4 (ACCEPT: MATTER TRANSFER = FILLING A GAS TANK WITH FUEL);C = 3 (ACCEPT: ELECTROMAGNETIC RADIATION = SEEING A BRIGHT LIGHT BULB);D = 2 (ACCEPT: MECHANICAL WAVES = LISTENING TO MUSIC) High School Round 4 A Page 9
TOSS-UP19) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice The drug colchicine [KOL-chuh-seen] inhibits polymerization [puh-lim-er-uh-ZAY-shuhn] of tubulin in microtubule assembly. Which of the following cell processes would be most severely impacted by colchicine activity?W) DNA replicationX) Mitosis [my-TOH-sis] Y) TranslationZ) Cellular respirationANSWER: X) MITOSIS19) BIOLOGY Short Answer Name the two types of cell junctions that connect the cytoplasm[SY-tuh-plaz-uhm] of adjacent cellsANSWER: PLASMODESMATA (ACCEPT: PLASMODESMA) AND GAP JUNCTION (ACCEPT:COMMUNICATING JUNCTION)TOSS-UP20) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Alfred Wegener believed that which of the following caused the continents to move?W) Strong earthquakesX) Strong windsY) The spinning of the EarthZ) The rotation of the Earth’s magnetic fieldANSWER: Y) THE SPINNING OF THE EARTHBONUS20) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The dissolving ability of water is related to which of the following?W) The attraction between the water molecule's positive and negative charges and charges on other atomsX) Its ability to form hydrogen bonds with other moleculesY) Its ability to transmit energy from water molecule to water moleculeZ) Its low viscosityANSWER: W) THE ATTRACTION BETWEEN THE WATER MOLECULE'S POSITIVE AND NEGATIVE CHARGES AND CHARGES ON OTHER ATOMSBONUS High School Round 4 A Page 10
TOSS-UP21) MATH Multiple Choice A student must enroll in 5 classes. She must take English, either Sociology or Economics, and either Chemistry, Biology, or Geology. For the other two courses, six offerings are available. How many different schedule selections are possible?W) 36 X) 90 Y) 180 Z) 360ANSWER: X) 9021) MATH Short Answer The sides of a right triangle have lengths m, m + n, and m + 2n. If n ispositive, what is the ratio of m to n? ANSWER: 3:1 (ACCEPT: 3)TOSS-UP22) ENERGY Short Answer Some prokaryotes [proh-KAR-ee-ohts] derive energy from inorganic compounds such as sulfides, hydrogen, or ammonia. What is this type of metabolism called?ANSWER: CHEMOLITHOTROPHYBONUS22) ENERGY Short Answer Oxides of which two elements comprise most acid rain resulting from power generation?ANSWER: NITROGEN AND SULFURBONUS High School Round 4 A Page 11
TOSS-UP23) BIOLOGY Short Answer What human aneuploid [an-yoo-PLOID] syndrome is characterized by an XXY chromosome composition and sexual immaturity?ANSWER: KLINEFELTERBONUS23) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is a carnivorous [kahr-NIV-or-uhs] plant?W) MushroomX) NightshadeY) Nepenthes [ni-PEN-theez] Z) Datura [duh-TOOR-uh]ANSWER: Y) NEPENTHES TOSS-UP24) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice With regard to a graph illustrating the distribution of molecular speeds for a gas at different temperatures, which of the following occurs as temperature decreases?W) The curve flattensX) The average speed increasesY) The percentage of gas at higher speeds decreases Z) The mean free path decreasesANSWER: Y) THE PERCENTAGE OF GAS AT HIGHER SPEEDS DECREASESBONUS24) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Rank the following four gases in order of increasing effusion rates: 1) Argon, 2) Helium, 3) Oxygen, 4) Chlorine.ANSWER: 4, 1, 3, 2 (ACCEPT: CHLORINE, ARGON, OXYGEN, HELIUM)High School Round 4 A Page 12
TOSS-UP25) PHYSICS Short Answer A metal rod with coefficient of linear expansion 1.7 x 10-5 per degree Celsius and length 10.0 meters is at 20° Celsius. What is the increase in length in millimeters when it is heated to 30° Celsius?ANSWER: 1.725) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Two pipes of diameters 𝑑1 and 𝑑2 are connected. What is theratio of kinetic energy per unit volume (k1/k2) of water flowing through these pipes? W) �𝑑2�4 [open parenthesis d2 over d1 close parenthesis to the power of 4]𝑑1 2X) �𝑑2� [open parenthesis d2 over d1 close parenthesis to the power of 2]BONUS 𝑑1Y) �𝑑1�4 [open parenthesis d1 over d2 close parenthesis to the power of 4] 𝑑1Z) �𝑑2�2 [open parenthesis d1 over d2 close parenthesis to the power of 2] 𝑑2 4 ANSWER: W) �𝑑2� 𝑑1 High School Round 4 A Page 13