ROUND 13          1) MATH Short 𝑥A2nswer Let 𝑦 = 𝑒𝑥2[e to the power of x squared]. Find dy/dx.TOSS-UPANSWER: 2𝑥𝑒BONUS1) MATH Short Answer How many distinct permutations can be made from the letters in the word INFINITY?ANSWER: 3360TOSS-UP2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice What is the local VSEPR geometry of a fully substituted carbonyl carbon? W) TetrahedralX) Trigonal pyramidal Y) Trigonal planarZ) T-shapedANSWER: Y) TRIGONAL PLANARBONUS2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following analytical tools can provide information about the crystalline structure of unknown materials?W) X-ray diffractionX) X-ray photoelectron spectroscopyY) High pressure liquid chromatography Z) Dynamic light scatteringANSWER: W) X-RAY DIFFRACTIONHigh School Round 13 A Page 1
TOSS-UP3) PHYSICS Short Answer A ball is dropped from rest at a height of 60 meters above the ground. If the potential energy is zero at the ground, then at what height in meters is the potential energy 60% of its initial potential energy?ANSWER: 36BONUS3) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the minimum current in amperes a circuit breaker fuse must be able to handle in order to run a 1450 watt refrigerator hooked up to a 110 volt kitchen circuit, assuming fuses are only available in whole number increments?ANSWER: 14TOSS-UP4) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice During an El Niño event, the thermocline [THUR-muh- klyn] in the eastern equatorial Pacific is which of the following, compared to normal?W) ThickerX) ThinnerY) The sameZ) Either thicker or thinner depending on the salinityANSWER: W) THICKERBONUS4) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following scenarios made navigation difficult for early sailors and, according to legend, caused them to sacrifice their horses?W) Sailing from east to west between a subtropical high and subpolar low X) Sailing adjacent to the intertropical convergence zoneY) Sailing through the middle of a subtropical highZ) Sailing from west to east at 23.5° latitudeANSWER: Y) SAILING THROUGH THE MIDDLE OF A SUBTROPICAL HIGH High School Round 13 A Page 2
TOSS-UP5) BIOLOGY Short Answer What wasteful process occurs when rubisco acts as an oxygenase [OK-si-juh-nays] instead of a carboxylase [kahr-BOK-suh-layz] during the Calvin cycle, decreasing the efficiency of photosynthesis and producing carbon dioxide?ANSWER: PHOTORESPIRATION5) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In contrast to the lysogenic [ly-suh-JEN-ik] cycle of abacteriophage [bak-TEER-ee-uh-fayj], the lytic cycle does which of the following?W) Integrates phage DNA into the host chromosomeX) Involves the dissolution of host cells to release new phagesY) Features prophages that can be excised from the host chromosome Z) Copies phage DNA when the cell dividesANSWER: X) INVOLVES THE DISSOLUTION OF HOST CELLS TO RELEASE NEW PHAGESTOSS-UP6) ENERGY Multiple Choice The Marcellus shale gas formation is located in which of the following states?W) Pennsylvania X) TexasY) OklahomaZ) WyomingANSWER: W) PENNSYLVANIABONUS BONUS6) ENERGY Multiple Choice Compounds of bismuth telluride are used in which of the following types of devices?W) Photovoltaic devices X) Computer chipsY) Energy control devices Z) Thermoelectric devicesANSWER: Z) THERMOELECTRIC DEVICESHigh School Round 13 A Page 3
dy/dx at the point (3, 2). ANSWER: 6/31BONUSTOSS-UP7) MATH Short Answer Solve for x: ln(x + 1) - 1 = 0 [the natural log of open parenthesis x plus 1 close parenthesis minus 1 equals 0].ANSWER: e - 17) MATH Short Answer Assuming y2 + 3x2y = 7x2 – 5 implicitly defines y as a function of x, findTOSS-UP8) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice What are the products of the complete combustion of cyclohexane [sy-kluh-HEK-sayn]?W) Carbon monoxide, carbon trioxide and water X) Carbon dioxide and waterY) Carbon monoxide and waterZ) A variety of small hydrocarbonsANSWER: X) CARBON DIOXIDE AND WATERBONUS8) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following ionization techniques will produce the maximum amount of fragmentation?W) Chemical ionizationX) Fast atom bombardment Y) Plasma desorptionZ) Electron impactANSWER: Z) ELECTRON IMPACT High School Round 13 A Page 4
TOSS-UP9) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the efficiency of a Carnot heat engine in which 500 joules of heat enters from the hot reservoir and 300 joules exits into the cold reservoir?ANSWER: 40%BONUS9) PHYSICS Short Answer A typical incandescent light bulb wastes 90% of its power as heat. Ignoring the contribution of the walls and any furniture, if you left a 100 watt incandescent bulb on in a 5 by 5 by 5 meter room for 100,000 seconds, how much would the temperature of the air in the room increase, in degrees Celsius? Assume, for simplicity, that the room is a closed thermodynamic system, the heat capacity of air is 1 joule per gram per degree, and the mass density of air in the room is 1.2 kilograms per cubic meter.ANSWER: 60TOSS-UP10) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Which class of supernova exhibits strong silicon lines but no hydrogen or helium lines?ANSWER: TYPE IABONUS10) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice How does the Sound Fixing and Ranging (SOFAR) channel support our study of climate change?W) The deep SOFAR channel is populated with organisms extremely sensitive to ocean temperature changeX) World War II submarines gathered rich and extensive data sets about the SOFAR channel that can be compared with current dataY) Video monitoring of marine mammal mating behavior is useful because mating behavior in this region is impacted by temperatureZ) Speed of sound is temperature-dependent in the SOFAR channelANSWER: Z) SPEED OF SOUND IS TEMPERATURE-DEPENDENT IN THE SOFAR CHANNEL High School Round 13 A Page 5
TOSS-UP11) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following organisms stores major food reserves as laminarin and oil instead of starch?W) Green algaeX) Brown algaeY) Red algaeZ) Flowering plantsANSWER: X) BROWN ALGAEBONUS11) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following reactions is incorrectly matched to its enzyme?W) Kinase: catalyzes the removal of a phosphate group from a moleculeX) Isomerase [eye-SOM-uh-rays]: catalyzes the rearrangement of bonds within a single moleculeY) Synthase: condenses two smaller molecules togetherZ) Protease [PROH-tee-ays]: breaks down proteins by hydrolyzing bonds between amino acidsANSWER: W) KINASE: CATALYZES THE REMOVAL OF A PHOSPHATE GROUP FROM A MOLECULETOSS-UP12) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following explanations is used by scientists to justify the observed accelerating expansion of the universe? W) Dark matterX) Fast moving neutrinosY) Dark energyZ) Supernovae [soo-per-NOH-vee]ANSWER: Y) DARK ENERGYBONUS12) ENERGY Multiple Choice Power is being transmitted at 100,000 volts and the current flow is 20 amperes. What is the power loss in watts over 120 miles if the resistance of the power line is 0.5 ohms per mile?W) 6,000 X) 6,667 Y) 12,000 Z) 24,000ANSWER: Z) 24,000High School Round 13 A Page 6
TOSS-UP1−cos(𝑥)13) MATH Short Answer Given 𝑔(𝑥) = 𝑥 [g of x equals the fraction with numerator 10 of g of x]. ANSWER: 1/2BONUS13) MATH Short Answer A store has been buying a certain type of calculator at $25 and selling them at $40. At this price, they have been selling 50 calculators per month. The owner of the store wishes to increase the price of the calculator and estimates that for each $1 increase in price, 3 fewer calculators will be sold each month. Determine the price, to the nearest dollar, that maximizes profit.ANSWER: $41TOSS-UP14) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is considered a diatomic element?2minus cosine of x and denominator x squared], find lim 𝑔(𝑥) [the limit as x approaches𝑥→0  W) Sodium X) SulfurY) IodineZ) TungstenANSWER: Y) IODINE14) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following molecules does NOT have D3h symmetry?W) Phosphorus pentachloride X) CyclopropaneY) Boric acidZ) Bicyclo[2.2.2]octaneANSWER: Y) BORIC ACIDBONUSHigh School Round 13 A Page 7
TOSS-UP15) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A small rubber duck is held underwater at a depth of 10 meters, then released. When the duck reaches a depth of 5 meters, how much has the buoyant force on the duck changed?W) It has decreased by half X) It is unchangedY) It has doubledZ) It has quadrupledANSWER: X) IT IS UNCHANGEDBONUS15) PHYSICS Short Answer Charged particles in a uniform magnetic field will undergo circular motion with a period of T = 2πm/(qB). The magnetic field of the Earth is roughly 10-4 tesla, assuming it is uniform. Given the mass of a proton to be 1.6 x 10-27 kilograms and its electric charge to be 1.6 x 10-19 coulombs, providing your answer in scientific notation to one significant figure, what period in seconds would you measure for a proton?ANSWER: 6 x 10-4TOSS-UP16) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice For the mass-radius relation of white dwarfs, M is proportional to R to what power? W) -1/3 X) 1/3 Y) 1Z) 3ANSWER: W) -1/3BONUS16) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice What is the primary mode of heat transport in a white dwarf?W) Convection X) Conduction Y) Radiation Z) AdvectionANSWER: X) CONDUCTIONHigh School Round 13 A Page 8
TOSS-UP17) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following marine fish groups reproduces ovoviviparously [oh-voh-vy-vip-ER-uhs-lee]?W) Coelocanth [SEE-luh-kanth] X) RatfishY) RayZ) LampreyANSWER: W) COELOCANTHBONUS17) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the process in which a protein inhibits the function of a second protein by binding to the regulatory site of that second protein, thus altering its functionality?ANSWER: ALLOSTERIC REGULATION (ACCEPT: ALLOSTERIC INHIBITION)TOSS-UP18) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Dr. Ecniecs, the evil genius, has released multiple dangerous weather balloons into the atmosphere, filled with his new concoction - Boomgas! If the density of Boomgas drops below one third of its density at room temperature, it will explode with the force of 1/10th of an atomic bomb. Which of the following disposal methods would force the balloons to explode?W) Throwing weighted balloons into the seaX) Releasing the balloons into spaceY) Cryogenically storing the balloons in liquid nitrogen Z) Venting Boomgas from the balloonsANSWER: X) RELEASING THE BALLOONS INTO SPACEBONUS18) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Consider the following reaction: 5H2O(l)+ S2O32- + 4Cl2 (aq) → [yields] 8Cl-(aq) + 2SO42-(aq) + 10H+. What is the oxidizing agent in this reaction?W) Cl-X) S2O32- Y) Cl2Z) H2OANSWER: Y) Cl2[(L) = LIQUID; (AQ) = AQUEOUS] High School Round 13 A Page 9
TOSS-UP19) MATH Short Answer Given 𝑓(𝑥) = 𝑙𝑙√𝑒𝑥 [f of x equals the natural log of the square root of the quantity e to the x], find its first derivative with respect to x. ANSWER: 1/219) MATH Short Answer Providing y𝑥our answer in slope intercept form, what is the equation ofBONUSthe line tangent to the graph of 𝑦 = 𝑒2𝑥 [y equals the fraction with numerator e to the power 2of 2x and denominator x squared] where x = 1? ANSWER: y = e2 (ACCEPT: y = 0x + e2)  TOSS-UP20) ENERGY Multiple Choice How much energy is required to run a device with compressed air compared to running the same device with electricity?W) An equal amount X) Twice as muchY) Four times as much Z) Six times as muchANSWER: Y) FOUR TIMES AS MUCHBONUS20) ENERGY Multiple Choice Traditional solar cells have a maximum conversion efficiency of about 34% because many of the captured wavelengths result in the creation of heat, not electrons. Newly published research has shown that cell efficiencies can reach up to 44% by doing which of the following?W) Making them thinnerX) Capturing the blue wavelengthY) Using gallium arsenide instead of silicon Z) Using selenium in one of the layersANSWER: X) CAPTURING THE BLUE WAVELENGTHHigh School Round 13 A Page 10
TOSS-UP21) PHYSICS Short Answer What law describes the relationship between the direction of incident and refracted light rays?ANSWER: SNELL’S LAWBONUS21) PHYSICS Short Answer A container contains 3 moles of helium. The volume remains constant after 2 moles of gas are added and the temperature is halved. Providing your answer as a fraction, what is the ratio of the initial gas pressure to the final gas pressure?ANSWER: 6/5TOSS-UP22) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice According to the United Nations, what is the global warming potential of methane on a 100 year time scale? W) 1 X) 21 Y) 150 Z) 310ANSWER: X) 21BONUS22) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following pairs correctly matches the U.S. geographic location and its typical tidal pattern?W) West Coast – semidiurnalX) West Coast – diurnalY) Gulf of Mexico – diurnalZ) East Coast – mixed semidiurnalANSWER: Y) GULF OF MEXICO – DIURNALHigh School Round 13 A Page 11
TOSS-UP23) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In one form of the disease called macular degeneration, eyesight decreases due to overproduction of new blood vessels (angiogenesis [an-jee-oh-JEN-uh-sis]) in the eye. Inhibition of a gene involved in angiogenesis can be achieved by introducing which of the following forms of complementary RNA molecule into the eye?W) siRNAX) Messenger RNA Y) lncRNAZ) Transfer RNAANSWER: W) siRNABONUS23) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Enzyme A has a high Km value and low Vmax value relative to Enzyme B. This means Enzyme A, relative to Enzyme B has which of the following?W) Higher substrate affinity and a lower reaction rate X) Lower substrate affinity and a higher reaction rate Y) Higher substrate affinity and higher reaction rate Z) Lower substrate affinity and lower reaction rateANSWER: Z) LOWER SUBSTRATE AFFINITY AND LOWER REACTION RATETOSS-UP24) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the oxidation number of tin in SnS2? ANSWER: +4BONUS24) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What term describes the general process by which a racemate [ray-SEE-mayt] is separated into its component enantiomers [i-NAN-tee-uh-mers]?ANSWER: RESOLUTION (ACCEPT: CHEMICAL RESOLUTION) High School Round 13 A Page 12
TOSS-UP25) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice You suspect that Cylon, an alien, may be the parent of a human- alien hybrid baby. The alien’s blood type happens to be homozygous [hoh-muh-ZY-guhs] for blood type P for purple, the allele of which is symbolized by IP [eye superscript P]. As with other blood types, the P protein is co-dominant. If the human parent’s blood type is A with a homozygous genotype, what blood phenotype would the baby have to be in order to be a confirmed human-alien hybrid baby?W) O X) AP Y) P Z) AANSWER: X) AP25) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice How do bacteria protect their own genomic DNA from being cutby their restriction endonucleases [en-duh-NOO-klee-ays-is]?W) Genomic DNA of a bacterial species does not contain the recognition sequences for its own restriction endonucleasesX) Bacteria apply protective methyl groups to DNA at sites recognized by their restriction endonucleasesY) Bacteria have proteins associated with their genomic DNA, preventing the endonucleases from getting close enough to cutZ) Sequestration of chromosomal DNA in the nucleoid region of a bacterial cell protects it from being cut by restriction endonucleasesANSWER: X) BACTERIA APPLY PROTECTIVE METHYL GROUPS TO DNA AT SITES RECOGNIZED BY THEIR RESTRICTION ENDONUCLEASESBONUSHigh School Round 13 A Page 13