ROUND 2          TOSS-UP1) PHYSICS Multiple Choice If the viscous force acting on an object moving through a liquid or gas is modeled as F = -bv, where F is the resistive force, v is the velocity, and b is a constant, which of the following types of equation will need to be solved in order to determine the acceleration as a function of time?W) Transcendental X) DifferentialY) HyperbolicZ) LogarithmicANSWER: X) DIFFERENTIALBONUS1) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Two objects of masses m1 and m2 with speeds v1 and v2, where v2 = 0, suffer collision, stick together, and move off with speed V. Which of the following equals the ratio v1/V?W) 1 + m2/m1 X) 1 + m1/m2 Y) 1 - m2/m1 Z) 1 - m1/m2ANSWER: W) 1 + m2/m1 TOSS-UP2) ENERGY Short Answer Line losses vary linearly with what physical characteristic of power lines?ANSWER: RESISTANCE (ACCEPT: RESISTIVITY)BONUS2) ENERGY Short Answer Arrange the following four sectors based on the number of tons of greenhouse gases released from smallest to largest: 1) Agriculture, 2) Residential, 3) Commercial, 4) Transportation.ANSWER: 1, 2, 3, 4 (ACCEPT: AGRICULTURE, RESIDENTIAL, COMMERCIAL, TRANSPORTATION)High School Round 2 A Page 1
TOSS-UP3) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following functional group pairs corresponds to those constituting a hemiaminal?W) Thiol [THY-ol] and nitrile [NY-tril] X) Halogen and alkyl [AL-kuhl]Y) Amine [uh-MEEN] and hydroxyl Z) Azide and alkoxy [AL-kok-see]ANSWER: Y) AMINE AND HYDROXYLBONUS3) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Providing your answer as a decimal to the nearest hundredth, what is the reduced mass of an oscillator made up of a hydrogen and a fluorine atom?ANSWER: 0.95 (ACCEPT: 0.96)TOSS-UP4) BIOLOGY Short Answer What gene, sometimes called the guardian of the genome, has a central role in cell cycle checkpoints and is the most frequently mutated gene in human cancers?ANSWER: P53 (ACCEPT: TUMOR SUPPRESSOR P53, PROTEIN 53, TUMOR PROTEIN 53, TUMOR ANTIGEN P53, TRP53, TRANSFORMATION RELATED PROTEIN 53)BONUS4) BIOLOGY Short Answer Amino acids are joined to one another in linear polymers that fold to form proteins. What is the name of the chemical bond that joins the amino terminus of one amino acid to the carboxyl terminus of the next amino acid in the sequence?ANSWER: PEPTIDE BOND (ACCEPT: PEPTIDE, AMINE BOND) High School Round 2 A Page 2
TOSS-UP 2 5) MATH Sh2ort Answer What is the derivative with respect to x of xe[x times e squared]?ANSWER: e5) MATH Short Answer Solve for x: 2x+1 = 4x+3[2 raised to the quantity x+1 equals 4 raised tothe quantity x+3]. ANSWER: -5TOSS-UP6) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Moving away from the ridges, oceanic crust becomes which of the following?W) Hotter and younger X) Hotter and olderY) Cooler and olderZ) Cooler and youngerANSWER: Y) COOLER AND OLDERBONUS BONUS6) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the name for the great circle that passes through the northernmost point on the horizon and the zenith?ANSWER: MERIDIANHigh School Round 2 A Page 3
TOSS-UP7) PHYSICS Multiple Choice You are at a party where the sound level is 70 decibels. Someone turns up the radio and the sound level suddenly increases to 100 decibels. By what factor has the sound intensity been multiplied?W) 30X) 100Y) 1000 Z) 10,000ANSWER: Y) 1000BONUS7) PHYSICS Short Answer After running for 20 minutes, a person’s diastolic blood pressure is 100 millimeters of mercury. Providing your answer to two significant figures, what is the equivalent height in centimeters of a column of water, assuming the mass density of mercury is 13.6 grams per cubic centimeter and the mass density of water is 1.0 grams per cubic centimeter?ANSWER: 140TOSS-UP8) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true when writing electron configurations?W) Atomic orbitals can accommodate two electronsX) Electrons pair in degenerate orbitals when possibleY) Electrons will populate orbitals to maximize spinZ) Noble gas cores are often used to truncate longer configurationsANSWER: X) ELECTRONS PAIR IN DEGENERATE ORBITALS WHEN POSSIBLEBONUS8) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Which quantum number is allowed values ranging from 0 to n -1 and is associated with atomic orbital shape?ANSWER: ANGULAR MOMENTUM QUANTUM NUMBER (ACCEPT: l, AZIMUTHAL, SUBSIDIARY) High School Round 2 A Page 4
TOSS-UP9) BIOLOGY Short Answer In eukaryotes [yoo-KAR-ee-ohts], the spliceosome [SPLY-see-uh- sohm] is an RNA-protein complex important for RNA processing. What does this complex remove?ANSWER: INTRONSBONUS9) BIOLOGY Short Answer In the standard genetic code, how many of the 64 codons signal for stop of translation?ANSWER: 310) MATH Multiple Choice If the line y = 2 is reflected over the y-axis, what is the equation of the image?ANSWER: Z) y = 210) MATH Short Answer What is ∫2 |𝑥| 𝑑𝑥 [the integral from negative 2 to 2 of the absolute W) x = -2 X) y = -2 Y) x= 2 Z) y = 2value of x dx]? −2 ANSWER: 4TOSS-UPBONUSHigh School Round 2 A Page 5
TOSS-UP11) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the term for the wind-driven transport process that causes sand particles to skip or bounce for short distances?ANSWER: SALTATIONBONUS11) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the second hottest spectral class? ANSWER: BTOSS-UP12) PHYSICS Multiple Choice What is the main difference between transverse and longitudinal waves?W) WavelengthX) FrequencyY) Direction of the medium displacement with respect to the direction of wave propagation Z) Phase differenceANSWER: Y) DIRECTION OF THE MEDIUM DISPLACEMENT WITH RESPECT TO THE DIRECTION OF WAVE PROPAGATIONBONUS12) PHYSICS Multiple Choice What is the wavelength in nanometers of a photon of period 3.33 × 10-18 seconds?W) 1 X) 3 Y) 6 Z) 9ANSWER: W) 1 High School Round 2 A Page 6
TOSS-UP13) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following equations best represents the conservation of energy in fluid systems?W) LaplaceX) BernoulliY) Navier-Stokes Z) EulerANSWER: X) BERNOULLIW) 320 X) 400 Y) 450 Z) 500ANSWER: Z) 500BONUS13) ENERGY Multiple Choice How many BTUs are required to raise 5 pounds of water from 40° Fahrenheit to 120° Fahrenheit with a stove that is 80% efficient? TOSS-UP14) CHEMISTRY Short Answer When a peptide bond is formed between two amino acids, water is removed as a byproduct. Which group contributes the OH to form water, and which group contributes the hydrogen?ANSWER: CONTRIBUTES OH = CARBOXYL GROUP (ACCEPT: CARBOXYL, COOH, OR COOH GROUP); CONTRIBUTES HYDROGEN = AMINO GROUP (ACCEPT: AMINO, NH2, OR NH2 GROUP)BONUS14) CHEMISTRY Short Answer In the Haber reaction, where diatomic hydrogen and diatomic nitrogen react to form ammonia, how many moles of ammonia could be formed if one starts with 0.75 moles of hydrogen?ANSWER: 0.50High School Round 2 A Page 7
TOSS-UP15) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the only infectious human disease to be declared completely eradicated from nature?ANSWER: SMALLPOXBONUS15) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following cellular phenomena uses double-stranded RNA with the same or similar sequence to a gene to target that gene for inhibition of transcription and translation?W) RNA interference X) TranspositionY) RNA editingZ) Alternative splicingANSWER: W) RNA INTERFERENCE TOSS-UP16) MATH Short Answer What are the coordinates of the point where the graph ofx2y + 3x – 4y – 24 = 0 [x squared y plus 3 x minus 4 y minus 24 equals zero] crosses the x- axis?ANSWER: (8, 0) (DO NOT ACCEPT: 8 ALONE, X = 8)BONUS16) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following represents a simplification of: (𝐴12 + 𝐴12)2 [open parenthesis a to the power of one half plus a to the power of one half close parenthesis squared]?  W) A2 X) 4A Y) 2A Z) √𝐴 ANSWER: X) 4AHigh School Round 2 A Page 8
TOSS-UP17) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Based on current scientific data, the most widely accepted cause of past ice ages is which of the following?W) Volcanic aerosols in the atmosphere from major eruptionsX) Increased absorption of carbon dioxide by the oceans and land masses Y) A decrease in solar intensity such as during the Maunder MinimumZ) Milankovitch cyclesANSWER: Z) MILANKOVITCH CYCLESBONUS17) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Some quasars exhibit multiple images. What phenomenon explains this observation?W) Structure doubling X) Faraday rotationY) WormholesZ) Gravitational lensingANSWER: Z) GRAVITATIONAL LENSINGTOSS-UP18) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice G-protein coupled receptors regulate various cell signaling events in a cell. How many transmembrane segments are typically found in these receptors? W) 5 X) 6 Y) 7 Z) 9ANSWER: Y) 7BONUS18) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice An ecologist uses seven foot tall mist nets to capture birds. In which of these habitats would the number of captures most likely underestimate the actual number of birds present?W) TundraX) Temperate grassland Y) ChaparralZ) Temperate forestANSWER: Z) TEMPERATE FORESTHigh School Round 2 A Page 9
TOSS-UP19) PHYSICS Multiple Choice The number of lines per centimeter in a transmission grating is 10,000. What is the distance in meters between the lines of the grating?W) 10-3 X) 10-4 Y) 10-5 Z) 10-6ANSWER: Z) 10-6BONUS19) PHYSICS Short Answer A proton is travelling with a speed of 300,000 meters per second to the east in a region where there is a magnetic field of 4 teslas pointing to the north. What is the magnitude and direction of the electric field in newtons per coulomb that must be present if the proton is to move through this region undeflected?ANSWER: 1,200,000, DOWNTOSS-UP20) ENERGY Short Answer In CFL light bulbs, what is the name for the process where electricity excites mercury vapor and light is released?ANSWER: FLUORESCENCEBONUS20) ENERGY Multiple Choice When photons strike a photovoltaic cell, which of the following must occur to generate electricity?W) Absorption X) Reflection Y) Refraction Z) ResectionANSWER: W) ABSORPTION High School Round 2 A Page 10
TOSS-UP21) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice With regard to crystalline solids, which of the following most aptly describes a covalent network?W) Low melting point, soft, excellent thermal conductorX) Low to high melting point, hard, moderate electrical conductor Y) High melting point, soft, poor electrical conductorZ) High melting point, hard, poor thermal conductorANSWER: Z) HIGH MELTING POINT, HARD, POOR THERMAL CONDUCTORBONUS21) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Identify, respectively, the isotopes created by the emission of one beta minus particle from the following three isotopes: 1) cesium-137, 2) phosphorus-32, 3) carbon-14.ANSWER: 1) BARIUM-137, 2) SULFUR-32, 3) NITROGEN-14TOSS-UP22) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following bacterial gene transfer mechanisms requires the involvement of a bacteriophage [bak-TEER-ee-uh-fayj]? W) ConjugationX) TransductionY) Horizontal gene transfer Z) Bacterial transformationANSWER: X) TRANSDUCTIONBONUS22) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Plasmids are autonomously replicating circles of DNA containing one or a few genes. How many plasmids may a single bacterium carry?W) 0X) 1Y) 2Z) No fixed limitANSWER: Z) NO FIXED LIMITHigh School Round 2 A Page 11
23) MATH Short Answer Find the magnitude of the vector 5i – 12j. ANSWER: 13BONUStotheequationkx +7x–5=0. 9 ANSWER: k = -49/20 (ACCEPT: -2 20 OR -2.45)TOSS-UP23) MATH Short Answer Find the nonzero value of k that will result in exactly one real solution 2  TOSS-UP24) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a feature produced by wave erosion?W) Sea cave X) Sea stack Y) Sea arch Z) ShoalANSWER: Z) SHOALBONUS24) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice While most scientists believe global warming will cause soils of northern latitudes to emit more carbon dioxide, one recent study predicted they would sequester more carbon in the future. Which of the following mechanisms could explain this?W) Warmer temperatures accelerate soil respirationX) Warmer temperatures promote vegetation growth, which fixes more carbonY) Warmer temperatures dry out soilsZ) Warmer temperatures cause vegetation to grow and die faster, which puts more carbon into the soil and accelerates soil respirationANSWER: X) WARMER TEMPERATURES PROMOTE VEGETATION GROWTH, WHICH FIXES MORE CARBONHigh School Round 2 A Page 12
TOSS-UP25) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A top is spinning at a rate of 2π radians per second when it slows uniformly to a stop in 15 seconds. Through how many revolutions did the top turn before stopping?W) 7.5 X) 7.5π Y) 15 Z) 15πANSWER: W) 7.5BONUS25) PHYSICS Short Answer A 100 microfarad parallel plate capacitor with air between the plates is connected to a 1.5 volt battery and becomes fully charged. The battery is disconnected from the capacitor and a dielectric with a dielectric constant of 7 is inserted between the plates. What is the charge in microcoulombs on one plate of the capacitor after the dielectric is inserted?ANSWER: 150High School Round 2 A Page 13