ROUND 1 TOSS-UP1) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What organelle functions to isolate a human cell’s chromosomes from the cytoplasm?ANSWER: NUCLEUSBONUS1) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the primary oxygen-carrying protein found in red blood cells?ANSWER: HEMOGLOBINTOSS-UP2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What physical state of matter is intermediate between a solid and gas?ANSWER: LIQUIDBONUS2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following BEST describes the term static:W) stationary X) lowY) constant Z) usedANSWER: W) STATIONARY Middle School Round 1Page 1TOSS-UP3) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the general name for the rising and falling of sea levels in response to the forces exerted by the Moon and Sun?ANSWER: TIDESBONUS3) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Approximately what fraction of Earth’s surface is covered by oceans:W) one-halfX) two-thirds Y) seven-tenths Z) four-fifthsANSWER: Y) SEVEN-TENTHS 4) MATH Short Answer How many degrees are in one-third of a right angle? ANSWER: 30BONUS4) MATH Short Answer Round the number 535,279 to the nearest ten-thousand: ANSWER: 540,000TOSS-UPMiddle School Round 1Page 2TOSS-UP5) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer The number 4.56 × 1011 has how many zeroes? ANSWER: 9BONUS5) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Giving your answer in grams, subtract 200 grams from 6.2 kilograms:ANSWER: 6,000 (ACCEPT: 6 × 10^3)TOSS-UP6) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer How many permanent teeth does a typical adult human have? ANSWER: 32BONUS6) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer How many canine teeth does the typical human adult have? ANSWER: 4TOSS-UP7) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Mary tried to lift her couch by exerting 500 newtons of force but it doesn’t budge. If the couch weighed 2,000 newtons, how much work did she do:W) 0X) 50 watts Y) 500 joules Z) 2000 joulesANSWER: W) 0BONUS7) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Jeff walks west in a straight path for 100 meters and then east in a straight path for 150 meters. What is the magnitude of his displacement, in meters?ANSWER: 50TOSS-UP8) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The hydrologic cycle describes the circulation of Earth’s: W) tidesX) waterY) sediments Z) rocksANSWER: X) WATERBONUS8) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the rock that makes up most of the ocean floor and volcanic ocean islands?ANSWER: BASALTMiddle School Round 1 Page 4TOSS-UP9) MATH Short Answer In a right triangle, what is the name for the side opposite the 90o angle? ANSWER: HYPOTENUSEBONUS9) MATH Short Answer Rounded to the nearest meter, find the length of the hypotenuse of a right triangle if the legs measure 5 and 12 meters?ANSWER: 13(Solution: 52 + 122 = c2; c = 13) 10) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the SI base unit for length? ANSWER: METERBONUS10) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 3 choices that are measurements units for speed: mach; newton; knotsANSWER: MACH; KNOTSTOSS-UPMiddle School Round 1Page 5TOSS-UP11) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Most of the heart is composed of which of the following types of tissues:W) epithelial X) connective Y) nervous Z) muscleANSWER: Z) MUSCLEBONUS11) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer In the taxonomical name Homo sapiens, what taxonomical rank does sapiens represent?ANSWER: SPECIESTOSS-UP12) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What atomic particle balances the charge of protons to produce a neutral atom?ANSWER: ELECTRONBONUS12) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Isotopes of the same element are based on their different numbers of what atomic particle?ANSWER: NEUTRONS Middle School Round 1 Page 6TOSS-UP13) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Which of the Gas giant planets is closest to the Sun? ANSWER: JUPITERBONUS13) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What are the 2 main factors causing the metamorphism of rocks?ANSWER: HEAT AND PRESSURE (in any order)TOSS-UP14) MATH Short Answer What is the name for any segment with one endpoint at the center of a circle and the other endpoint on the circle?ANSWER: RADIUS (ACCEPT: RADII)BONUS14) MATH Short Answer Rounded to the nearest ten-thousandth, convert 1 rd to a decimal: 3ANSWER: 0.3333 (ACCEPT: .3333)  Middle School Round 1 Page 7TOSS-UP15) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer If there are 640 ounces of water in 5 gallons, how many ounces are in 1⁄2 gallon?ANSWER: 64BONUS15) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 choices that are measurement units of area: meter; hectare; acre; mileANSWER: HECTARE; ACRETOSS-UP16) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is generally considered the basic unit of life? ANSWER: THE CELLBONUS16) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer In what organelle of a plant cell does photosynthesis occur? ANSWER: CHLOROPLAST (ACCEPT: PLASTID) Middle School Round 1 Page 8TOSS-UP17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer An ionic state of an atom of hydrogen would have how many protons?ANSWER: 1BONUS17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the biochemical process that converts grape juice into wine or soy beans into soy sauce?ANSWER: FERMENTATIONTOSS-UP18) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Giving your answer as north, south, east, or west, a southerly wind blows FROM what direction? ANSWER: SOUTH18) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following clouds has little vertical development:W) altostratus X) altocumulus Y) cirrusZ) nimbostratusANSWER: Y) CIRRUSBONUSMiddle School Round 1Page 9TOSS-UP19) MATH Short Answer What is the exact circumference, in centimeters, of a circle whose radius is 3 centimeters?ANSWER: 6πBONUS19) MATH Short Answer Change each of the following 3 fractions, respectively, to equivalent fractions with a denominator of 30: 13 ; 53 ; 56ANSWER: 10 ; 18 ; 25 30 30 30TOSS-UP20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the common name for the antiseptic, found in many homes, that decomposes into water and oxygen?ANSWER: HYDROGEN PEROXIDEBONUS20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the chemical formula for hydrogen peroxide? ANSWER: H2O2       Middle School Round 1 Page 10TOSS-UP21) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the scientific name for the white of a cooked egg? ANSWER: ALBUMENBONUS21) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What term is generally used for biological catalysts? ANSWER: ENZYMESTOSS-UP22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What term do scientists use for the force of gravity acting on anything that has mass?ANSWER: WEIGHTBONUS22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer How many protons are present in a single helium nucleus?ANSWER: 2 Middle School Round 1 Page 11TOSS-UP23) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice A weather forecast of 100% relative humidity suggests an increased possibility of:W) rainX) windY) rising temperature Z) drying conditionsANSWER: W) RAINBONUS23) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for all Great Circles that pass through the north and south poles?ANSWER: LONGITUDES (ACCEPT: MERIDIANS)TOSS-UP24) MATH Short Answer Every triangle has how many vertices? ANSWER: 3BONUS24) MATH Short Answer If the perimeter of a triangle is 45 centimeters and the lengths of two of its sides are 16 and 12 centimeters, find the length of the third side, in centimeters:ANSWER: 17 Middle School Round 1 Page 12TOSS-UP25) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What general term describes the angle or degree north or south of the equator?ANSWER: LATITUDE25) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer The geographic north pole is at what latitude? ANSWER: 90 (ACCEPT: 90o NORTH)BONUSMiddle School Round 1Page 13