ROUND 8 TOSS-UP1) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT generally characteristic of oceanic-continental plate boundaries:W) high mountain systems X) wide continental shelves Y) ocean trenchesZ) earthquake prone areasANSWER: X) WIDE CONTINENTAL SHELVESBONUS1) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of an island arc collision zone:W) JapanX) OregonY) MaineZ) Chile and PeruANSWER: W) JAPAN TOSS-UP2) MATH Short Answer In what quadrant of the coordinate system are both x and y negative? ANSWER: 3 (ACCEPT: III or THIRD)BONUS2) MATH Short Answer Bottled water is selling for 60-cents per bottle. If you buy a dozen bottles and hand the cashier a ten-dollar bill, how much change are your owed, in dollars and cents?ANSWER: $2.80Middle School Round 8 Page 1
TOSS-UP3) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is CLOSEST to the volume of 4 liters in quarts:W) 3.8 X) 4.0 Y) 4.2 Z) 4.4ANSWER: Y) 4.2(Solution: 1 L = 1.06 q; 4 L = 4.24 q)BONUS3) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Arrange the following 3 choices in order of INCREASING mass: largest moon of Saturn; Brown dwarf star; EarthANSWER: LARGEST MOON OF SATURN; EARTH; BROWN DWARF STARTOSS-UP4) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following terms do biologists most often use to describe animals that do not move by their own design or effort: W) saprophytic X) instarY) motileZ) sessileANSWER: Z) SESSILEBONUS4) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the base nucleotide to which adenine binds on its opposing strand in DNA?ANSWER: THYMINEMiddle School Round 8 Page 2
TOSS-UP5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Light typically travels in waves that are oriented in all planes traveling in a given direction. What is the term for light waves that are traveling in one plane?ANSWER: POLARIZED (ACCEPT: LINEAR POLARIZED)BONUS5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 choices that are electromagnetic radiation: radio waves; x-rays; cathode rays; visible lightANSWER: ALLTOSS-UP6) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Name all the planets that appear to have phases like our Moon to Earthbound observers?ANSWER: MERCURY; VENUSBONUS6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The greatest annual variation in the intensity of solar radiation on Earth throughout the year is in which of the following locations:W) tropicsX) north of the Arctic CircleY) south of the Antarctic Circle Z) temperate, middle latitude zoneANSWER: Z) TEMPERATE, MIDDLE LATITUDE ZONE Middle SchoolRound 8Page 3
TOSS-UP7) MATH Multiple Choice Pick any arbitrary point in the interior of a circle 12-inches in diameter and cut the circle into 8 slices by cutting at 45o angles through that arbitrary point. If you color alternate pieces blue and yellow, then the total area of the blue slices will:W) equal the area of the yellow slicesX) be twice the area of the yellow slicesY) be one-half the area of the yellow slices Z) be one-third the area of the yellow slicesANSWER: W) EQUAL THE AREA OF THE YELLOW SLICESBONUS7) MATH Short Answer Consider the four angles formed by two intersecting lines. If one angle measures 50o, find the measure of the remaining three angles, in degrees:ANSWER: 50; 130; 130TOSS-UP8) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a property of diamonds:W) extremely hardX) transparentY) poor thermal conductor Z) good electrical insulatorANSWER: Y) POOR THERMAL CONDUCTORBONUS8) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Give the Roman numeral equivalent of 2009: ANSWER: MMIX (DO NOT ACCEPT: MMVIIII) Middle School Round 8 Page 4
TOSS-UP9) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What anatomical structure in boney fish allows them to adjust their buoyancy and stay afloat without swimming?ANSWER: SWIMBLADDER (ACCEPT: AIR BLADDER or GAS BLADDER)BONUS9) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common name for the fluid in a spider that serves a similar function to blood in vertebrates?ANSWER: HAEMOLYMPH (ACCEPT: HEMOLYMPH)TOSS-UP10) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which of the following units would capacitance most likely be given: W) webers X) farads Y) teslas Z) ohmsANSWER: X) FARADSBONUS10) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 3 choices that are DC voltage sources: 9-volt battery; lightning; static electricityANSWER: ALLMiddle School Round 8 Page 5
TOSS-UP11) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes how volcanic glass or obsidian is formed:W) magma cools rapidly and crystals do not formX) magma cools slowly and 1 large crystal is formed Y) magma cools in direct contact with waterZ) magma is heated, cooled, then reheatedANSWER: W) MAGMA COOLS RAPIDLY AND CRYSTALS DO NOT FORMBONUS11) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The dominant component of most magma is:W) carbonX) sulfur dioxide Y) silicon dioxide Z) nitrogenANSWER: Y) SILICON DIOXIDE TOSS-UP12) MATH Short Answer Any number, except zero, to the zero power equals what? ANSWER: 1BONUS12) MATH Short Answer Give the numerical value of 20 factorial divided by 18 factorial: ANSWER: 380Middle School Round 8 Page 6
TOSS-UP13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer From what element are most semiconductors primarily composed?ANSWER: SILICONBONUS13) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is CLOSEST to 56 miles per hour in kilometers per hour:W) 20 X) 50 Y) 90 Z) 120ANSWER: Y) 90 TOSS-UP14) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What organelle with attached ribosomes is most directly responsible for the translation of proteins destined to be transported out of the cell?ANSWER: ENDOPLASMIC RETICULUM(ACCEPT: ER or RER or ROUGH ER or ROUGH ENDOPLASMIC RETICULUM)(DO NOT ACCEPT: SER or SMOOTH ER or SMOOTH ENDOPLASMIC RETICULUM)BONUS14) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 functional groups that are found in all amino acids: carboxyl; ketone; amino; phosphateANSWER: CARBOXYL; AMINOMiddle School Round 8 Page 7
TOSS-UP15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the resultant force when a force of 50 newtons is opposed in an opposite direction by a 10-newton force?ANSWER: 40BONUS15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A dog-sled team runs at 15 kilometers per hour for 6 hours and gets stuck in a partially melted lake for 3 hours, where it make no progress. It then runs at 10 kilometers per hour for another 5 hours and crosses the finish line. What is the dog sled team’s average speed for the entire race, in kilometers per hour?ANSWER: 10(Solution: (6 × 15 = 90) + (5 × 10 = 50) = 140; 140/14 = 10 km/hr)TOSS-UP16) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Banded iron formations that are present in mountain ranges around the world formed during the Achaean Era as a direct result of the presence of: W) nitrogen X) oxygen Y) hydrogen Z) methaneANSWER: X) OXYGEN16) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a carbonate mineral:W) halite X) fluorite Y) feldspar Z) dolomiteANSWER: Z) DOLOMITEBONUSMiddle SchoolRound 8Page 8
TOSS-UP17) MATH Short Answer How many terms are in the following variable expression and what is the coefficient of the second term: 5x2 – x – 12yz2 + 9ANSWER: TERMS = 4; COEFFICIENT = –1BONUS17) MATH Short Answer Sue and Sierra are making necklaces. If Sue makes an average of 3 every 30 minutes and Sierra averages 6 every hour, how many necklaces do they average every hour if they work together?ANSWER: 12(Solution: 3/0.5 + 6/1 = 12)TOSS-UP18) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What specific cell in your body becomes sickle-shaped if you are afflicted with sickle cell anemia?ANSWER: RED BLOOD CELL (ACCEPT: RBC or ERYTHROCYTE or RED CORPUSCLE)BONUS18) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 laboratory tools that would require a user to read a meniscus: graduated pipet; pH paper; watch glass; Buchner funnelANSWER: GRADUATED PIPET Middle School Round 8 Page 9
TOSS-UP19) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common name of the plant pigments that give fruits and many plant parts their orange color?ANSWER: CAROTENOIDSBONUS19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following organisms has an archegonium:W) moss X) birdY) frogZ) oak treeANSWER: W) MOSS TOSS-UP20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most commonly used scientific name for the compound with the chemical formula C6H12O6, which is a product of photosynthesis?ANSWER: GLUCOSE (ACCEPT: D-GLUCOSE or DEXTROSE)BONUS20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Arrange the following 4 substances in order of DECREASING pH: normal human saliva; black coffee; bleach; stomach acidANSWER: BLEACH; NORMAL HUMAN SALIVA; BLACK COFFEE; STOMACH ACID (Solution: bleach = 13; saliva = 6.5-7.4; coffee = 5; stomach acid = 2)Middle School Round 8 Page 10
TOSS-UP21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Stratovolcanoes are typically found in which of the following locations:W) continents and volcanic arcs X) the abyssal plainY) along basaltic plateausZ) above hot spots in Earth’s crustANSWER: W) CONTINENTS AND VOLCANIC ARCSBONUS21) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of the troposphere:W) the air is much dryer above the troposphereX) the troposphere is 78% nitrogen gas and 21% oxygen gasY) the troposphere extends from the Earth’s surface up to an average of 27 miles Z) the troposphere ends where temperature no longer varies with heightANSWER: Y) THE TROPOSPHERE EXTENDS FROM THE EARTH’S SURFACE UP TO AN AVERAGE OF 27 MILESTOSS-UP22) MATH Short Answer For the equation y = mx + b, b represents what value?ANSWER: Y-INTERCEPT (ACCEPT: WHERE THE LINE CROSSES THE Y OR ORDINATEAXIS)BONUS22) MATH Short Answer Find a number such that 10-times the number reduced by 3 equals 4- times the number increased by 15:ANSWER: 3(Solution: 10x – 3 = 4x + 15) Middle School Round 8 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer From what constellation do the Geminids meteor shower appear to originate?ANSWER: GEMINIBONUS23) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following astronomers devised a system of the orbits for the planets that is considered heliocentric and published in his book “On the Revolutions of the Heavenly Spheres”:W) GalileoX) Copernicus Y) NewtonZ) KeplerANSWER: X) COPERNICUS TOSS-UP24) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer How many pairs of wings do beetles typically have? ANSWER: 2BONUS24) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer How many cervical vertebrae are found in most mammals? ANSWER: 7Middle School Round 8 Page 12
TOSS-UP25) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer How many wavelengths per second are equal to 5 kilohertz?ANSWER: 5,000BONUS25) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the percent efficiency for a lever that has a work input of 2,000 joules and a work output of 1,600 joules?ANSWER: 80(Solution: %efficiency = Work out/ Work in × 1001600/2000 × 100 = 80%)Middle School Round 8 Page 13