ROUND 9 TOSS-UP1) MATH Short Answer Find the product of 23 × 32: ANSWER: 72BONUS1) MATH Short Answer Arrange the following 4 choices in INCREASING order: 2001; 53; 35; 202ANSWER: 53; 2001; 35; 202TOSS-UP2) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A blimp or airship that uses helium as its lifting gas primarily controls its buoyancy by doing which of the following:W) adding or removing small amounts of hydrogen gas because it is lighter than helium X) heating or cooling the helium gas within the outside bladder of the blimpY) intaking or venting airZ) producing or destroying helium gasANSWER: Y) INTAKING OR VENTING AIRBONUS2) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Arrange the following 4 choices from the one with the LOWEST mass to the HIGHEST mass: virus; mouse spleen; mosquito; water moleculeANSWER: WATER MOLECULE; VIRUS; MOSQUITO; MOUSE SPLEEN Middle School Round 9 Page 1
TOSS-UP3) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common name for the junctions across which nerve cells carry chemical messages from cell to cell?ANSWER: SYNAPSEBONUS3) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common name of the part of a neuron that takes its name from the Greek word for tree, and functions to carry electrical messages from other nerve cells to the soma?ANSWER: DENDRITETOSS-UP4) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A fifty-fifty solution of distilled water and pure ethanol will appear: W) clearX) cloudyY) purpleZ) heterogeneousANSWER: W) CLEARBONUS4) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following chemical names is NOT correctly matched with its chemical formula:W) H2SO4 and sulfuric acid X) HCl and hydrochloric acid Y) BeCl2 and boron dichloride Z) SO2 and sulfur dioxideANSWER: Y) BeCL2 AND BORON DICHLORIDEMiddle SchoolRound 9Page 2
TOSS-UP5) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a feature made by a continental glacier and NOT made by an alpine glacier:W) cirqueX) hanging valley Y) truncated spur Z) drumlinANSWER: Z) DRUMLINBONUS5) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What type of moraine forms along the valley walls of an alpine glacier?ANSWER: LATERAL (DO NOT ACCEPT ANY OTHER MORAINE TYPE)TOSS-UP6) MATH Short Answer Evaluate | –x | (read as: the absolute value of negative x) for x = –5:ANSWER: 5BONUS6) MATH Short Answer Maxine buys a stock for $100.00 and then sells it for $75.00. She repurchases the stock for $125.00, and 3 months later sells it for $200.00. What was her profit, in dollars?ANSWER: 50(Solution: –100 + 75 – 125 + 200 = $50.00) Middle School Round 9 Page 3
TOSS-UP7) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the physical state of a saturated fat and a polyunsaturated fat, respectively, at room temperature, if both have 18 carbons per molecule?ANSWER: SATURATED FAT = SOLID; UNSATURATED FAT = LIQUIDBONUS7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is closest to the maximum running speed of a human:W) 0.3 meters per second X) 30 meters per second Y) 18 kilometers per hour Z) 38 kilometers per hourANSWER: Z) 38 KILOMETERS PER HOURTOSS-UP8) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which of the following cells would myelin most likely be found: W) oocyteX) red blood cell Y) neuronZ) skin cellANSWER: Y) NEURONBONUS8) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 choices of eukaryotic sub-cellular structures that do NOT have their own specific membrane: chloroplast; lysosome; centriole; golgiANSWER: CENTRIOLEMiddle School Round 9 Page 4
TOSS-UP9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer How many times as much momentum does a truck have traveling at 40 kilometers per hour if it triples its mass?ANSWER: 3BONUS9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 substances that will turn blue litmus paper red: citric acid; carbonated water; ammonia; sodium hydroxideANSWER: CITRIC ACID; CARBONATED WATERTOSS-UP10) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The hard coral of coral reefs are primarily made of:W) basaltX) calcium carbonate Y) silicatesZ) haliteANSWER: X) CALCIUM CARBONATEBONUS10) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice According to the Rock Cycle, once conglomerate sedimentary rocks are formed, the most direct pathway in the formation of sediments is by which of the following:W) weathering and erosionX) compaction and cementation Y) cooling and crystallization Z) heat and pressureANSWER: W) WEATHERING AND EROSION Middle SchoolRound 9Page 5
TOSS-UP11) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:W) a line that intersects 2 other lines at different points is called a transversalX) if a ≤ 0 (read as: if a is less than or equal to 0), then the absolute value of a equals a Y) the square of an integer is called a perfect squareZ) the real numbers include all rational and irrational numbersANSWER: X) IF A ≤ 0 THEN THE ABSOLUTE VALUE OF A EQUALS A BONUS11) MATH Short Answer A college student has a budget of $600.00 per month. If at the end of a given month she spent $350.00 and earned an extra $150.00 in wages, how much is left in the budget at month’s end?ANSWER: $400.00TOSS-UP12) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What fossil fuel is the greatest fuel source for electricity generation in the world?ANSWER: COALBONUS12) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer The acidity of a water sample with a pH of 5 is how many times as great as that of a sample with a pH of 6?ANSWER: 10 Middle School Round 9 Page 6
TOSS-UP13) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the most important function of fiber tracheids (read as: TRAY-key-ids) in woody plants:W) energy storageX) structural supportY) sugary sap movementZ) absorption of nutrients from the soilANSWER: X) STRUCTURAL SUPPORTBONUS13) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the smallest object that a typical student compound light microscope is able to allow a person to see:W) mRNA X) ribosomes Y) E.coliZ) polio virusANSWER: Y) E.COLI TOSS-UP14) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer According to Charles’s gas law, the volume of a fixed amount of gas varies directly with what property?ANSWER: TEMPERATUREBONUS14) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following processes is exothermic:W) solid water changes to water vapor X) solid water changes to liquid water Y) liquid water changes to solid water Z) liquid water changes to water vaporANSWER: Y) LIQUID WATER CHANGES TO SOLID WATER (Solution: freezing is exothermic)Middle SchoolRound 9Page 7
TOSS-UP15) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice An igneous rock in which individual mineral grains or crystals are visible to the naked eye most likely was formed by which of the following processes:W) rapid cooling X) slow cooling Y) quenchingZ) metamorphosisANSWER: X) SLOW COOLINGBONUS15) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What type of boundary exists where plates are neither produced nor destroyed, an example of which is the San Andreas fault?ANSWER: TRANSFORM FAULT BOUNDARY (ACCEPT: TRANSFORM MARGIN or TRANSFORM )TOSS-UP16) MATH Short Answer By words or number, name all of the following 3 statements which are always TRUE:1) the smaller angle formed by the hands of a clock at 2 o’clock is acute 2) two non-vertical parallel lines have the same slope3) an altitude of an equilateral triangle forms two, 45o, 45o, 90o trianglesANSWER: 1 AND 2BONUS16) MATH Short Answer If a staple-gun misfires 5 times for every 200 shots, how many times will it be expected to misfire in 4,000 shots?ANSWER: 100 Middle School Round 9 Page 8
TOSS-UP17) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer If a star has a mass of 10 solar masses, how many times as much mass does it have as the Sun?ANSWER: 10BONUS17) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The majority of stars in the universe are thought to have surface temperatures of:W) about 20,000 K X) about 10,000 K Y) about 6,000 K Z) less than 3,500 KANSWER: Z) LESS THAN 3,500 K 18) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Adipose tissue stores mostly:W) lipidX) protein Y) starch Z) glycogenANSWER: W) LIPIDTOSS-UPBONUS18) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following biological molecules make up the main part of the bilayer and hydrophobic region of the plasma cell membrane:W) oligosaccharides (read as: oh-LEE-go-SACK-ah-rides) X) carbohydratesY) phospholipidsZ) proteinsANSWER: Y) PHOSPHOLIPIDSMiddle SchoolRound 9Page 9
TOSS-UP19) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Giving your answer in scientific notation to the second decimal place, how many molecules are in 10 moles of H2O?ANSWER: 6.02 × 1024(Solution: (10 mol H2O)(6.023 × 1023 molecules/mole) = 6.023 × 1024 molecules)BONUS19) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Using proper chemical formulas, finish balancing the following equation: N2 + 3H2  what?ANSWER: 2NH3TOSS-UP20) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following forms of winter precipitation is most likely to cause downed power lines and broken tree limbs: W) freezing rain X) sleetY) snowZ) hailANSWER: W) FREEZING RAINBONUS20) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT one of the 10 major cloud types:W) cirrusX) cirrocumulus Y) cirrostratus Z) cirronimbusANSWER: Z) CIRRONIMBUSMiddle SchoolRound 9Page 10
TOSS-UP21) MATH Short Answer Solve the following inequality for x: 3(x + 1) ≥ 9 ANSWER: x ≥ 2BONUS21) MATH Short Answer Evaluate the following complex fraction, giving your answer as an improper fraction in lowest terms: 2 − 17 1 − 12 ANSWER: 26   7TOSS-UP22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the time zone immediately east of the Eastern Time Zone?ANSWER: ATLANTIC TIME ZONE (ACCEPT: ATLANTIC)BONUS22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Ignoring boundary adjustments, most individual time zones are how many degrees of longitude apart?ANSWER: 15 Middle School Round 9 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Keratins are considered structural proteins. This is because they are most often arranged in which of the following shapes:W) long, thin fibersX) spherical and smoothY) short and irregularZ) small, irregular, and hydrophilicANSWER: W) LONG THIN FIBERSBONUS23) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 molecules that are storage forms of glucose: starch; wax; glycogen; maltoseANSWER: STARCH; GLYCOGENTOSS-UP24) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the particle that carries the electromagnetic force?ANSWER: PHOTONBONUS24) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer If a wave has a frequency of 2,000 hertz, what is its period, in seconds?ANSWER: 0.0005 (ACCEPT: 5 × 10–4) (Solution: period = 1/f) Middle School Round 9 Page 12
TOSS-UP25) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is indicated by the following forecast: “A front moves through New England Monday with a few showers. Chillier air moves in behind the front gradually changing to lake-effect snows, followed by clear skies on Tuesday”:W) cold frontX) warm frontY) stationary front Z) inverted frontANSWER: W) COLD FRONTBONUS25) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is CLOSEST to the estimate of how many million years ago the first bacteria appeared on Earth:W) 65 X) 280 Y) 1,500 Z) 3,800ANSWER: Z) 3,800Middle SchoolRound 9Page 13