ROUND 5 TOSS-UP1) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following does the prefix “photo” (spell out the letters p, h, o, t, o ) mean, as in the word photometer:W) record (read as: REE-cord) X) lightY) measureZ) exposeANSWER: X) LIGHTBONUS1) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Arrange the following 3 choices in order of DECREASING average size: blood platelet; grain of common table salt; ragweed pollenANSWER: GRAIN OF SALT; RAGWEED POLLEN; BLOOD PLATELETTOSS-UP2) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a structure found in human cells: W) mitochondrion X) cell wallY) lysosomeZ) peroxisomeANSWER: X) CELL WALL2) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is closest to the meaning of intercellular (read carefully as: in-TER-cellular):W) from within cells X) between cellsY) inside of cellsZ) underneath cellsANSWER: X) BETWEEN CELLSBONUSMiddle School Round 5 Page 1
TOSS-UP3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following must be TRUE for a tree that doubled its mass over a growing period of 2 years:W) it has doubled its volumeX) it has doubled its number of atoms Y) it has doubled its inertiaZ) it has doubled its densityANSWER: Y) IT HAS DOUBLED ITS INERTIABONUS3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the ideal mechanical advantage of a ramp that is 24 meters long and 4 meters higher at one end versus the other?ANSWER: 6(Solution: input distance/output distance: 24/4 = 6)TOSS-UP4) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The presence of which of the following is evidence that 2 valley glaciers have or had at one time joined into a larger glacier: W) perpendicular striation pattern X) overlapping end morainesY) medial moraineZ) V-shaped valleyANSWER: Y) MEDIAL MORAINEBONUS4) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT generally true regarding glaciers:W) the Antarctic ice sheet is depressing the crust of the EarthX) we are currently in an interglacial periodY) the ice front of a glacier with a large zone of ablation is rapidly advancing Z) the Little Ice Age ended around the mid-nineteenth centuryANSWER: Y) THE ICE FRONT OF A GLACIER WITH A LARGE ZONE OF ABLATION IS RAPIDLY ADVANCINGMiddle School Round 5 Page 2
TOSS-UP5) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is the exact interval notation for all real numbers greater than or equal to –10 and less than 5:W) (–10, 5] (read as: open parenthesis, negative 10, comma, 5, close bracket) X) [–10, 5] (read as: open bracket, negative 10, comma, 5, close bracket)Y) [–10, 5) (read as: open bracket, negative 10, comma, 5, close parenthesis)Z) (–10, 5) (read as: open parenthesis, negative 10, comma, 5, close parenthesis)ANSWER: Y) [–10, 5)(note: if student interrupts, accept: “bracket, negative or minus 10, 5 parenthesis)(Solution: bracket for numbers included in the set; parenthesis for # not included in the set)BONUS5) MATH Short Answer Name all of the following 5 numbers that are NOT prime numbers: 2; 5; 17; 33; 37ANSWER: 33TOSS-UP6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the average internal Celsius temperature of the human body?ANSWER: 37BONUS6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, arrange the following 3 choices from the one with the LOWEST temperature to the HIGHEST temperature: 1) coldest temperature recorded on Earth; 2) average surface temperature of Saturn; 3) coldest ocean water temperatureANSWER: 2) AVERAGE SURFACE TEMPERATURE OF SATURN; 1) COLDEST TEMPERATURE RECORDED ON EARTH; 3) COLDEST OCEAN WATER TEMPERATURE (ACCEPT: 2; 1; 3) Middle School Round 5 Page 3
TOSS-UP7) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the blood vessels in vertebrate bodies where most of the exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide occurs?ANSWER: CAPILLARIES (ACCEPT: CAPILLARY)BONUS7) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What specific part of the human brain is most responsible for regulating body temperature?ANSWER: HYPOTHALAMUSTOSS-UP8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Which one of Newtons Laws of motion most directly deals with the resistance of a body to a change in its motion?ANSWER: FIRST LAW (ACCEPT: LAW OF INERTIA)BONUS8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Jerry has a mass of 100 kilograms. He runs with a velocity of 0.5 meters per second. Giving your answer in proper SI units, what is his momentum?ANSWER: 50 KILOGRAM METERS PER SECOND (must give units) (Solution: momentum = mv = (100kg)(0.5 m/s) = 50 kg.m/s) Middle School Round 5 Page 4
TOSS-UP9) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following geological terms best refers to deposits of unsorted and unstratified sediments deposited by the movement of a glacier:W) tillX) loess (read as: LUSS) Y) varveZ) glacial milkANSWER: W) TILL9) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most abundant element in the Sun? ANSWER: HYDROGENTOSS-UP10) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is undefined:BONUS W) 2÷0 X) 0 ÷ 2 Y) 0 – 0 Z) 02ANSWER: W) 2 ÷ 0BONUS10) MATH Short Answer Add the following 2 fractions and give your answer as a mixed fraction in lowest terms: 23 + 2 3  24 ANSWER: 1414 Middle School Round 5 Page 5
TOSS-UP11) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the SI base unit used for the intensity of a light source?ANSWER: CANDELABONUS11) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Giving your answer in proper scientific notation, convert 400 grams per liter into milligrams per liter:ANSWER: 4 × 105TOSS-UP12) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following describes the shape of a bacterial pilus: W) a solid sphereX) a cuboidal shaped cell Y) a thin tubeZ) a helical thick solid fiberANSWER: Y) A THIN TUBEBONUS12) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 groups of plants that are legumes: peas; rice; soy beans; peanutsANSWER: PEAS; SOY BEANS; PEANUTS (ACCEPT: ALL BUT RICE)Middle School Round 5 Page 6
TOSS-UP13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The most useful unit of concentration in the chemistry lab is:W) mole fraction X) mass percent Y) normalityZ) molarityANSWER: Z) MOLARITYBONUS13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of chemical reactions:W) they are always reversibleX) energy is either absorbed or released Y) a new substance is formedZ) chemical bonds are broken and formedANSWER: W) THEY ARE ALWAYS REVERSIBLETOSS-UP14) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What northward-moving ocean current is the dominant feature generally located off the east coast of the U.S.?ANSWER: GULF STREAMBONUS14) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Spring tides typically coincide with what 2 phases of the Moon?ANSWER: FULL; NEW (in any order) Middle School Round 5 Page 7
TOSS-UP15) MATH Short Answer What is the length, in inches, of one side of a square if the diagonal measures 7 2 ?ANSWER: 7BONUS15) MATH Short Answer If the area of a rectangle is 200 centimeters squared and the length is 20 centimeters, what is the perimeter of the rectangle, in centimeters?ANSWER: 60(Solution: 200 = (20)(w), w = 10; P = 2(20) +2(10) = 60 cm)TOSS-UP16) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the study of spiders:  W) arachnologyX) dendrochronology Y) planktologyZ) lepidopterologyANSWER: W) ARACHNOLOGYBONUS16) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the astronomical term for the orbital arrangement of a superior planet with reference to the positions of the Sun and Earth, at which time the superior planet will usually appear its brightest?ANSWER: OPPOSITIONMiddle School Round 5 Page 8
TOSS-UP17) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the location of the human thymus gland:W) upper chest X) inguinal canal Y) abdomenZ) brainANSWER: W) UPPER CHESTBONUS17) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common globular protein in red blood cells? ANSWER: HEMOGLOBINTOSS-UP18) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a heterogeneous mixture:W) 5.0% glucose solutionX) rubbing alcoholY) mixture of hydrogen and oxygen gases Z) concreteANSWER: Z) CONCRETEBONUS18) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following would be the most logical instrument to use when a small amount of suspended particles must be separated from a liquid:W) pH meter X) centrifuge Y) spectrometer Z) tweezersANSWER: X) CENTRIFUGE Middle School Round 5 Page 9
TOSS-UP19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes how stalagmites in caves are formed:W) mechanical weathering X) chemical weathering Y) meltingZ) decayingANSWER: X) CHEMICAL WEATHERINGBONUS19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the chief constituent of limestone:W) quartz X) clay Y) sand Z) calciteANSWER: Z) CALCITE TOSS-UP20) MATH Short Answer If a line has a slope of 10, what is the slope of every line that is perpendicular to it?ANSWER: – 1 (ACCEPT: –0.1) 10BONUS20) MATH Short Answer Consider an isosceles triangle whose vertex angle measures 20o. Find the measure of one of the EXTERIOR angles, in degrees, at the base of the triangle:ANSWER: 100 Middle School Round 5 Page 10
TOSS-UP21) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the atomic process that provides the energy for a star to shine?ANSWER: FUSIONBONUS21) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer The zodiac is typically considered to be made of how many constellations?ANSWER: 12TOSS-UP22) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT found in prokaryotes: W) DNAX) RNAY) ribosomes Z) golgiANSWER: Z) GOLGIBONUS22) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following 4 groups of organisms that are insects: flies; beetles; crayfish; mothsANSWER: FLIES; BEETLES; MOTHS (ACCEPT: ALL BUT CRAYFISH)Middle School Round 5 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Ultrasonic sound frequencies are typically considered to be:W) above 20 hertzX) below 20 hertzY) above 20 kilohertz Z) above 2,000 hertzANSWER: Y) ABOVE 20 KILOHERTZBONUS23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer In color synthesis using visible light, what is the most common term for the colors produced by combining equal proportions of two primary colors?ANSWER: SECONDARYTOSS-UP24) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The transfer of energy from the Sun across space is accomplished primarily by: W) conduction X) convection Y) radiation Z) radio wavesANSWER: Y) RADIATION24) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What layer of Earth’s atmosphere starts at about the stratopause and extends upwards to about 55 miles above the Earth?ANSWER: MESOSPHEREBONUSMiddle School Round 5 Page 12
TOSS-UP25) MATH Short Answer If a car travels at a rate of 50 miles per hour, what is the distance, in miles, traveled in 5 hours?ANSWER: 250(Solution: d = rt = (50mi/hr)(5 hr) = 250 miles)BONUS25) MATH Short Answer Giving your answer in exponential form, simplify the following expression: 103 ×104 102 ANSWER: 105Middle School Round 5 Page 13