ROUND 3          1) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Female insects usually lay their eggs near which of the following?W) Light X) Shade Y) Food Z) WaterANSWER: Y) FOODRound 3Page 1TOSS-UPBONUS1) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following biological molecules most directly enables the structural compartmentalization required for cellular respiration and photosynthesis [foh- tuh-SIN-thuh-sis]?W) Amino acidsX) Phospholipids [fos-foh-LIP-ids] Y) Glycogen [GLY-kuh-juhn]Z) CholesterolANSWER: X) PHOSPHOLIPIDS TOSS-UP2) PHYSICS Short Answer Which Greek scientist discovered that, when an object is immersed in a fluid, there is a buoyant force acting upward on the object equal to the weight of the displaced fluid?ANSWER: ARCHIMEDESBONUS2) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following is true for a cyclist applying her brakes while traveling west on a straight path?W) Her acceleration is zeroX) She accelerates to the eastY) She accelerates to the westZ) She accelerates both to the east and the westANSWER: X) SHE ACCELERATES TO THE EASTTOSS-UP3) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice In which of the following ways would oxygen’s electrons fill the 3 p subshells?W) 1 pair, 2 unpaired X) 1 pair, 1 unpaired Y) 2 pairsZ) 3 pairsANSWER: W) 1 PAIR, 2 UNPAIREDBONUS3) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What gaseous organic compound is made when ethanol is heated in a concentrated solution of sulfuric acid?ANSWER: ETHYLENE (ACCEPT: ETHENE)TOSS-UP4) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Mechanical weathering is one type of weathering, what is the other?ANSWER: CHEMICAL (ALSO ACCEPT BIOLOGICAL)BONUS4) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice For the June solstice, which of the following statements is NOT true?W) The northern hemisphere experiences the day with the longest period of sunlight X) There are 24 hours of sunlight in the Arctic CircleY) Earth is further from the Sun than it is at the winter solsticeZ) The Sun is directly overhead at noon in the Arctic CircleANSWER: Z) THE SUN IS DIRECTLY OVERHEAD AT NOON IN THE ARCTIC CIRCLE Round 3Page 2TOSS-UP5) MATH Short Answer How many distinct diagonals does a pentagon have? ANSWER: 5BONUS5)MATH Short Answer Thepolynomialp(x)=x^4 +5x^3 –2x^2 –24x has a zero at x=2.Factor p completely.ANSWER: x(x – 2)(x + 3)(x + 4) [NOTE: EXPRESSIONS IN ANSWER CAN BE IN ANY ORDER]TOSS-UP6) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following describes the purpose of the ground connection on a common power outlet?W) Provide a zero potential referenceX) Remove excess heat from the transmission systemY) Give a low resistance path for short circuits to travel through Z) Act as a small current source to prevent corrosionANSWER: Y) GIVE A LOW RESISTANCE PATH FOR SHORT CIRCUITS TO TRAVEL THROUGHBONUS6) ENERGY Short Answer If a solar panel produces energy directly proportional to the flux of incident photons, what is the best orientation it can have, relative to the line from the Earth to the Sun?ANSWER: PERPENDICULAR (ACCEPT: ORTHOGONAL)Round 3 Page 3TOSS-UP7) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true about spike moss?W) They do not have true rootsX) They have a well-developed vascular systemY) They are widely distributed in all parts of the world Z) Their leaves are spore-bearingANSWER: X) THEY HAVE A WELL-DEVELOPED VASCULAR SYSTEMBONUS7) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the term for the organic substance that consists of a dendritic network polymer of phenylpropene units and binds the cells, fibers, and vessels that constitute wood?ANSWER: LIGNINTOSS-UP8) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Pascal’s law governs the actions of forces in which of the following?W) GasesX) SolidsY) Incompressible fluids Z) A vacuumANSWER: Y) INCOMPRESSIBLE FLUIDSBONUS8) PHYSICS Short Answer What current, in amperes, is carried in a lightning stroke that lasts 0.5 seconds and transfers 100 coulombs of charge?ANSWER: 200 Round 3 Page 4TOSS-UP9) CHEMISTRY Short Answer In a flame test on an unknown compound, the flame is violet. What element is likely to be in the compound?ANSWER: POTASSIUM (ACCEPT: RUBIDIUM, CESIUM)BONUS9) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following anhydrous compounds has the lowest melting point?W) Aluminum chloride X) Calcium chloride Y) Copper (II) chloride Z) Lead (III) chlorideANSWER: W) ALUMINUM CHLORIDETOSS-UP10) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What term is used to describe the advance of desert conditions into formerly non-desert areas? ANSWER: DESERTIFICATION10) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The Intertropical Convergence Zone is NOT characterized by which of the following?W) DivergenceX) UpliftY) High cloud cover Z) Heavy precipitationANSWER: W) DIVERGENCERound 3Page 5BONUSTOSS-UP11) MATH Short Answer What is the surface area of a cube with volume 8? ANSWER: 24BONUS11) MATH Short Answer In terms of x and in standard polynomial form, what is the volume of a right rectangular prism with dimensions (x + 4), (x + 1), and (x + 6)?ANSWER: x3 + 11x2 + 34x + 24TOSS-UP 12) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following uses stored electricity and is required to get a gasoline-powered car's engine going?W) Catalytic converter X) Starter motorY) Fuel railZ) AlternatorANSWER: X) STARTER MOTORBONUS12) ENERGY Short Answer Most coals of the softer varieties are forms of which of the three major rock types?ANSWER: SEDIMENTARYRound 3 Page 6TOSS-UP13) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes blood?W) It is a specialized type of cell found in blood vesselsX) It is a type of cell formed in the bone marrowY) It is a kind of connective tissue in which red and white blood cells are suspended in plasma Z) It is a kind of epithelial tissue [ep-uh-THEE-lee-al]ANSWER: Y) IT IS A KIND OF CONNECTIVE TISSUE IN WHICH RED AND WHITE BLOOD CELLS ARE SUSPENDED IN PLASMABONUS13) BIOLOGY Short Answer Valproic acid and trapoxin are inhibitors of what class of enzymes that regulate gene expression by altering chromatin accessibility?ANSWER: HDAC (ACCEPT: HISTONE DEACETYLASES; DO NOT ACCEPT: HAT)TOSS-UP14) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements about the Moon best describes why we only see one side of the Moon from Earth?W) It does not rotateX) It has a side that is always darkY) It does not revolveZ) It has the same period for rotation and revolutionANSWER: Z) IT HAS THE SAME PERIOD FOR ROTATION AND REVOLUTIONBONUS14) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following elements CANNOT be a source of fuel in nuclear fusion?W) IronX) Oxygen Y) Nitrogen Z) CarbonANSWER: W) IRON Round 3Page 7TOSS-UP15) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following statements best describes the thermodynamic effect of an enzyme on the reaction it catalyzes?W) The energy level of the reactants is decreased in the presence of the enzyme X) The activation energy of the reaction is decreasedY) The activation energy of the reaction is increasedZ) The ΔG [delta-G] between products and reactants is decreasedANSWER: X) THE ACTIVATION ENERGY OF THE REACTION IS DECREASEDBONUS15) BIOLOGY Short Answer What recessive, life-threatening disorder affects the cells that produce mucus, sweat, and digestive juices, rendering secretions thick and sticky?ANSWER: CYSTIC FIBROSIS (ALSO ACCEPT CF OR MUCOVISCIDOSIS)TOSS-UP16) PHYSICS Short Answer The two leaves of an electroscope repel each other and stand out at an angle. What force balances the electrical force so the leaves don’t stand out farther?ANSWER: GRAVITYBONUS16) PHYSICS Short Answer A block of wood, when floating in water, displaces 300 cubic centimeters of water. When completely submerged, the block displaces 400 cubic centimeters of water. What is the specific gravity of the block?ANSWER: 0.75 Round 3 Page 8TOSS-UP17) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice A nitrogen atom present in the backbone of a polypeptide [pol-ee-PEP-tyd] is part of which of the following functional groups?W) A primary amineX) A secondary amineY) A tertiary amine [TER-shee-er-ee] Z) An amideANSWER: Z) AN AMIDE17) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the final product of purine metabolism excreted in the urine?W) UreaX) Uric acid Y) Ammonia Z) AmmoniumANSWER: X) URIC ACIDBONUS TOSS-UP18) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the most common element in Earth’s crust? ANSWER: OXYGENBONUS18) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of the mixed layer of the ocean?W) Relatively stratified in the verticalX) In direct contact with the atmosphere Y) Stirred by winds and convectionZ) Varied depth with latitude and seasonANSWER: W) RELATIVELY STRATIFIED IN THE VERTICALRound 3Page 9TOSS-UPBONUS19) MATH Short Answer For what values of x is the function f(x)= [f of x equals the fraction with numerator x squared and denominator x squared minus 4 x plus 4] NOTdefined? ANSWER: 2 19) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following inequalities has NO solutions?W) 7x + 4 > 3X) |x – 1| > -10 [the absolute value of the quantity x minus 1 is greater than negative 10] Y) |x + 3| < -2 [the absolute value of the quantity x plus 3 is less than negative 2]Z) -100x + 5 ≥ 8ANSWER: Y) |x + 3| < -2TOSS-UP 20) ENERGY Short Answer What energy barrier must a chemical reaction pass in order to proceed?ANSWER: ACTIVATION ENERGYBONUS20) ENERGY Short Answer One proposed geoengineering mechanism that could be used to mitigate increased atmospheric carbon dioxide levels is called iron seeding and involves spreading large quantities of iron over the surface of the ocean. What is the name of the organism that would grow as a result, leading to carbon sequestration [see-kwes-TRAY- shuhn]?ANSWER: PLANKTON (ACCEPT: PHYTOPLANKTON)Round 3 Page 10TOSS-UP21) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following choices is NOT a source of new genetic combinations?W) Mitosis [my-TOH-sis] X) FertilizationY) MutationZ) Meiosis [meye-OH-sis]ANSWER: W) MITOSISBONUS21) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following parts of B and T cells bind to antigens?W) Variable region X) Heavy chainY) Alpha chain only Z) Disulfide bridgeANSWER: W) VARIABLE REGION TOSS-UP22) PHYSICS Short Answer What force does a charged particle moving through a magnetic field experience that is perpendicular to the direction the particle is traveling?ANSWER: LORENTZ (ACCEPT: MAGNETIC FORCE)BONUS22) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the mass, in kilograms, of a 2 kilogram rock on a planet with a gravitational acceleration of 8.2 meters per second squared?ANSWER: 2Round 3 Page 11TOSS-UP23) CHEMISTRY Short Answer At -78o Celsius, dry ice changes directly from a solid to a gas. What is this process called?ANSWER: SUBLIMATIONBONUS23) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the formula for n-Octadecanoic acid?W) C6H12O6X) C18H36COOH Y) C17H35COOH Z) C16H32COOHANSWER: Y) C17H35COOH TOSS-UP24) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer In what compass direction would the magnetic north pole of your compass point during a period in which the Earth’s magnetic field was reversed?ANSWER: SOUTHBONUS24) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes why Neptune is blue?W) A sub-surface ocean below a layer of iceX) Absorption of light by methane in its atmosphere Y) Blue-shifted due to its orbitZ) Hydrocarbon hazeANSWER: X) ABSORPTION OF LIGHT BY METHANE IN ITS ATMOSPHERERound 3Page 12TOSS-UP25) MATH Short Answer If ln   [natural log of the quantity x cubed equals 6], what is ln   [the natural log of the quantity x squared]?ANSWER: 425) MATH Short Answer If f(x) = 4x3 – 4x2 + 10, then what is f(-2) [f of negative 2]? ANSWER: -38Round 3Page 13BONUS