ROUND 2          TOSS-UP1) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the name of the sedimentary rock formed by compaction and cementation of rounded, pebble-size particles?ANSWER: CONGLOMERATEBONUS1) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of a good index fossil?W) Easy to identifyX) Geographically widespread Y) Slow evolutionZ) Easy to preserveANSWER: Y) SLOW EVOLUTION TOSS-UP2) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT an evolutionary adaptation of plants to arid climates?W) Leaves have a waxy coatingX) Carbon incorporation and the Calvin cycle are separated Y) Stomata are closed at nightZ) Leaves are absentANSWER: Y) STOMATA ARE CLOSED AT NIGHTBONUS2) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following mammal species is usually considered diurnal [dy-UR-nl]?W) Eastern fox squirrel X) Black-footed ferret Y) Virginia opossumZ) RaccoonANSWER: W) EASTERN FOX SQUIRRELRound 2Page 1
TOSS-UP3) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the specific chemical term for the minimum pressure required to produce liquefaction of a substance at the critical temperature?ANSWER: CRITICAL PRESSUREBONUS3) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Name the molecule with the formula CH3COOCH2CH2CH3. ANSWER: PROPYL ETHANOATE (ACCEPT: PROPYL ACETATE)TOSS-UP 4) MATH Multiple Choice The variables x and y vary directly. Which of the following equations could represent the relationship between x and y?W) (1/5)x = 1/y [one fifth x equals 1 over y] X) x/y = 1/5 [x over y equals one fifth]Y) xy = 1/5 [x y equals one fifth]Z) xy = 5ANSWER: X) x/y = 1/5BONUS4) MATH Short Answer An open box is to be made from a rectangular piece of material 8 inches by 6 inches by cutting equal squares of side x from the four corners and turning up the sides. In terms of x, give an expression for the volume of the box in cubic inches.ANSWER: x(8- 2x)(6- 2x) (ACCEPT: 4x3 – 28x2 + 48x)Round 2 Page 2
TOSS-UP5) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A rock is thrown vertically upwards with speed v from the edge of a cliff. At the same moment, a second rock is thrown vertically downwards with the same initial speed v. Neglecting air resistance, which of the following statements is true?W) The rock that was thrown upwards reaches the bottom of the cliff with a higher velocity X) The rock that was thrown downwards reaches the bottom of the cliff with a higher velocity Y) Both rocks reach the bottom of the cliff with the same velocity at the same timeZ) Both rocks reach the bottom of the cliff with the same velocity but at different timesANSWER: Z) BOTH ROCKS REACH THE BOTTOM OF THE CLIFF WITH THE SAME VELOCITY BUT AT DIFFERENT TIMESBONUS5) PHYSICS Short Answer A mass is spun horizontally at the end of a string. If its speed is changed so that the centripetal force is doubled, in simplest decimal form to the nearest tenth, what is the ratio of final speed to initial speed?ANSWER: 1.4TOSS-UP6) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following mineral properties is most reliable for identification? W) ColorX) Density Y) Cleavage Z) LusterANSWER: Y) CLEAVAGEBONUS6) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer In what wavelengths of electromagnetic radiation do greenhouse gases absorb and reradiate energy back to Earth’s surface?ANSWER: INFRARED (ACCEPT: IR)Round 2 Page 3
TOSS-UP7) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is true of enzymes?W) They increase the activation energy of metabolic reactionsX) They have active sites that bind to specific substrate molecules Y) They are made of chitin [KY-tin] proteinZ) They generally act on a variety of substrate moleculesANSWER: X) THEY HAVE ACTIVE SITES THAT BIND TO SPECIFIC SUBSTRATE MOLECULESBONUS7) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following branches of science deals with study of the life and phenomena of inland standing waters, especially lakes and ponds?W) Limnology [lim-NOL-uh-jee] X) HydrologyY) Ichthyology [ik-thee-OL-uh-jee] Z) EcologyANSWER: W) LIMNOLOGY TOSS-UP8) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a potential source of biogas?W) LandfillsX) Sewage treatment plants Y) Automobile engineZ) Animal wasteANSWER: Y) AUTOMOBILE ENGINEBONUS8) ENERGY Multiple Choice The presence of which of the following traits is required for the creation of all oil traps?W) AnticlineX) SynclineY) Impermeable layer Z) FaultANSWER: Y) IMPERMEABLE LAYERRound 2Page 4
TOSS-UP9) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following catabolic pathways liberates carbon dioxide?W) Electron transportX) Glycolysis [gly-KOL-uh-sis] Y) Citric acid cycleZ) Cori cycleANSWER: Y) CITRIC ACID CYCLEBONUS9) CHEMISTRY Short Answer If one mole of a substance with a molar mass of 20 is burned at constant pressure and 800 kilojoules of energy is released as heat, what is the standard enthalpy change, in kilojoules, when a 5-gram sample of this substance is burned at constant pressure?ANSWER: -200 (MUST INCLUDE NEGATIVE SIGN IN ANSWER)TOSS-UP 63!following fraction: 62!3! [the numerator is 63 factorial; the denominator is 62 factorial times 310) MATH Short Answer Providing your answer to one decimal place, find the value of the factorial]. ANSWER: 10.5BONUS10) MATH Short Answer Name all of the quadrants that contain solutions of the inequality 2x – y > 4 .ANSWER: I, III, IV (ACCEPT: 1, 3, 4 or FIRST, THIRD, FOURTH)Round 2 Page 5
TOSS-UP11) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A string 40 centimeters long produces a fundamental frequency of 384 hertz. To produce a note one octave higher, the tension in the string must be increased by which of the following factors?W) 0.7 X) 1.4 Y) 2 Z) 4ANSWER: Z) 4BONUS11) PHYSICS Short Answer A meter stick is held by a low-friction support on a stand. A single weight and an air-filled balloon hang from the left side of the meter stick; a weight hangs from the right side of the meter stick. The fulcrum is adjusted so that the system is balanced and level. If the string holding the balloon is burned so as to exert no torque when the string breaks, identify by number what will happen when the string breaks: 1) the right side of the meter stick will go down; 2) the left side of the meter stick will go down; or 3) the meter stick will remain balanced.ANSWER: 1TOSS-UP12) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is produced by gas-to-particle conversion in the atmosphere?W) Primary particulate matter X) Secondary particulate matter Y) Tertiary aerosolsZ) Primary aerosolsANSWER: X) SECONDARY PARTICULATE MATTERBONUS12) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What are the two most abundant minerals in the continental crust?ANSWER: QUARTZ AND FELDSPAR (ACCEPT: FELDSPAR FAMILY) Round 2 Page 6
TOSS-UP13) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the highest level of protein structure present in collagen, a fibrous protein with three discrete helical polypeptides [HEL-i-kuhl pol-ee-PEP-tyds] supercoiled into a triple helix?ANSWER: QUATERNARYBONUS13) BIOLOGY Short Answer Estrogen and progesterone [proh-JES-tuh-rohn] are most directly regulated by which two hormones?ANSWER: FSH AND LH (ACCEPT: FOLLICLE-STIMULATING AND LUTEINIZING)TOSS-UP14) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is typically increased in order for electricity to travel long distances through transmission lines? W) Voltage X) Amperage Y) Wattage Z) CurrentANSWER: W) VOLTAGE14) ENERGY Short Answer What type of semi-conducting junction is essential to the functioning of a solar cell?ANSWER: P-N JUNCTION (ACCEPT: P-N)Round 2Page 7BONUS
TOSS-UP15) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is an aldehyde [AL-duh-hyd]?W) C11H20X) C5H11OH Y) C5H11CHO Z) C5H11NH2ANSWER: Y) C5H11CHOBONUS15) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Which one of the following five metals would react the least with dilute hydrochloric acid: 1) lead, 2) chromium, 3) manganese, 4) nickel, 5) gold?ANSWER: 5 (ACCEPT: GOLD)TOSS-UP 16) MATH Multiple Choice If the surface area of a cube is 96 square units, which of the following is the length of a diagonal of a face of the cube?W) 4X) 4√2 Y) 4√3 Z) 16√2   ANSWER: X) 4√216) MATH Short Answer Determine the largest possible real domain of y = √𝑥−1 [y equals BONUS√𝑥2− 1   the fraction with numerator the square root of the quantity x minus 1 and denominator the square root of the quantity x squared minus 1 ].ANSWER: x > 1Round 2 Page 8
TOSS-UP17) PHYSICS Multiple Choice If two inductance coils of inductance L are connected in parallel, but are well separated, the equivalent inductance of the system is which of the following?W) 0.5L X) LY) 2L Z) L2ANSWER: W) 0.5LBONUS17) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Two balls are dropped one second apart from a tall building. Given g as 10 meters per second squared and neglecting air resistance, what is the approximate distance in meters between the two balls three seconds after the first ball is dropped?W) 20X) 25Y) 45Z) Depends on the massesANSWER: X) 25 TOSS-UP18) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following theories describes the random movement of small particles in the atmosphere?W) DiffusionX) Reynolds number Y) Brownian motion Z) KineticANSWER: Y) BROWNIAN MOTIONBONUS18) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Igneous [IG-nee-uhs] rocks and magmas are classified into four main compositional groups: ultramafic, mafic, intermediate, and felsic, based on the content of what chemical compound?ANSWER: SILICARound 2 Page 9
TOSS-UP19) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the term for the process in which a reptile sheds its outer layer of skin, or an arthropod [AHR-thruh-pod] or crustacean [kruh-STAY-shuhn] sheds its outer shell?ANSWER: ECDYSIS (ACCEPT: MOLTING)BONUS19) BIOLOGY Short Answer The acronym NAD stands for what phrase? ANSWER: NICOTINAMIDE ADENINE DINUCLEOTIDETOSS-UP20) ENERGY Short Answer Cadmium and boron are used in a nuclear reactor to absorb which subatomic particle?ANSWER: NEUTRONBONUS20) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the elements, used as a nuclear fuel, is most abundant in the Earth's crust?W) Uranium X) Plutonium Y) Thorium Z) AmericiumANSWER: Y) THORIUM Round 2Page 10
TOSS-UP21) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice When hydrogen reacts with 2-butanone, which of the following is the primary product?W) A primary aldehyde [AL-duh-hyd] X) A secondary aldehydeY) A primary alcoholZ) A secondary alcoholANSWER: Z) A SECONDARY ALCOHOLBONUS21) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Arrange the following three choices in order of increasing number of oxygen atoms: 1) one mole of carbon monoxide; 2) one mole of carbon dioxide; 3) one-half mole of calcium carbonate.ANSWER: 1, 3, 2 (ACCEPT: ONE MOLE OF CARBON MONOXIDE; ONE-HALF MOLE OF CALCIUM CARBONATE; ONE MOLE OF CARBON DIOXIDE)TOSS-UP22) MATH Short Answer If two 6-sided fair dice are rolled, providing your answer as a fraction in lowest te1rms, what is the probability that both numbers will be even?ANSWER: 422) MATH Short Answer Mary travels for 110 miles averaging 55 miles per hour and for 150miles averaging 50 miles per hour. What is Mary’s average speed in miles per hour for the trip? ANSWER: 52  BONUSRound 2 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) PHYSICS Multiple Choice White light is incident on a diffraction grating. Which of the following colors will be diffracted through the largest angle?W) Red X) Yellow Y) Blue Z) GreenANSWER: W) RED23) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A square conducting loop of length L on a side carries a currenti. Which of the following best characterizes the magnetic field at the center of the loop?W) Independent of LX) Inversely proportional to L Y) Proportional to L2Z) Proportional to LANSWER: X) INVERSELY PROPORTIONAL TO L TOSS-UP24) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following clockwise currents brings warm Caribbean waters into the Gulf of Mexico before joining the Gulf Stream?W) Caribbean system X) LoopY) North Equatorial Z) FloridaANSWER: X) LOOPBONUS BONUS24) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following does NOT describe the asthenosphere?W) Region of the lower mantleX) Viscous [VIS-kuhs]Y) Mechanically weak and ductileZ) Involved in plate tectonic movementsANSWER: W) REGION OF THE LOWER MANTLERound 2Page 12
TOSS-UP25) BIOLOGY Short Answer Who discovered the antibiotic nature of penicillin in 1928? ANSWER: SIR ALEXANDER FLEMING (ACCEPT: ALEXANDER FLEMING, FLEMING)BONUS25) BIOLOGY Short Answer Of the following four choices, identify all that are involved in plant primary growth: 1) axillary bud meristem, 2) cork cambium, 3) apical meristem, 4) vascular cambium.ANSWER: 1, 3 (ACCEPT: AXILLARY BUD MERISTEM, APICAL MERISTEM)Round 2 Page 13