          1) Earth and Space – Short Answer earthquake originates?ANSWER: EPICENTERROUND 1 TOSS-UPWhat term is used to describe the point on the surface, below which anBONUS1) Earth and Space – Multiple Choice You are traveling west by jet and cross three time zone boundaries. If your watch reads 3:00 p.m. when you arrive, to what time should you reset it?W) 12:00 noonX) 6:00 p.m.Y) 12:00 midnight Z) 6:00 a.m.ANSWER: W) 12:00 NOON                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP2) Biology – Short Answer What type of leukocytes, characterized by their CD4 receptors, secrete cytokines [sigh-toe-kines] that activate nearby B and T cells?ANSWER: HELPER T CELLS2) Biology – Short Answer What is the term used to describe a virus that attacks bacteria? ANSWER: BACTERIOPHAGE (ACCEPT: PHAGE)BONUSRound 1Page 1
TOSS-UP3) Math – Short Answer Where is the derivative of the function f(x) = 2x2 + 5x – 3 equal to zero? Answer: AT x = -5/4 (ALSO ACCEPT x = -1.25 OR -11⁄4)BONUS3) Math – Short Answer If the line tangent to the graph of the function f(x) at the point (1, 3) passes through the point (-1.5, -2), then what is value of the derivative of f(x) when x = 1?ANSWER: 2~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP4) Energy – Multiple Choice If the frequency of a wave is decreased, which of the following changes must occur for the wave to maintain a constant velocity?W) The period must decreaseX) The wavelength must increase Y) The amplitude must increase Z) The amplitude must decreaseANSWER: X) THE WAVELENGTH MUST INCREASEBONUS4) Energy – Short Answer What is the process in plant metabolism in which Rubisco adds oxygen instead of carbon dioxide into the carbon intermediate of the Calvin Cycle, thus reducing photosynthetic efficiency?ANSWER: PHOTORESPIRATIONRound 1 Page 2
TOSS-UP5) Chemistry – Short Answer What name is given to the thermodynamic state function equal to the sum of internal energy and the product of pressure and volume, whose difference in a chemical reaction is equal to the isobaric heat transfer accompanying the reaction, and which is symbolized by the letter H?ANSWER: ENTHALPYBONUS5) Chemistry – Multiple Choice Which of the following statements regarding stoichiometry [stoh-kee-om- et-ree] is not true?W) Calculating a stochiometric ratio of reagents assumes the reaction goes to completionX) Volume ratios can be substituted for molar ratios in calculations for gas phase reactionsY) Percent yield is the ratio of theoretical yield to empirical yield for a reactionZ) Limiting reagent calculations require knowledge of the molar masses of all reactant speciesANSWER: Y) PERCENT YIELD IS THE RATIO OF THEORETICAL YIELD TO EMPIRICAL YIELD FOR A REACTION                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP6) Physics – Short Answer The electric potential at a point due to a unit positive charge is found to be V. If the distance between the charge and the point is quadrupled, what is the new value of the electric potential?ANSWER: V/4BONUS6) Physics – Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is not true regarding light?W) The energy of light increases as frequency increasesX) Refraction occurs when a beam of light travels between mediums with different indices of refraction Y) Light can be thought of as a self-propagating electromagnetic waveZ) Diffraction arises due to the wave-like properties of light, but interference is due to the particle-like properties of lightANSWER: Z) DIFFRACTION ARISES DUE TO THE WAVE-LIKE PROPERTIES OF LIGHT, BUT INTERFERENCE IS DUE TO THE PARTICLE-LIKE PROPERTIES OF LIGHTRound 1Page 3
7) Earth and Space – Short Answer of a massive star?ANSWER: SUPERNOVA7) Earth and Space – Short Answer ANSWER: WATER VAPORTOSS-UPWhat extremely luminous explosion of radiation occurs from the deathBONUSWhat greenhouse gas has the greatest abundance in the atmosphere?                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP8) Biology – Short Answer When a phylogenetic tree has the fewest number of evolutionary events possible, it is said to embody what principle of simplicity?ANSWER: PARSIMONYBONUS8) Biology – Short Answer What phenomenon involves the injection of double-stranded RNAs turning off the expression of genes with the same sequence as the RNA?ANSWER: RNA INTERFERENCERound 1 Page 4
TOSS-UP9) Energy – Short Answer What is the SI unit commonly used to measure electrical resistance? ANSWER: OHMBONUS9) Energy – Short Answer What law in physical chemistry, important in reaction thermodynamics, states that the total enthalpy change of a reaction is the sum of the enthalpy changes of each step of the reaction?ANSWER: HESS’S LAW                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP10) Math – Short Answer If one side of a right triangle is 14 inches and its opposite angle is 30 degrees, what is the diameter of the circle circumscribed around this triangle?ANSWER: 28BONUS10) Math – Short Answer A particle’s position is defined by the equation x(t) = 2t3 – 15t2 + 24t – 60. At what times t is the particle at rest?ANSWER: t = 1 AND 4Round 1 Page 5
11) Chemistry – Multiple ChoiceW) Network solid X) Ionic solidY) Molecular solid Z) Metallic solidANSWER: W) NETWORK SOLIDW) Newton X) Bernoulli Y) PascalZ) ArchimedesANSWER: Z) ARCHIMEDES12) Physics – Multiple Choice along a surface?BONUSWhich of the following statements is NOT true regarding a wheel rollingTOSS-UPCeramic materials typically belong to what class of solid structure?BONUS11) Chemistry – Short Answer Consider the reaction of nitrogen dioxide with molecular oxygen to form dinitrogen pentoxide. If the rate of consumption of oxygen gas is 1 liter per minute, what is the rate, in liters per minute, of disappearance of nitrogen dioxide gas?ANSWER: 4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP12) Physics – Multiple Choice What is the name of the principle that states that an object, partly or completely, submerged in a fluid will experience a buoyant force equal to the weight of the fluid the object displaces?W) If the wheel is rolling smoothly, the only friction acting on it is static frictionX) When rolling down a ramp, the force of static friction on the wheel is directed down the rampY) When rolling on a flat surface, the force of static friction on the wheel is directed in the opposite direction as the motion of the wheelZ) For a wheel rolling down a ramp, the normal force is perpendicular to the rampANSWER: X) WHEN ROLLING DOWN A RAMP, THE FORCE OF STATIC FRICTION ON THE WHEEL IS DIRECTED DOWN THE RAMPRound 1 Page 6
TOSS-UP13) Earth and Space – Short Answer What force is primarily responsible for the collapse of molecular clouds into stars?ANSWER: GRAVITYBONUS13) Earth and Space – Multiple Choice Native to Asia, the Burmese python was brought to the United States for sale as a pet. Owners released their Burmese pythons into the wild of the Florida Everglades, creating ecological problems in that habitat. Which best describes the Burmese Python?W) Non-competitive species X) Invasive speciesY) Keystone speciesZ) Primary successionANSWER: X) INVASIVE SPECIES                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~14) Math – Short Answer ANSWER: II, III, AND IVTOSS-UPIn what quadrants does the graph of the equation y = -2x – 3 lie? (ACCEPT: SECOND, THIRD, AND FOURTH OR ALL BUT FIRST)BONUSAssuming x is a value for which the denominator is defined, simplify the fraction14) Math – Short Answerwith numerator 6x2 + 4x – 2 and denominator 12x2 – 4x.      ANSWER: (x +1)/(2x)Round 1 Page 7
TOSS-UP15) Chemistry – Multiple Choice Which of the following elemental substances is not at standard state?W) Diamond at 25 degrees Celsius and one atmosphereX) Rhombic sulfur at 25 degrees Celsius and one atmosphere Y) Gaseous dioxygen at 25 degrees Celsius and one atmosphere Z) Gaseous neon at 25 degrees Celsius and one atmosphereANSWER: W) DIAMOND AT 25 DEGREES CELSIUS AND ONE ATMOSPHEREBONUS15) Chemistry – Multiple Choice Metallic sodium will react with water to form sodium hydroxide and hydrogen gas. What type of reaction is this?W) SynthesisX) DecompositionY) Single displacement Z) Double displacementANSWER: Y) SINGLE DISPLACEMENT                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP16) Biology – Short Answer What neurotransmitter is released by motor neurons at the neuromuscular junction?ANSWER: ACETYLCHOLINE [uh-see-tul-koe-leen]16) Biology – Multiple ChoiceW) SucroseX) Galactose [guh-lac-tohs] Y) MaltoseZ) LactoseANSWER: X) GALACTOSEBONUSWhich of the following is a monosaccharide?Round 1Page 8
TOSS-UP17) Energy – Short Answer What is the name of the prediction in classical physics that incorrectly proposed that an ideal black body at thermal equilibrium will emit increasingly higher frequencies of radiation with infinite power?ANSWER: ULTRAVIOLET CATASTROPHE (ACCEPT: RAYLEIGH-JEANS CATASTROPHE)BONUS17) Energy – Short Answer What is the primary energy carrier that is synthesized in the Krebs Cycle and is one of the most common reducing agents in the cell?ANSWER: NADH OR NICOTINAMIDE ADENINE DINUCLEOTIDE (DO NOT ACCEPT: NAD+)                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~18) Physics – Multiple ChoiceW) Balmer series X) Lyman series Y) Paschen series Z) Bohr seriesANSWER: W) BALMER SERIESTOSS-UPThe lines in the visible region of the hydrogen spectrum are known as the:BONUS18) Physics – Short Answer Color confinement refers to the inability to find what two particles in isolation? ANSWER: QUARKS, GLUONSRound 1 Page 9
TOSS-UP19) Earth and Space – Short Answer What prefix describes clouds found in the middle altitude range? ANSWER: ALTOBONUS19) Earth and Space – Short Answer What gravitationally bound systems of matter, classified by the Hubble sequence, are the basic units of the Universe?ANSWER: GALAXIES~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP20) Biology – Short Answer What immunoglobulin class is the largest antibody present in the human circulatory system?ANSWER: IgMBONUS20) Biology – Multiple Choice A scientist isolates a small amount of DNA from a Tyrannosaur fossil. Which of the following would be most useful for increasing the amount of DNA with which the scientist has to work?W) RFLP analysisX) Polymerase chain reaction Y) Southern blottingZ) SDS-PAGEANSWER: X) POLYMERASE CHAIN REACTIONRound 1Page 10
21) Math – Short Answer inverse of 6?ANSWER: 20821) Math – Short Answer ANSWER: 41TOSS-UPIf f(x) equals the cube root of open parenthesis x + 8 close parenthesis, what is fBONUSWhat is the sum of all the distinct prime factors of 15 factorial?                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP22) Chemistry – Short Answer What laboratory instrument, containing gradations that increase from top to bottom, is used to deliver precise quantities of titrant to the analyte in a titration?ANSWER: BURETTE (ACCEPT: BURET)BONUS22) Chemistry – Short Answer If you have 50 milliliters of a 0.75 molar solution of NaCl, how much water, in milliliters, should you add to dilute the NaCl concentration to 0.25 molar?ANSWER: 100Round 1 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) Physics – Short Answer A 100 milliwatt laser delivers 2.50 × 1017 photons per second. Expressing your answer in scientific notation with one significant figure, how much energy in joules does each photon deliver?ANSWER: 4 × 10-1923) Physics – Short Answer ANSWER: SIEVERTSBONUSRadiation dose equivalents are measured in what SI unit?Round 1Page 12