ROUND 7A TOSS-UP1) Math – Short Answer A scientist is designing an experiment in which she will determine if there is a correlation between drinking tea and contracting cancer. What statistical term is used to describe the assumption that drinking tea does not correlate with contracting cancer?ANSWER: NULL HYPOTHESISBONUS1) Math – Short Answer Subtracting a certain positive number from its square gives 110. Find the number. ANSWER: 11                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP2) Physics – Short Answer Two point charges, Q1 and Q2, that have charges of +8 nanocoulombs and -8 nanocoulombs, respectively, are placed at two vertices of an equilateral triangle. If a third charge, Q3, of +3 nanocoulombs is placed at the third vertex, what is the potential energy associated with Q3?ANSWER: ZEROBONUS2) Physics – Short Answer Identify all of the following four reference frames that can be considered approximately intertial: 1) A stationary book; 2) A car coasting along at a steady speed; 3) A sky diver at terminal velocity; 4) A rocket taking off.ANSWER: 1, 2, AND 3          Round 7A Page 1
3) Earth and Space – Multiple Choice what astronomical phenomenon?W) NovaX) White dwarf Y) Supernova Z) Black holeANSWER: Y) SUPERNOVATOSS-UPAll the elements that are more massive than iron were formed by3) Earth and Space – Multiple Choiceunsaturated air parcel will increase as the parcel is forced aloft?W) Relative humidityX) Mixing ratioY) Saturation vapor pressure Z) Barometric pressure4) Chemistry – Multiple ChoiceW) Iodic acidX) Formic acidY) Acetic acidZ) Hypochlorous acidANSWER: W) IODIC ACID4) Chemistry – Multiple Choice metals?TOSS-UPWhich of the following acids is stronger than hydrofluoric acid?BONUSWhich of the following statements is NOT true regarding alkaline earthW) Calcium burns brick-red in a flame testX) Magnesium has no naturally occurring radioisotopes Y) Radium is found in all uranium-bearing oresZ) Radium has 3 stable isotopesANSWER: Z) RADIUM HAS 3 STABLE ISOTOPESBONUSIn a stable atmosphere, which of the following properties of anANSWER: W) RELATIVE HUMIDITY                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Round 7APage 2
5) Biology – Multiple ChoiceW) Glutamine [gloo-tuh-meen] X) HistidineY) Leucine [loo-seen]Z) LysineANSWER: Y) LEUCINE5) Biology – Short Answer nontoxic form?ANSWER: URIC ACIDTOSS-UPWhich of the following amino acids is non-polar?BONUSInsects and reptiles excrete nitrogenous [nigh-traw-jen-uhs] waste in what~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP6) Energy – Short Answer During physics lab, you create a graph of the kinetic energy of a bouncing ball versus time. What physical quantity is represented by the slope of the graph?ANSWER: POWERBONUS6) Energy – Short Answer Identify all of the following four processes that result in a decrease in entropy: 1) freezing of water; 2) vaporization of water; 3) extraction of magnesium and pure water from sea water; 4) sublimation of dry ice.ANSWER: 1 AND 3Round 7A Page 3
TOSS-UP7) Math – Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT equal to a × log base b of c?W) 1/a × log base b of the fraction a/cX) –a × log base b of the fraction 1/cY) –log base b of open parenthesis c-a close parenthesis Z) Natural log of (ea) × log base b of cANSWER: W) 1/a × log BASE b OF THE FRACTION a/c BONUS7) Math – Multiple Choice It takes 3 painters 4 hours to paint one house. How many hours does it take one painter to paint two houses of the same size?W) 12 X) 24 Y) 36 Z) 48ANSWER: X) 24~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP8) Physics – Short Answer Identify all of the following three particles that are considered leptons: 1) Protons; 2) Electrons; 3) Neutrons.ANSWER: 2BONUS8) Physics – Short Answer A figure skater is holding his hands outstretched as he spins at 180 rotations per minute. If his hands are 180 centimeters apart, what is the speed in meters per second of his hands in terms of π?ANSWER: 5.4π (ACCEPT: 27/5π)Round 7A Page 4
9) Earth and Space – Multiple ChoiceW) Full moon X) New moon Y) First quarter Z) Last quarterANSWER: W) FULL MOON9) Earth and Space – Multiple Choice occur?W) Near the groundX) 10 meters above the ground Y) 50 meters above the ground Z) 100 meters above the groundANSWER: W) NEAR THE GROUNDTOSS-UPA lunar eclipse can occur only during what phase of the moon?BONUSAt what altitude does the greatest variation in daily temperature                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP10) Chemistry – Short Answer What major organic product is produced when an ethene and hydrogen gas are reacted on Raney [ray-nee] nickel?ANSWER: ETHANEBONUS10) Chemistry – Multiple Choice To measure the number of moles of barium in a solution containing both magnesium 2+ and barium 2+ ions, a student added sodium sulfate and collected the precipitate. Then, he weighed the precipitate, and used stoichiometric conversions to estimate the number of moles of barium, and discovered that his method over-reported the actual value stated by his teacher. Which of the following plausibly explains the discrepancy?W) The student precipitated both magnesium and barium when adding sodium sulfate X) The student used a molar mass for barium that was 10% too highY) The student used a molar mass for sulfur that was 10% too highZ) The student didn’t properly dry his precipitate before weighingANSWER: Z) THE STUDENT DIDN’T PROPERLY DRY HIS PRECIPITATE BEFORE WEIGHINGRound 7A Page 5
TOSS-UP11) Biology – Multiple Choice Which of the following types of cells has the longest lifespan in circulation?W) Erythrocyte [uh-ree-throh-sight] X) PlateletY) MonocyteZ) Neutrophil [nyoo-troh-fil]ANSWER: W) ERYTHROCYTEBONUS11) Biology – Short Answer What model in population genetics predicts that allele frequencies will stay constant from generation to generation, assuming that the population remains free of other evolutionary influences?ANSWER: HARDY-WEINBERG PRINCIPLE                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP12) Math – Multiple Choice The average value of a continuous function f(x) on a closed interval from 2 to 6 is 8. What is the value of the definite integral from 2 to 6 of f(x) dx?W) 4 X) 8 Y) 24 Z) 32ANSWER: Z) 32BONUSf(x) is a twice differentiable function where f prime of x is less than 0 and f12) Math – Short Answerdouble prime of x is less than 0 for all real numbers. If f(4) = 12 and f(5) = 9, what is the largest possible integer value for f(6)?ANSWER: 5Round 7A Page 6
TOSS-UP13) Physics – Short Answer The equations x-prime = x - vt and t-prime = t represent what mathematical conversion, used between two reference frames traveling at speeds much less than the speed of light?ANSWER: GALILEAN TRANSFORMATIONBONUS13) Physics – Multiple Choice An electromagnetic wave that has a wavelength of 10 meters would be best classified as is in which of the following regions of the electromagnetic spectrum?W) Microwave X) Ultraviolet Y) VisibleZ) RadioANSWER: Z) RADIO14) Earth and Space – Multiple Choice direction?W) Northeast X) Northwest Y) Southeast Z) SouthwestANSWER: Y) SoutheastTOSS-UPA wind blowing from 135° equates to the wind coming from which~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~BONUS14) Earth and Space – Multiple Choicestrength of a tornado by assessing which of the following?W) Winds of the tornadoX) Minimum barometric pressure of the tornado Y) Vorticity of the tornadoZ) Damage left behind from the tornadoANSWER: Z) DAMAGE LEFT BEHIND FROM THE TORNADOMeteorologists use the Enhanced Fujita Scale to determine theRound 7APage 7
TOSS-UP15) Energy – Short Answer High power density, low electrical energy capacity, and long cycle life describe what type of battery found in most cars in the United States?ANSWER: LEAD ACID BATTERYBONUS15) Energy – Short Answer If a solar farm has a nameplate capacity of 50 mega-watts, what is its capacity factor, to the nearest tenth, if it generates an average of 40 mega-watts for 12 hours each day?ANSWER: 0.4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP16) Chemistry – Multiple Choice Which of the following methods would be most accurate when determining the molecular weight of a polymer?W) Freezing-point depression analysis X) GravimetryY) TitrationZ) OsmometryANSWER: Z) OSMOMETRY16) Chemistry – Short Answercoordination number of each chromium atom in this lattice?ANSWER: 8BONUSChromium metal crystallizes in a body-centered cubic lattice. What is theRound 7A Page 8
TOSS-UP17) Math – Short Answer For the equation y = 15 + 45 times log base 10 of open parenthesis 10x close parenthesis, where x is the number of years after 2000, find the value of y in 2010.ANSWER: y = 105BONUS17) Math – Short Answer Find the smallest three-digit positive integer not ending in zero such that the product of the digits is double the square of the ones-digit.  ANSWER: 121~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~TOSS-UP18) Biology – Multiple Choice Which of the following diseases is caused by a virus?W) AcneX) ShinglesY) ImpetigoZ) Necrotizing fasciitis [fash-ee-eye-tis]ANSWER: X) SHINGLESBONUS18) Biology – Multiple Choice Which of the following compounds would one use to detect the presence of DNA in an agarose gel?W) Ethidium bromide [eth-ih-dee-um broh-myde] X) Coomassie Blue [coo-mah-see]Y) Rhodamine 2 [row-duh-meen]Z) Fluorescein [flow-ruh-seen]ANSWER: W) ETHIDIUM BROMIDERound 7APage 9
TOSS-UP19) Physics – Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true regarding semiconductors?W) Doping is used to modulate the electrical properties of a semiconductor X) Silica glass is a semiconductorY) Silicon is the most commonly used semiconductor in electronicsZ) Light emitting diodes can be made of semiconductorsANSWER: X) SILICA GLASS IS A SEMICONDUCTORBONUS19) Physics – Multiple Choice A 50 gram ball moving to the right at 4 meters per second overtakes and collides perfectly elastically with a 100 gram ball moving to the right at 2 meters per second. Which of the following is true after the collision?W) Both balls are moving to the left at 1.33 meters per second and 3.33 meters per second, respectively X) Both balls are moving to the right at 1.33 meters per second and 3.33 meters per second, respectively Y) Both balls are moving to the left at 1.66 and 3.00 meters per second, respectivelyZ) Both balls are moving to the right at 1.66 and 3.00 meters per second, respectivelyANSWER: X) BOTH BALLS ARE MOVING TO THE RIGHT AT 1.33 AND 3.33 METERS PER SECOND, RESPECTIVELY                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~20) Energy – Multiple ChoiceW) GeothermalX) CoalY) Natural GasZ) Hydrothermal energyANSWER: Y) NATURAL GAS20) Energy – Multiple Choice climate change?TOSS-UPWhich of the following types of fuel is extracted by hydraulic fracturing?BONUSWhich of the following represents a negative feedback process regardingW) Increasing temperature of the Earth causes more water vapor to enter the atmosphereX) As ice melts, the albedo of the Earth decreasesY) As the temperature of the Earth increases, more radiation is radiated into spaceZ) As the temperature of the Earth increases, methane clathrates release more methane into the atmosphereANSWER: Y) AS THE TEMPERATURE OF THE EARTH INCREASES, MORE RADIATION IS RADIATED INTO SPACERound 7A Page 10
TOSS-UP21) Biology – Multiple Choice If a protein contains a signal peptide, in which of the following locations would it LEAST likely be found?W) CytosolX) Golgi Body Y) Rough ER Z) LysosomeANSWER: W) CYTOSOL21) Biology – Multiple Choicebetter in dim light when compared to diurnal animals?22) Earth and Space – Multiple Choice front?W) Wind direction shiftX) Drop in relative humidity Y) Drop in barometric pressure Z) Clearing skiesTOSS-UPWhich of the following does not occur after the passage of a coldBONUSWhich of the following eye adaptations allows nocturnal animals to seeW) Relatively higher numbers of cone cellsX) Presence of a tapetum [tuh-pee-tum] that reflects rather than absorbs light Y) Chemically distinctive vitreous humor that better supports the retinaZ) A less convex lens that facilities an ideal focal length in dim lightANSWER: X) PRESENCE OF A TAPETUM THAT REFLECTS RATHER THAN ABSORBS LIGHT                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ANSWER: Y) DROP IN BAROMETRIC PRESSUREBONUS22) Earth and Space – Short Answer What is the name for the opening found on the surface of volcanic systems that vents volcanic gases?ANSWER: FUMAROLERound 7A Page 11
TOSS-UP23) Chemistry – Short Answer For a given reaction, the rate constant is equal to 93 liters squared per moles squared per second. What is the order of this reaction?ANSWER: THREEBONUS23) Chemistry – Short Answer A closed vessel contains nitrogen gas, oxygen gas, and nitrogen dioxide gas. Nitrogen dioxide has a positive enthalpy of formation. Identify all of the following three changes that would shift the equilibrium to the products: 1) Increasing the temperature; 2) Increasing the pressure by adding nitrogen dioxide gas; 3) Increasing the pressure by adding an inert gas.ANSWER: 1Round 7A Page 12