ROUND ROBIN 1 TOSS-UP1) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Living organisms are often divided into five Kingdoms. In which of the 5 Kingdoms would E. coli be classified?ANSWER: MONERABONUS1) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the binomial scientific genus and species name for humans?ANSWER: HOMO SAPIENSTOSS-UP2) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer The Triassic, Jurassic, and Cretaceous are all periods in what era?ANSWER: MESOZOICBONUS2) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the correct term for a large crack in ice:W) creviceX) chasmY) canyonZ) crevasse (PRONOUNCE: crah-VAHSS)ANSWER: Z) CREVASSEJunior National Science Bowl Round Robin 1 Page 1TOSS-UP3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the density given as specific gravity, of a one centimeter cube of a metal that weighs 5 grams:W) .5 X) 5 Y) 2 Z) .2ANSWER: X) 5BONUS3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following has the greatest density:W) 10 kilogram of pure water X) 10 kilogram of aluminum Y) 2 kilogram of silverZ) 1 kilogram of goldANSWER: Z) 1 KILOGRAM OF GOLDTOSS-UP4) MATH Short Answer Peter bought a soda from a vending machine with a dollar bill. The soda cost 35 cents. What is the smallest number of coins he could receive in change if pennies are not included?ANSWER: FOURBONUS4) MATH Short Answer What is the integer value of 105 divided by 103?ANSWER: 100 (DO NOT ACCEPT: 102)Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 1 Page 2TOSS-UP5) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Rickets, which was a common disease in the early twentieth century, is caused by a deficiency in what vitamin:W) riboflavin X) vitamin B12 Y) vitamin K Z) vitamin DANSWER: Z) VITAMIN DBONUS5) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Exposure to sunlight converts cholesterol found in human skin into what vitamin?ANSWER: VITAMIN DTOSS-UP6) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is present only where benthic organisms reside:W) phytoplanktonX) zooplanktonY) diatomsZ) deep sea ventsANSWER: Z) DEEP SEA VENTSBONUS6) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the rapid rise of coastal water that accompanies the arrival of a cyclone?ANSWER: TIDAL SURGE (ACCEPT: STORM OR BASAL SURGE)TOSS-UP7) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following metals is attracted to a magnet?W) goldX) silverY) ironZ) aluminumANSWER: Y) IRON7) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice as wood and paper with oxygen to produce carbon dioxide, water and heat is called:W) fissionX) fusionY) endothermic Z) combustionANSWER: Z) COMBUSTION8) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Metamorphism transforms limestone into a metamorphic rock called:W) quartzite X) marble Y) hornfel Z) graniteANSWER: X) MARBLEBONUSMultiple Choice The reaction of hydrocarbons found in such thingsTOSS-UPBONUS8) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What are the icicle-shaped deposits of limestone hanging from the roof of a cave called:ANSWER: STALACTITESJunior National Science Bowl Round Robin 1 Page 4TOSS-UP9) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the region of the body where the stapes bone is located:W) ankle X) ear Y) wrist Z) kneeANSWER: X) EARBONUS9) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Sharks belong the class Chondricthyes because they have a skeleton made of what substance?ANSWER: CARTILAGETOSS-UP10) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Engineers in the USA often report pressure in PSI’s. What does the abbreviation PSI stand for?ANSWER: POUNDS per SQUARE INCHBONUS10) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which planet does not have an element named after it?W) Uranus X) MarsY) Mercury Z) PlutoANSWER: X) MARSJunior National Science BowlRound Robin 1Page 5TOSS-UP11) MATH Multiple Choice A parallelogram whose adjacent sides are unequal is a:W) deltoid X) rectangle Y) rhomboid Z) monogramANSWER: Y) RHOMBOIDBONUS11) MATH Short Answer Solve the following equation: 9x – 13 = 14 ANSWER: 3TOSS-UP12) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer On the Centigrade temperature scale give the whole number value that is the closest to absolute zero.ANSWER: MINUS 273BONUS12) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT seen by reflection of sun light:W) the moon X) MercuryY) MarsZ) the north starANSWER: Z) THE NORTH STARJunior National Science BowlRound Robin 1Page 6TOSS-UP13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Metals that can be hammered into thin sheets are called:W) malleable X) ductileY) moltenZ) pureANSWER: W) MALLEABLEBONUS13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A white-colored object illuminated by a blue light will appear as what color to the human eye?ANSWER: BLUETOSS-UP14) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an intracellular parasite:W) malariaX) sleeping sickness Y) tapewormZ) shigellaANSWER: W) MALARIABONUS14) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice In mammals, what teeth are evolved primarily to function in gripping and tearingW) incissors X) canines Y) molars Z) wisdomANSWER: X) CANINESJunior National Science BowlRound Robin 1Page 7TOSS-UP15) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Each day, most coastal beaches encounter:W) one high tide and one low tideX) two high tides and one low tideY) two high tides and two low tides Z) three high tides and three low tidesANSWER: Y) TWO HIGH TIDES AND TWO LOW TIDESBONUS15) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a metamorphic rock:W) sandstone X) graniteY) quartzZ) marbleANSWER: Z) MARBLE16) MATH Short Answer What is the cube root of 8? ANSWER: 2BONUS16) MATH Short Answer Solve the following equation: 3x + 15 = -12 ANSWER: -9TOSS-UPJunior National Science Bowl Round Robin 1 Page 8TOSS-UP17) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer At its greatest possible brightness, which is the brightest planet in the night sky?ANSWER: VENUSBONUS17) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The largest of the suns planets are:W) Venus and MarsX) Jupiter and Saturn Y) Neptune and Pluto Z) Mercury and UranusANSWER: X) JUPITER AND SATURNTOSS-UP18) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple choice By our current estimations, the Earth is approximately how many billions of years old:W) 8.4 X) 6.2 Y) 4.6 Z) 2.4ANSWER: Y) 4.6BONUS18) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The Earth's mantle is approximately how many miles thick:W) 1000 X) 1200 Y) 1500 Z) 1800ANSWER: Z) 1800Junior National Science BowlRound Robin 1Page 9TOSS-UP19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of these organisms in not a kind of worm?W) planerian X) flukeY) leechZ) centipedeANSWER: Z) CENTIPEDE20) MATH Multiple Choice Four divided by zero is:W) 4X) undefined Y) 0Z) infinityANSWER: X) UNDEFINED20) MATH Short Answer Find the value of x2 – y2 when x = -5 and y = -2: ANSWER: 21Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 1Page 10BONUS19) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the common specific name for the bond that joins two amino acids to form a growing protein:ANSWER: PEPTIDE BONDTOSS-UPBONUSTOSS-UP21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the common scientific term for the ratio of the density of a material to that of water at 4°cANSWER: SPECIFIC GRAVITYBONUS21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Starch is made of what simple sugar?W) fructose X) mannose Y) glucose Z) riboseANSWER: Y) GLUCOSETOSS-UP22) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer A large mass of ice, formed on land by the compaction and recrystallization of snow, that is moving downhill or outward under the force of gravity is called:ANSWER: A GLACIERBONUS22) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice A flat-topped plateau bordered on all sides by cliffs is called a:W) hillock X) butte Y) drumlin Z) karstANSWER: X) BUTTEJunior National Science BowlRound Robin 1Page 11TOSS-UP23) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer How many microgams are in a single milligram? ANSWER: 1000BONUS23) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The moon moves around the earth traveling primarily:W) east to west X) north to south Y) west to east Z) south to northANSWER: Y) WEST TO EASTTOSS-UP24) MATH Short Answer If a ≠ 0 (read as: a does not equal 0), what is the multiplicative inverse of a?ANSWER: 1a24) MATH Short Answer What is the square root of 169?ANSWER: 13 BONUSJunior National Science Bowl Round Robin 1 Page 12TOSS-UP25) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple choice The Tropic of Cancer lies at which of the following latitudes:W) 23 1⁄2° North X) 23 1⁄2° South Y) 26 1⁄2° North Z) 26 1⁄2° SouthANSWER: W) 23 1⁄2° NORTHBONUS25) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Magma that reached the Earth’s surface is called what? ANSWER: LAVAJunior National Science Bowl Round Robin 1 Page 13