ROUND ROBIN 4 TOSS-UP
1) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A child�s seesaw would be considered:
W) a complex machine
X) a form of inclined plane Y) a compound lever
Z) a class 1 lever
ANSWER: Z) A CLASS ONE LEVER
BONUS
1) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A 100-watt light bulb is lighted by a 100 volt power source. What is the current, in amperes, running through the bulb?
ANSWER: 1 AMPERE
(Solution: current = watts/volts; 100/100 = 1 ampere)
TOSS-UP
2) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the scientific name for the part of the human brain where higher brain operations occur such as thinking, imagination, mathematical reasoning and language:
W) cerebral cortex
X) cerebellum
Y) medulla oblongata Z) hypothalamus
ANSWER: W) CEREBRAL CORTEX
BONUS
2) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the common botanical term for the response a cell or plant has towards or away from a stimulus?
ANSWER: TAXIS
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 4 Page 1
TOSS-UP
3) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What layer of the Sun�s atmosphere is immediately interior to the corona?
ANSWER: THE CHROMOSPHERE
BONUS
3) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer How many angstroms are in 1 micron? ANSWER: 10,000
TOSS-UP
4) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the joint that is formed by the articulation of the tibia, fibula, and femur?
W) wrist X) knee Y) elbow Z) ankle
ANSWER: X) KNEE
4) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice occurs normally in:
W) venules X) arterioles Y) veins
Z) capillaries
ANSWER: Z) CAPILLARIES
Junior National Science Bowl
Round Robin 4
Page 2
BONUS
Multiple Choice The exchange of gases between blood and the tissue
TOSS-UP
5) MATH Short Answer What does 12 times 13 divided by 2 equal? ANSWER: 78
BONUS
5) MATH Short Answer Four factorial equals what number? ANSWER: 24
TOSS-UP
6) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer During which month does the vernal equinox occur? ANSWER: MARCH
BONUS
6) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer The temperature at which the relative humidity reaches 100% and condensation starts is called the:
ANSWER: DEW POINT
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 4 Page 3
TOSS-UP
7) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Sigmund Freud proposed the idea that the subconscious mind exited in three separate divisions two of which he called the ego and the superego. What was the third?
ANSWER: THE ID
BONUS
7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Galaxies are:
W) clouds of gases around stars X) clusters of billion of stars Y) rare in the universe
Z) always spherical in shape
ANSWER: X) CLUSTERS OF BILLION OF STARS
TOSS-UP
8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer The amount of heat needed to increase the temperature of 1.00 gram of water from 14.5�C to 15.5�C is defined as what unit of measurement?
ANSWER: CALORIE
BONUS
8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the chemical formula for hydrogen peroxide? ANSWER: H2O2
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 4 Page 4
TOSS-UP
9) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following minerals best illustrates the property of cleavage:
W) quartz X) diamond Y) topaz
Z) mica
ANSWER: Z) MICA

BONUS
9) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Based on how it was formed, slate is classified as what type of rock:
W) igneous
X) sedimentary Y) metamorphic Z) volcanic
ANSWER: Y) METAMORPHIC
TOSS-UP
10) MATH Short Answer What is the name of the famous theorem of geometry that states the sum of the squares of a right triangle is equal to the square of the hypotenuse?
ANSWER: PYTHAGOREAN THEOREM (ACCEPT: PYTHAGOREAN OR PYTHAGORAS
BONUS
10) MATH Short Answer What is the following Roman Numeral number equal to in an Arabic number: MCMLXI
ANSWER: 1961
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 4 Page 5
TOSS-UP
11) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The mass of a quantity of matter divided by its volume provides which specific property?
W) weight
X) specific gravity Y) density
Z) malleability
ANSWER: Y) DENSITY

12) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What are the four main human blood types? ANSWER: O, A, B, AND AB
BONUS
11) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Assuming friction is negligible, if a lever has a mechanical advantage of 5, how much effort in newtons is needed to lift a 10 newton load?
ANSWER: 2 NEWTONS
(Solution: Force = resistance / mechanical advantage)
TOSS-UP
12) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice In 1665, what person, using a microscope he built, observed perforations in plant stems, which he called cells:
W) Robert Hooke
X) Anton Van Leewenhoek Y) Carolus Linnaeus
Z) Theodor Schwann
ANSWER: W) ROBERT HOOKE
BONUS
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 4 Page 6
TOSS-UP
13) MATH Short Answer Solve the following equation: 6x = -8 ANSWER: -48
BONUS
13) MATH Short Answer Find the area of a circle when the radius equals 10: ANSWER: 314
(Solution: A = �r2)
TOSS-UP
14) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the phenomenon that causes an accumulation of heat in the lower atmosphere because of the absorption of long wavelength radiation from the Earth's surface?
ANSWER: GREENHOUSE EFFECT
BONUS
14) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer A meteor that reaches the surface of the Earth is more accurately called a:
ANSWER: METEORITE
 Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 4 Page 7
TOSS-UP
15) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the region of the body where the thyroid gland is located:
W) neck
X) abdomen Y) brain
Z) arm pit
ANSWER: W) NECK
BONUS
15) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Encephalitis is an inflammation of what organ? ANSWER: BRAIN
TOSS-UP
16) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Ring, Helix, Dumbbell and Veil are all names of what specific type of heavenly bodies?
ANSWER: NEBULA
BONUS
16) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Rounded to the nearest whole number, what is the temperature in Fahrenheit of a substance at 100�C ?
ANSWER: 212�
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 4 Page 8
TOSS-UP
17) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Which equinox marks the moment when fall begins in the Northern Hemisphere?
ANSWER: AUTUMNAL EQUINOX
BONUS
17) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Underwater volcanoes that have a flat top are called:
W) seamounts
X) island arcs
Y) abyssal mountains Z) guyots
ANSWER: Z) GUYOTS
TOSS-UP
18) MATH Short Answer What is the smallest two-digit whole number? ANSWER: 10
BONUS
18) MATH Short Answer On your first math test you scored a 56% and on the second test you scored 70%. By what percentage did you increase your score?
ANSWER: 25%
(Solution = 70-56= 14, 14/56=25%)
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 4 Page 9
TOSS-UP
19) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What term do physicists and engineers use most commonly to describe a change in the velocity of an object?
ANSWER: ACCELERATION
BONUS
19) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which list is out of order of closest to furthest distance from the sun:
W) Mercury, Venus, Earth X) Jupiter, Saturn, Neptune Y) Venus, Mars, Earth
Z) Mercury, Jupiter, Pluto
ANSWER: Y) VENUS, MARS, EARTH
TOSS-UP
20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A color made from the addition of two primary colors is called a:
ANSWER: SECONDARY COLOR
BONUS
20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice At 100 degrees Fahrenheit, which of the following substances would feel hottest to touch?
W) wood X) water Y) sand Z) gold
ANSWER: Z) GOLD
Junior National Science Bowl
Round Robin 4
Page 10
TOSS-UP
21) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer In a compound light microscope, the lens closest to the specimen is usually called the
ANSWER: OBJECTIVE
BONUS
21) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the nearest star to Earth in the Milky Way? ANSWER: THE SUN
TOSS-UP
22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What property of waves allows them to bend around the edges of obstacle:
W) reflection X) diffraction Y) deflection Z) dispersion
ANSWER: X) DIFFRACTION
BONUS
22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer For a toaster that draws 12 amps on a 120 volt line, what is the resistance of the toaster?
ANSWER: 10 OHMS
(Solution: I = V/R, R = V/I, R = 120/12 =10)
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 4 Page 11
TOSS-UP
23) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is not a case of symbiosis:
W) parasitism
X) commensalism Y) mutualism
Z) formatism
ANSWER: Z) FORMATISM
BONUS
23) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the protein which is primarily responsible for the varying shades of color in human skin and increases in production after exposure to sunlight.
ANSWER: MELANIN
TOSS-UP
24) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of a mixture of molten rock, suspended mineral grains, and dissolved gases that forms within the crust or mantle of the Earth when temperatures are sufficiently high:
ANSWER: MAGMA (DO NOT ACCEPT: LAVA) (Solution: magma becomes lava when it erupts at the surface )
BONUS
24) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice In what geological period did the first organisms with shells first become abundant:
W) Precambrian X) Cambrian
Y) Devonian
Z) Permian
ANSWER: X) CAMBRIAN
Junior National Science Bowl
Round Robin 4
Page 12
TOSS-UP
25) MATH Short Answer What is the standard formula for the surface area of a sphere? ANSWER: 4�r2
BONUS
25) MATH Short Answer Multiply the following 5 numbers: (-2)(-5)(-4)(-3)(-1) ANSWER: -120
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 4 Page 13
