ROUND ROBIN 3 TOSS-UP
1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Vestigial (pronounced VES-ti-gee-al) structures:
W) have no known function in their present owners X) function in an analogous fashion in all species Y) evolve homologously until functional
Z) control nervous system functions
ANSWER: W) HAVE NO KNOWN FUNCTION IN THEIR PRESENT OWNERS
BONUS
1) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Mallus ioeusis and Mallus sylvestris are the genera and species of what common tree?
ANSWER: APPLE
TOSS-UP
2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the decibel scale most often used to measure?
W) size of bells
X) magnitude of hurricanes Y) loudness of a sound
Z) brightness of lights
ANSWER: Y) LOUDNESS OF A SOUND
BONUS
46) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the name of the lowest energy subshell of an atom where electrons are found:
W) s X) p Y) d Z) a
ANSWER: W) S
Junior National Science Bowl
Round Robin 3
Page 1
TOSS-UP
3) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following are the highest of the clouds in the troposphere and are composed entirely of ice crystals:
W) stratus
X) cirrus
Y) cumulus
Z) altocumulus
ANSWER: X) CIRRUS

BONUS
3) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice In the Northern Hemisphere, when is the Earth the greatest distance from the sun:
W) winter X) spring Y) summer Z) fall
ANSWER: Y) SUMMER
TOSS-UP
4) MATH Short Answer The identity element for addition is what number? ANSWER: 0
BONUS
4) MATH Short Answer On a math test, 20 students averaged a score of 80% while 10 students averaged 90%. To the nearest whole number, what is the mean score of the entire class?
ANSWER: 83%
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 3 Page 2
TOSS-UP
5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following units is used to measure electric current:
W) voltage X) ohms Y) amperes Z) watts
ANSWER: Y) AMPERES
BONUS
5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the current, in amperes, running through a 200-watt light bulb running on a 100 volt power source.
ANSWER: 2 AMPERE
(Solution: current = watts/volts; 200/100 = 2 ampere)
TOSS-UP
6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the scientific term often used by astronomers and geoscientists that refers to the point directly overhead?
ANSWER: ZENITH
BONUS
6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The light year is a useful unit of measure for the distance between:
W) planets X) stars
Y) atoms Z) asteroids
ANSWER: X) STARS

Page 3
TOSS-UP
7) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following parts of a plant produces pollen:
W) petal X) stamen Y) pistil Z) sepal
ANSWER: X) STAMEN

BONUS
7) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Plant cells differ from animal cells in that only plant cells possess:
W) a nucleus
X) mitochondria Y) a cell wall
Z) lysosomes
ANSWER: Y) A CELL WALL
TOSS-UP
8) MATH Short Answer Solve the following equation: 3x = -12 4
ANSWER: -16
BONUS
8) MATH Short Answer Convert the periodic decimal 0.8333 or 0.83 �bar� into a fraction: ANSWER: 5/6
 Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 3 Page 4
TOSS-UP
9) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice When, in the geological time scale, did dinosaurs roam the Earth in large numbers:
W) Jurassic X) Triassic Y) Cretaceous Z) Tertiary
ANSWER: W) JURASSIC
BONUS
9) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Meteor showers are composed of:
W) large pieces of falling rocks
X) dust and other debris from comets Y) falling stars
Z) solar flares
ANSWER: X) DUST AND OTHER DEBRIS FROM COMETS
TOSS-UP
10) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Rounded to the nearest whole number, how many centimeters are in 2 inches ?
ANSWER: 5
BONUS
10) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of comets:
W) they have highly elliptical orbits around the sun
X) they leave a trail of particles that reflect sun light
Y) they are made of rocks and condensed gases
Z) they can only be seen when they pass through the atmosphere
ANSWER: Z) THEY CAN ONLY BE SEEN WHEN THEY PASS THROUGH THE A TMOSPHERE
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 3 Page 5
TOSS-UP
11) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the apparent force that causes hurricanes to be deflected to the right in the Northern hemisphere and to the left in the Southern hemisphere?
ANSWER: THE CORIOLIS EFFECT (ACCEPT: CORIOLIS FORCE)
BONUS
11) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The supercontinent Pangea started to break apart into our present day continents approximately how many million years ago:
W) 100 X) 200 Y) 300 Z) 400
ANSWER: X) 200
TOSS-UP
12) MATH Short Answer Add the following numbers: 0.5 + 0.05 + 0.005 ANSWER: 0.555
BONUS
12) MATH Short Answer Remove the grouping symbols in the following expression: -3x(2 � 5z)
ANSWER: -6x + 15xz (ACCEPT: 15xz � 6x)
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 3 Page 6
TOSS-UP
13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the least dense at standard temperature and pressure:
W) 10 kilogram of pure water X) 10 kilogram of aluminum Y) 2 kilogram of silver
Z) 1 kilogram of gold
ANSWER: W) 10 kilogram of pure water
BONUS
13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer How many electron does the s subshell of an atom hold?
ANSWER: 2
TOSS-UP
14) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the scientific name for the knee cap:
W) fibula X) malleus Y) patella Z) scapula
ANSWER: Y) PATELLA
BONUS
14) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Organize the following 3 tooth layers from the outermost to the innermost of a tooth: dentin, enamel, pulp
ANSWER: ENAMEL, DENTIN, PULP
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 3 Page 7
TOSS-UP
15) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer How much does one cubic centimeter of water weigh at standard temperature and pressure?
ANSWER: 1 gram
BONUS
15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Craters on the moon is evidence of :
W) lakes that once existed X) visits from other life
forms
Y) asteroid impacts Z) plate tectonics
ANSWER: Y) ASTEROID IMPACTS

16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice All metals:
W) melt at high temperatures X) conduct heat and electricity Y) contain iron
Z) react with air and water
ANSWER: X) CONDUCT HEAT AND ELECTRICITY
TOSS-UP
16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The particles in an atom that determine which element it is are the:
W) nuclei X) electrons Y) neutrons Z) protons
ANSWER: Z) PROTONS
BONUS
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 3 Page 8
TOSS-UP
17) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following parts of a cell is most directly responsible for synthesizing proteins:
W) ribosomes
X) endoplasmic reticulum Y) vacuoles
Z) lysosomee
ANSWER: W) RIBOSOMES
BONUS
17) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer This structure that develops in the wall of the uterus functions in the pregnant mammals to transfer nourishment and oxygen and remove wastes from the developing offspring.
ANSWER: PLACENTA
TOSS-UP
18) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Which equinox marks the beginning of spring in the Northern Hemisphere?
ANSWER: VERNAL EQUINOX
BONUS
18) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Steep-sided volcanoes such as Mounts Rainier, Hood, and Fuji, are examples of what kind of volcanoes:
W) stratovolcanoes
X) tephra cone volcanoes Y) shield volcanoes
Z) tower volcanoes
ANSWER: W) STRATOVOLCANOES
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 3 Page 9
TOSS-UP
19) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The Sahara Desert in Africa is what type of desert?
W) subtropical X) continental Y) rain shadow Z) coastal
ANSWER: W) SUBTROPICAL

BONUS
19) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What are the 4 physical states of matter? ANSWER: SOLID, LIQUID, GAS, PLASMA
TOSS-UP
20) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the scientific name for the thigh bone:
W) tibia
X) femur Y) fibula Z) humerus
ANSWER: X) FEMUR
BONUS
20) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer When a nerve message reaches the end of an axon it sends a message or impulse across the space between the nerves to continue its message to the next nerve. What is the space across which the message is sent usually called?
ANSWER: SYNAPSE
Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 3 Page 10
TOSS-UP
21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice When a car turns a corner on dry pavement, the wheels do not slide sideways and the car completes the turn due to what interaction between the tires and the pavement?
W) friction
X) torque
Y) drag
Z) acceleration
ANSWER: W) FRICTION
21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Complex carbohydrates are called:
W) polypeptides X) polynuclides Y) polypropylenes Z) polysaccharides
ANSWER: Z) POLYSACCHARIDES
22) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following numbers is divisible by 3:
W) 5,163 X) 2,465 Y) 1,315 Z) 313
ANSWER: W) 5,163
Junior National Science Bowl
Round Robin 3
Page 11
BONUS
TOSS-UP
22) MATH Short Answer What kind of fraction has the absolute value of the numerator greater than the denominator?
ANSWER: IMPROPER FRACTION
BONUS
TOSS-UP
23) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer With a Mohs� hardness of 1, what is the softest mineral known?
ANSWER: TALC
BONUS
23) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The first scientist to propose the hypothesis of the past existence of the supercontinent Pangea was:
W) James Hutton
X) John Filmore Hayford Y) Charles Darwin
Z) Alfred Wegener
ANSWER: Z) ALFRED WEGENER
TOSS-UP
24) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What vitamin is the most directly associated with the disease scurvy?
ANSWER: VITAMIN C
BONUS
24) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the best estimate of what a gallon of water weighs in kilograms?
W) 2 kilograms X) 4 kilograms Y) 6 kilograms Z) 8 kilograms
ANSWER: X) 4 KILOGRAMS
Junior National Science Bowl
Round Robin 3
Page 12
TOSS-UP
25) MATH Short Answer What is the name for a set that contains no elements? ANSWER: EMPTY SET
BONUS
25) MATH Short Answer Solve the following expression: 2 25 + 25 � 5 ANSWER: 15
 Junior National Science Bowl Round Robin 3
Page 13
