ROUND 13A          TOSS-UP1) MATH Multiple Choice In 2014, January 1st fell on a Wednesday. What is the next year that January 1st will fall on a Wednesday?W) 2015 X) 2019 Y) 2020 Z) 2025ANSWER: Y) 2020BONUS1) MATH Short Answer The sums of three whole numbers taken in pairs are 11, 13, and 16. What is the product of these three numbers?ANSWER: 252 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP2) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice During which of the following phases of an action potential do voltage-gated sodium channels begin to close?W) Rising phaseX) Falling phaseY) After hyperpolarization Z) Refractory periodANSWER: X) FALLING PHASEBONUS2) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In humans, in addition to transferring antibodies, colostrum also stimulates the development of the neonatal gut through the transference of which of the following?W) PheromonesX) Non-heritable mutations Y) Beta-galactoseZ) Growth factorsANSWER: Z) GROWTH FACTORSHigh School Round 13APage 1
TOSS-UP3) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Halogenation [hal-uh-juh-NAY-shuhn] will occur fastest between methane and the radical of which of the following elements?W) Chlorine X) IodineY) Fluorine Z) BromineANSWER: Y) FLUORINEBONUS3) CHEMISTRY Short Answer In terms of the ideal gas constant R, what is the constant- pressure heat capacity, per mole, of a monatomic ideal gas?ANSWER: 5/2 R (ACCEPT: 2.5 R) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP4) PHYSICS Multiple Choice An antihydrogen atom is made of what two components?W) An antiproton and a positron X) An antiproton and an electron Y) A proton and a positronZ) A proton and a neutrinoANSWER: W) AN ANTIPROTON AND A POSITRONBONUS4) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A capillary tube with an inner radius of 0.1 millimeter is partially dipped in a liquid with a surface tension of 0.1 newtons per meter, with approximately 0 degrees of contact angle. The density of the liquid is approximately the same as that of water. Calculate the liquid rise in the tube.W) 2 millimeter X) 2 centimeter Y) 20 centimeter Z) 2 meterANSWER: Y) 20 cmHigh School Round 13APage 2
TOSS-UP5) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice At a latitude of 45 degrees, which of the following is closest to the percentage of astronomical sources that are circumpolar?W) 0% X) 30% Y) 50% Z) 100%ANSWER: X) 30%W) Prophase I X) Prophase II Y) Metaphase I Z) Anaphase IIANSWER: W) PROPHASE IBONUS5) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice A poikiloblastic [poi-kil-uh-BLAS-tik] texture is characterized by which of the following?W) Idioblasts embedded within a fine matrixX) Homogeneously [hoh-muh-JEE-nee-uhs-li] xenoblastic with little to no evidence of additional alteration mineralsY) Fine, phyllitic [fi-LIT-ik] foliation accompanied by porphyroblasts [por-FI-roh-blasts] Z) Inclusions from other minerals enveloped during porphyroblast growthANSWER: Z) INCLUSIONS FROM OTHER MINERALS ENVELOPED DURING PORPHYROBLAST GROWTH           _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following phases of meiosis [my-OH-sis] is longest?BONUS6) BIOLOGY Short Answer Arrange the following three steps of cell respiration from lowest to highest in terms of net NADH molecules produced per one molecule of glucose entering respiration: 1) glycolysis [gly-KOL-uh-sis], 2) electron transport chain, 3) Krebs cycle.ANSWER: 2, 1, 3 (ACCEPT: ELECTRON TRANSPORT CHAIN, GLYCOLYSIS, KREBS CYCLE)High School Round 13A Page 3
TOSS-UP7) ENERGY Multiple Choice What major rock type is the medium for fracking?W) Schist [SHIST] X) ShaleY) BasaltZ) LimestoneANSWER: X) SHALEBONUS7) ENERGY Multiple Choice What substance was the primary fuel source for NASA space shuttles?W) PropaneX) Helium gasY) Liquid hydrogen Z) MethaneANSWER: Y) LIQUID HYDROGEN _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP8) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the full list of products produced by the mild heating of sodium bicarbonate at temperatures of about 80 degrees Celsius?W) Sodium oxide and carbon dioxideX) Sodium peroxide and carbon dioxideY) Sodium carbonate, water, and carbon dioxide Z) Sodium carbonate and carbon dioxideANSWER: Y) SODIUM CARBONATE, WATER, AND CARBON DIOXIDEBONUS8) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What rule is used to predict the aromaticity of conjugated alkenes?ANSWER: HUCKEL’S RULEHigh School Round 13APage 4
TOSS-UP9) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following does not interact with a magnetic field?W) A magnet at restX) Moving electric charges Y) A moving magnetZ) Electric charges at restANSWER: Z) ELECTRIC CHARGES AT RESTBONUS9) PHYSICS Multiple Choice The closest distance at which Gina can properly focus is 100 cm from her eye. The distance of normal vision is 0.25 m. Find the power in diopters [dy-OP-ters] of the converging lens for her eyeglass.W) -3 X) -0.03 Y) 0.03 Z) 3ANSWER: Z) 3 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following structures would have been most likely absent from the last shared common ancestor of osteichthyans [os-tee-IK-thee-uhns] and chondrichthyans [kan-DRIK-thee-ez]?W) TeethX) GillsY) ScalesZ) Swim bladderANSWER: Z) SWIM BLADDERBONUS10) BIOLOGY Short Answer Place the following four animals in order of lowest to highest energy cost per unit body weight for regulation of body temperature: python, canary, human, poodle.ANSWER: PYTHON, HUMAN, POODLE, CANARYHigh School Round 13A Page 5
TOSS-UP11) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following composes most of the insoluble residues of limestones?W) Calcite matrixX) Crystalline quartzY) Chert nodules [churt] Z) Clay mineralsANSWER: Y) CHERT NODULESBONUS11) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Long-term preservation of deep sea carbonates is rare because of which of the following?W) Most ocean crust and overlying sediments are subductedX) Carbonates readily dissolve along the ocean floor when exposed to seawaterY) There is little carbonate-forming material occurring in ocean waterZ) Carbonates react with silicates in the deep ocean, reducing the occurrence of carbonates along the ocean floorANSWER: W) MOST OCEAN CRUST AND OVERLYING SEDIMENTS ARE SUBDUCTED _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP12) CHEMISTRY Short Answer The van der Waals equation is an equation of state for real gases that contains two gas-dependent parameters, a and b. What state function from the ideal gas equation does the a parameter modify in the van der Waals equation?ANSWER: PRESSURE (ACCEPT: P)BONUS12) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following statements concerning the particle-in- a-box model is false?W) The potential well is approximated to be infinitely deepX) The ground state energy increases with the length of the box Y) The energy levels are quantizedZ) The energy of level n is proportional to n squaredANSWER: X) THE GROUND STATE ENERGY INCREASES WITH THE LENGTH OF THE BOXHigh School Round 13A Page 6
TOSS-UP13) MATH Multiple Choice If        [ two x divided by three minus x divided by six] is an   integer, which of the following MUST be true regarding x?W) x is negativeX) x is a multiple of two Y) x is a multiple of three Z) x is oddANSWER: X) x IS A MULTIPLE OF TWOBONUS13) MATH Short Answer What is the smallest positive integer that can be added to 2500 to get a perfect square?ANSWER: 101 ______________________________________________________TOSS-UP14) ENERGY Multiple Choice A 100 mile 765 kilovolt line carrying 1000 megawatts of energy can have losses ranging from 1.1% to 0.5%. Which of the following best approximates the losses as a ratio to the 1.0% of a 345 kilovolt line carrying the same load across the same distance?  W) 1/10 X) 1/4 Y) 4/1 Z) 10/1ANSWER: Y) 4/1BONUS14) ENERGY Short Answer If a single electric distribution line has a resistance of 1 ohm per 1000 meters and current at 50 amps, what will be the voltage reduction over a 10 kilometer run?ANSWER: 500High School Round 13A Page 7
TOSS-UP15) BIOLOGY Short Answer Identify all of the following three neurotransmitters that are considered to have only excitatory actions: 1) acetylcholine [uh-seet-l-KOH-leen], 2) GABA, 3) glutamate.ANSWER: 3 (ACCEPT: GLUTAMATE)BONUS15) BIOLOGY Short Answer What specific cell type in the stomach is responsible for production of hydrochloric acid in response to stimulation by gastrin?ANSWER: PARIETAL CELLS _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following organic functional groups does NOT exhibit sp2 [s-p-2] hybridization?W) KetonesX) Aldehydes [AL-duh-hyds] Y) AmidesZ) AminesANSWER: Z) AMINESBONUS16) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is true regarding the chemistry of the alkaline earth elements?W) Compounds of beryllium have the most covalent character X) Melting point increases as you go down the groupY) Atomic radius decreases as you go down the groupZ) Barium has a distinct red flame test colorANSWER: W) COMPOUNDS OF BERYLLIUM HAVE THE MOST COVALENT CHARACTERHigh School Round 13A Page 8
TOSS-UP17) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is TRUE?W)  7 is not a prime numberX)             [e to the power of quantity I times pi equals negative e to the power ofquantity negative I times pi]Y) All pairs of perpendicular lines in the Cartesian plane have slopes that are negative reciprocals of each otherZ) There is no number   such that log     [log of negative a] exists.ANSWER: W)  7 IS NOT A PRIME NUMBER BONUS17) MATH Short Answer If a circle is divided into 8 sectors whose central degree angles are integers that form an arithmetic sequence with first term 3, what is the common difference for the sequence?ANSWER: 12 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP18) PHYSICS Short Answer Assuming the heat of fusion for water is 80 calories per gram, what is the increase in entropy, in calories per Kelvin, for a 273 gram block of ice at 0 degrees Celsius when it melts?ANSWER: 80BONUS18) PHYSICS Multiple Choice An -particle [alpha particle] and a proton, both initially at rest, are accelerated through a potential difference of 105 kilovolts. Find the ratio (K/Kp) [k alpha over k proton] of their final kinetic energies.W) 1/4 X) 1/2 Y) 2 Z) 4ANSWER: Y) 2High School Round 13APage 9
TOSS-UP19) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice What will occur if a white dwarf in a binary exceeds its Roche [ROSH] lobe?W) Its companion will transfer mass to it until it shrinks below its Roche lobe X) It will form a planetary nebulaY) It will continue to expand and ablate onto its companionZ) It will transfer matter to its companion until it shrinks below its Roche lobeANSWER: Z) IT WILL TRANSFER MATTER TO ITS COMPANION UNTIL IT SHRINKS BELOW ITS ROCHE LOBEBONUS19) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following describes the carbonate compensation depth (CCD)?W) Occurring between 2,000-3,000 mX) Varying by latitude: deeper near the equator, shallower near the polesY) Restricted to waters near the poles in both hemispheresZ) The depth at which carbonates start to form at nearly two times the rate of formation in shallower waterANSWER: X) VARYING BY LATITUDE: DEEPER NEAR THE EQUATOR, SHALLOWER NEAR THE POLES           _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes the elementary kinetic step where a proton is transferred directly between an ammonium ion and water?W) Unimolecular X) Bimolecular Y) Trimolecular Z) TetramolecularANSWER: X) BIMOLECULARBONUS20) CHEMISTRY Short Answer One liter of a saturated solution of silver chromate contains 0.0002 moles of the silver cation [KAT-eye-uhn] and 0.00003 moles of the chromate ion. To two significant figures and in scientific notation, what is the Ksp of silver chromate?ANSWER: 1.2 x 10-12High School Round 13A Page 10
TOSS-UP21) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following vitamin deficiencies causes the condition known as “Pellagra”?W) Vitamin B3 X) Vitamin B6 Y) Vitamin B2 Z) Vitamin B1ANSWER: W) VITAMIN B3W) 1 X) 3 Y) 2 Z) 4ANSWER: Z) 4BONUS21) BIOLOGY Short Answer How many molecules of ATP are needed to synthesize two glucose molecules in the Calvin cycle?ANSWER: 36 ATP _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP22) ENERGY Multiple Choice Energy radiates from a surface as a function of temperature to what power?BONUS22) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following rare earth elements is used to produce magnets for wind turbines?W) EuropiumX) Gadolinium [gad-l-IN-ee-uhm] Y) ScandiumZ) NeodymiumANSWER: Z) NEODYMIUMHigh School Round 13APage 11
TOSS-UP23) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer A torus of sulfur and sodium has been detected along the orbit of which of Jupiter's moons?ANSWER: IOBONUS23) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Telescope A has an aperture with diameter 1 meter and telescope B has an aperture with diameter 2 meters. Both take diffraction-limited images to the same depth. What is the relationship between the smallest resolved angle and integration time of the two telescopes?W) Smallest resolved angle of A is twice that of B and integration time is four times that of B X) Smallest resolved angle of A is half that of B and integration time is four times that of B Y) Smallest resolved angle of A is half that of B and integration time is twice that of BZ) Smallest resolved angle of A is twice that of B and integration time is half that of BANSWER: W) SMALLEST RESOLVED ANGLE OF A IS TWICE THAT OF B AND INTEGRATION TIME IS FOUR TIMES THAT OF BHigh School Round 13A Page 12