ROUND 7A          TOSS-UP1) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice A sloppy chemist forgets to label two beakers. One contains barium chloride solution, and the other contains magnesium chloride solution. The chemist decides to add a third solution to each beaker in order to distinguish the two. Which of the following reagents would form a precipitate in only one of the two beakers?W) Sodium sulfateX) Sodium carbonate Y) Silver nitrateZ) Ammonium chlorideANSWER: W) SODIUM SULFATEBONUS1) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Rank, by name or number, the following three molecules or polyatomic ions from the one containing oxygen atoms in the least negative oxidation state, to the one containing oxygen atoms in the most negative oxidation state: 1) ozonide, 2) peroxide, 3) oxygen gas.ANSWER: 3, 1, 2 (ACCEPT: OXYGEN GAS, OZONIDE, PEROXIDE) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP2) BIOLOGY Short Answer In photorespiration, ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase [RY-byoo- lays bis-fos-FAYT kahr-BOK-suh-layz] binds what molecule instead of carbon dioxide?ANSWER: OXYGENBONUS2) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following would you NOT expect to experience during fasting or starvation?W) Increase in ketone body formationX) Decrease in plasma fatty acid levelsY) Depletion of glycogen [GLY-kuh-juhn]Z) Increased use of ketones for ATP production in the brainANSWER: X) DECREASE IN PLASMA FATTY ACID LEVELSHigh School Round 7APage 1
TOSS-UP3) ENERGYShort Answer What is the SI [S-I] unit used to measure capacitance, or the ability of a body to store an electrical charge?ANSWER: FARADBONUS3) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following foods has the highest energy density?W) Lean meat of a rabbit X) Cell wall of celeryY) Pericarp of an appleZ) Butter churned from milkANSWER: Z) BUTTER CHURNED FROM MILK _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP4) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Over a 720 minute period, through what angle in degrees does the Earth rotate?ANSWER: 180BONUS4) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following measures of natural disasters reflects only properties associated with the natural phenomenon and not damage to the human built environment?W) Moment Magnitude Scale X) Fujita ScaleY) Modified Mercalli ScaleZ) Saffir-Simpson ScaleANSWER: W) MOMENT MAGNITUDE SCALEHigh School Round 7APage 2
TOSS-UP5) MATH Short Answer What is the smallest possible value for the sum of a positive number and its own reciprocal?ANSWER: 2BONUS5) MATH Multiple Choice If a2 – 2ab + b2 = x, [A squared minus two A B plus B squared equals x] where a is an odd integer and b is an even integer, which of the following MUST be true about x?W) x is a prime numberX) x is divisible by 3Y) x is an even perfect square Z) x is an odd perfect squareANSWER: Z) x IS AN ODD PERFECT SQUARE _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) BIOLOGY Short Answer What general class of animal tissue is characterized by the presence of collagen?ANSWER: CONNECTIVEBONUS6) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following steroid hormones is the precursor to all of the others listed in the answer choices?W) EstroneX) TestosteroneY) ProgesteroneZ) Androstenedione [an-druh-steen-DY-ohn]ANSWER Y) PROGESTERONEHigh School Round 7APage 3
TOSS-UP7) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice You take an IR [I-R] spectrum that has a long, broad peak just below 3000 inverse centimeters. Which of the following is the likely identification of the molecule?W) Nonane [NO-nayn]X) Methylcyclopentane [meth-uhl-sy-kluh-PEN-tan] Y) HexeneZ) PentanolANSWER: Z) PENTANOLBONUS7) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following compounds is most thermodynamically unstable?W) Nitrogen trifluoride X) Nitrogen trichloride Y) Nitrogen tribromide Z) Nitrogen triiodideANSWER: Z) NITROGEN TRIIODIDE _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP8) PHYSICS Short Answer How much energy, in joules, does a circuit containing a 9 volt battery and a 6 ohm resistor dissipate over 8 seconds?ANSWER: 108BONUS8) PHYSICS Short Answer If the radius of a body is smaller than its Schwarzschild radius, the body becomes what?ANSWER: BLACK HOLEHigh School Round 7A Page 4
TOSS-UP9) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is true about kaolinite [KAY-uh-luh-nyt]?W) It has an inosilicate structure [in-uh-SIL-i-kayt]X) It has a high cation exchange capacity [KAT-eye-uhn]Y) It is a magnesium-rich silicate Z) It is a non-expanding clayANSWER: Z) IT IS A NON-EXPANDING CLAYBONUS9) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following meteorological sensors is not part of the suite of sensors on the Mars Rover Curiosity?W) Anemometer X) Thermometer Y) BarometerZ) PsychrometerANSWER: Z) PSYCHROMETER _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following animal cell junctions is most similar in function to plant cell plasmodesmata [plaz-muh-des-MUH-tuh]?W) Gap junctionX) Tight junctionY) DesmosomeZ) Adherens junctionANSWER: W) GAP JUNCTIONBONUS10) BIOLOGY Short Answer Luke Skywalker is looking for evidence about whether Darth Vader was his father. Luke has blood type A, and medical records show that his mother had blood type AB. What are all the possible blood types that Luke’s father could be?ANSWER: TYPES A, B, O, AB (SAYING “TYPES” IS NOT NECESSARY)High School Round 7A Page 5
TOSS-UP11) MATH Short Answer. Determine lim    . [the limit as x approaches zero of quantity xplus one divided by x] W) 40 Watts X) 54 Watts Y) 66 Watts Z) 70 WattsANSWER: X) 54 WATTS →   ANSWER: THE LIMIT DOES NOT EXIST (ACCEPT: NON-EXISTANT; DO NOT ACCEPT: INFINITY)BONUS11) MATH Multiple Choice Consider a circle in which a square is inscribed. Inscribed within that square is another circle. If the innermost circle has circumference of 12π, what is the area of the outermost circle?W) 64π X) 72π Y) 88π Z) 96πANSWER: X) 72π _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP12) ENERGYMultiple Choice What is the power generated by a circuit with a total current of 6 amperes running through two resistors in parallel, of 2 and 6 ohms?BONUS12) ENERGY Short Answer Consider a Carnot engine operating between two reservoirs [REZ- er-vwahrs] of different temperatures. If the temperatures in Kelvin of both reservoirs are doubled, by what factor is the efficiency multiplied?ANSWER: ONEHigh School Round 7A Page 6
TOSS-UP13) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following would be the most appropriate SN2 [S- N- two] leaving group?W) HydroxylX) O-Trifluoromethanesulfonate [try-FLOOR-oh-METH-ayn-SUHL-fuh-nayt] Y) O-EthylZ) O-AcylANSWER: X) O-TRIFLUOROMETHANESULFONATEBONUS13) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice What is a chief difference between an electrolytic cell and a galvanic cell?W) Galvanic cells convert electrical energy into chemical energy, electrolytic cells convert chemical energy into electrical energyX) Galvanic cells spontaneously produce an electrical current; an external voltage must be applied to an electrolytic cellY) Oxidation occurs at the anode for a galvanic cell and at the cathode for an electrolytic cell Z) Reduction occurs at the anode for a galvanic cell and at the cathode for an electrolytic cellANSWER: X) GALVANIC CELLS SPONTANEOUSLY PRODUCE AN ELECTRICAL CURRENT; AN EXTERNAL VOLTAGE MUST BE APPLIED TO AN ELECTROLYTIC CELL           _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP14) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following animals transfers oxygen to blood via a process called countercurrent exchange?W) GoldfishX) TarantulaY) Hummingbird Z) MoleANSWER: W) GOLDFISHBONUS14) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In a human, breathing air with too much carbon dioxide would lead to all of the following except:W) A reduction in oxygen carrying capacityX) A decrease in oxygen affinity for hemoglobinY) Facilitation of oxygen to tissuesZ) A rightward shift of the oxygen equilibrium curveANSWER: W) A REDUCTION IN OXYGEN CARRYING CAPACITYHigh School Round 7APage 7
TOSS-UP15) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is responsible for auroras occurring mainly in the polar regions?W) The moonX) Low temperaturesY) The geomagnetic fieldZ) The earth’s equatorial bulgeANSWER: Y) THE GEOMAGNETIC FIELDBONUS15) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Below the carbonate compensation depth, what sort of deep ocean ooze can no longer form?ANSWER: CALCAREOUS OOZE (ACCEPT: CALCIUM CARBONATE OOZE) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) ENERGYMultiple Choice In an adiabatic [ad-ee-uh-BAT-ik] process, in which direction does heat flow between the system and surroundings?W) Out of the systemX) Into the systemY) No heat flow into or out of the system Z) Through the system’s boundariesANSWER: Y) NO HEAT FLOW INTO OR OUT OF THE SYSTEMBONUS16) ENERGY Short Answer In a solar power tower system, what are the names of the mirrors that focus sunlight onto a pipe located at the focal line, heating up fluid inside and producing steam that drives a turbine?ANSWER: PARABOLIC TROUGHHigh School Round 7A Page 8
TOSS-UP17) MATH Short Answer A car leaves its original location traveling due west at a speed of 60 miles per hour and arrives at its destination in 3 hours. Later that day, the car returns to its original location. At what speed, in miles per hour, did it travel to cover the same distance in 2 hours?ANSWER: 90 MILES PER HOURBONUS17) MATH Short Answer. Simplify:          . [quantity log in base b of b raised to the power          of a raised to the power of b divided by quantity log in base a of a raised to the power of b, raised to the power of a]ANSWER: 1_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP18) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Two objects collide in a perfectly inelastic collision. Which of the following quantities is not conserved in the collision? W) Kinetic energy X) MomentumY) Potential energy Z) Total energyANSWER: W) KINETIC ENERGYBONUS18) PHYSICS Short Answer A Carnot [kahr-NOH] engine takes 2000 joules of heat from a reservoir at 500 kelvin, does some work, and then discards some heat to a reservoir [REZ-er- vwahr] at 300 kelvin. How much heat, in joules, is discarded by the Carnot engine?ANSWER: 1200 JOULES (DO NOT ACCEPT: -1200)High School Round 7A Page 9
TOSS-UP19) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice What disadvantage does the presence of introns and exons give eukaryotes [yoo-KAR-ee-ohts] when compared to other organisms?W) The ability to produce more proteins from the same primary transcript X) Greater stability during reproductionY) Lower error rate during replicationZ) Mutations are harder to detectANSWER: Z) MUTATIONS ARE HARDER TO DETECTBONUS19) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Over time, a large mountain range forms, separating two populations of squirrels for multiple generations. Which of the following pairs of terms best describes this speciation event?W) Anagenesis and allopatric speciation [an-uh-JEN-uh-sis]X) Cladogenesis and allopatric speciation [klad-uh-JEN-uh-sis] Y) Anagenesis and sympatric speciationZ) Cladogenesis and sympatric speciationANSWER: X) CLADOGENESIS AND ALLOPATRIC SPECIATION _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Lithium dialkylcuprates [dy-AL-kuh-KUHP-rayts] can be used in carbon-carbon bond-forming reactions and are usually known as what named reagent?W) Grignard X) Gilman Y) WittigZ) BirchANSWER: X) GILMANBONUS20) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Identify the enzyme that cleaves the first peptide bond at the C- terminal end of a peptide or protein and the organ where the enzyme is synthesized.ANSWER: CARBOXYPEPTIDASE; PANCREASHigh School Round 7A Page 10
TOSS-UP21) MATH Short Answer Differentiate the following expression with respect to  , provided x is not 0:   [ x over the quantity the absolute value of x].ANSWER: 0BONUS21) MATH Multiple Choice If f(x) =     [f of x equals the fraction with numerator one plus x  and denominator x], which of the following is equivalent to f(x)? W) f (-x) [f of negative x]X) f ( ) [f of the quantity one divided by x]Y) f (   ) [f of the quantity negative one divided by x]Z)        [the fraction with numerator f of the quantity one divided by x and denominator x]ANSWER: Z)        _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP22) PHYSICS Short Answer The statement that all points on a wavefront will serve as point sources for secondary wavelets is based on what principle?ANSWER: HUYGENS PRINCIPLE (ACCEPT: HUYGENS-FRESNEL PRINCIPLE)BONUS22) PHYSICS Short Answer Identify all of the following three statements that are true of the cosmic microwave background radiation: 1) The temperature of the radiation can be approximated by a black body; 2) The thermal black body spectrum is at a temperature of approximately 6 Kelvin; 3) The radiation is strongest in the radio and microwave regions of the electromagnetic spectrum.ANSWER: 1 AND 3 (ACCEPT: THE TEMPERATURE OF THE RADIATION CAN BE APPROXIMATED WITH A BLACK BODY AND THE RADIATION IS STRONGEST IN THE RADIO AND MICROWAVE REGIONS OF THE ELECTROMAGNETIC SPECTRUM) | |       High School Round 7A Page 11
TOSS-UP23) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is true about the Labrador Sea Water mass (LSW)?W) It is formed in the western Labrador Sea in the late springX) It travels south along the western edge of the North Atlantic Basin Y) It has decreased in temperature in recent decadesZ) It does not enter the subtropical gyre of the North AtlanticANSWER: X) IT TRAVELS SOUTH ALONG THE WESTERN EDGE OF THE NORTH ATLANTIC BASINBONUS23) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following volcanic hazards occurred from Mount Nyiragongo [nee-ir-uh-GON-goh] in 1977, killing 70 people in nearby villages?W) Eruption of a pyroclastic flow [py-ruh-KLAS-tik] X) Draining of a lava lakeY) Eruption of a noxious gas cloudZ) Creation of a large laharANSWER: X) DRAINING OF A LAVA LAKEHigh School Round 7APage 12