ROUND 3TOSS-UP1) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer During which phase of mitosis [my-TOH-sis] do chromosomes line up along the center of the cell nucleus?ANSWER: METAPHASEBONUS1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Old growth forests and ancient cypress swamps would be examples of which of the following?W) Primary successive speciesX) Secondary successive speciesY) Climax communitiesZ) CommensalismANSWER: Y) CLIMAX COMMUNITIESTOSS-UP2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following kinds of solutions is a mixture in which the solvent has dissolved all the solute it can at a given temperature?W) SaturatedX) UnsaturatedY) Supersaturated Z) ConcentratedANSWER: W) SATURATEDBONUS2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice When calculating the equilibrium constant for a reaction, the concentration of which of the following is generally included?W) Pure liquids X) Pure solids Y) SolventsZ) SolutesANSWER: Z) SOLUTESRound 3 - Page 1TOSS-UP3) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a pyrimidine [py-RIM-i- deen]?W) Guanine [GWAH-neen] X) ThymineY) Adenine [AD-n-een]Z) Xanthine [ZAN-theen]ANSWER: X) THYMINEBONUS3) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer To a very good approximation, a golf club hitting a ball is an example of what kind of collision?ANSWER: ELASTICTOSS-UP4) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What mountain chain composes the majority of the Western Continental Divide in North America?ANSWER: THE ROCKY MOUNTAINSBONUS4) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of estuaries?W) Bottom dominated by course sandsX) Physical connection to the oceanY) Physical connection with a freshwater source Z) Lower average water salinity than ocean waterANSWER: W) BOTTOM DOMINATED BY COURSE SANDS Round 3 - Page 2TOSS-UP5) MATH Short Answer Nick’s car costs $450 per month for car payment and insurance, and 25 cents per mile driven. What is the total monthly cost in dollars in terms of m, the miles driven?ANSWER: 0.25m + 450 (ACCEPT: m/4 + 450) BONUS5) MATH Short Answer A rectangular field has an area of 300 square meters and a perimeter of 80 meters. What are the dimensions of the field in meters?ANSWER: 30 AND 10TOSS-UP6) ENERGY Short Answer Environmentalists are most concerned about the environmental impact of hydroelectric plants on what group of organisms?ANSWER: FISHBONUS6) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following areas of the United States accounts for approximately half of the total hydroelectric power generation in the United States?W) Northeast X) Northwest Y) Southeast Z) SouthwestANSWER: X) NORTHWEST Round 3 - Page 3TOSS-UP7) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Organisms of the same class would also share which of the following?W) GenusX) FamilyY) Phylum [FY-luhm] Z) OrderANSWER: Y) PHYLUMBONUS7) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Scientists are using genetic engineering to develop a wheat crop that is resistant to a particular kind of moth. How would they determine if the plants are moth resistant?W) Determine the length of the moth reproductive cycle in normal wheatX) Monitor moth populations in separate fields planted with control and experimental wheat cropsY) Monitor numbers of moth species infesting normal wheatZ) Determine whether moths in test wheat can be controlled with chemical spraysANSWER: X) MONITOR MOTH POPULATIONS IN SEPARATE FIELDS PLANTED WITH CONTROL AND EXPERIMENTAL WHEAT CROPSTOSS-UP8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the individual repeating units of polymers?ANSWER: MONOMERSBONUS8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Identify by number all of the following that are related to the origin of the name of the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) located at CERN: 1) composite particles made from quarks, 2) particle beams of protons that the LHC was built to collide, 3) lead nuclei that the LHC was built to collide, 4) a famous physicist.ANSWER: 1, 2 AND 3 Round 3 - Page 4TOSS-UP9) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term for the tendency for an object to resist change in its motion?ANSWER: INERTIABONUS9) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Identify all of the following four choices which are possible examples of fossils: 1) seeds, 2) footprints, 3) teeth, 4) cave drawings.ANSWER: 1, 2, 3 (ACCEPT: SEEDS, FOOTPRINTS, TEETH)TOSS-UP10) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What adjective describes an air parcel when it reaches a relative humidity of 100%?ANSWER: SATURATEDBONUS10) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer In fluvial systems, what is the name of the crescent- shaped lake that is formed when a meander of a river is cut off from the main channel?ANSWER: OXBOW LAKE (ACCEPT: OXBOW, HORSESHOE LAKE) Round 3 - Page 5TOSS-UP11) MATH Short Answer If |200 − 𝑥| = 10 [the absolute value of the quantity 200 minus x equals 10], what are the possible values for x?ANSWER: 190 AND 21011) MATH Short Answer Solve the inequality -5 + |p +2| ≥ 0 [negative 5 plus the absolutevalue of the quantity p plus 2 is greater than or equal to 0]. ANSWER: p ≤ -7 OR p ≥ 3 (MUST GIVE BOTH ANSWERS)TOSS-UP12) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT an example of a biomass energy source?BONUS W) Coal X) Wood Y) Grain Z) SugarANSWER: W) COALBONUS12) ENERGY Multiple Choice In the summer, why is it best to do high energy consumption tasks, such as laundry and dishwashing, after 8 pm?W) It will increase the reliability and accessibility of electricity for critical needs in the electrical gridX) It takes more energy to run a dishwasher during the dayY) More energy is produced at nightZ) Hot water heaters are programmed to operate at maximum efficiency after 8 pmANSWER: W) IT WILL INCREASE THE RELIABILITY AND ACCESSIBILITY OF ELECTRICITY FOR CRITICAL NEEDS IN THE ELECTRICAL GRIDRound 3 - Page 6TOSS-UP13) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Of the following habitats, which is the most likely to have the highest amount of biodiversity?W) DesertX) Tropical rainforestY) Deciduous forest [di-SIJ-oo-uhs] Z) PrairieANSWER: X) TROPICAL RAINFORESTBONUS13) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following cats is the largest?W) African lion X) Snow leopard Y) Siberian tiger Z) King cheetahANSWER: Y) SIBERIAN TIGER TOSS-UP14) MATH Short Answer An isosceles triangle has a perimeter of 62 inches. If the base of the triangle is 18 inches, what is the length of each of the congruent legs?ANSWER: 2214) MATH Short Answer What is the standard form of the equation of the line that passesthrough (-2, 4) and is parallel to y = (-3/2)x + 3? ANSWER: 3x + 2y = 2 (DO NOT ACCEPT: -(3/2)x + 1)BONUSRound 3 - Page 7TOSS-UP15) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the least likely to be a characteristic of an invasive species?W) It will outcompete native speciesX) It will only survive under a narrow range of environmental conditions Y) It will have a longer reproductive cycle than native speciesZ) It will do economic and/or environmental harm in a new environmentANSWER: X) IT WILL ONLY SURVIVE UNDER A NARROW RANGE OF ENVIRONMENTAL CONDITIONSBONUS15) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of a jawless fish?W) Sea horse X) Lamprey Y) SharkZ) LungfishANSWER: X) LAMPREY TOSS-UP16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Einstein concluded that E = mc2, where m is mass and c is speed of light. According to this formula, which of the following statements is true?W) All objects have energy only if they are moving at the speed of light X) An object at rest cannot possess an amount of energy due to its mass Y) All objects have energy of being, or rest mass energyZ) Small relativistic objects all propagate at the speed of lightANSWER: Y) ALL OBJECTS HAVE ENERGY OF BEING, OR REST MASS ENERGYBONUS16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer When the force on a falling object is equal to the force of air friction on that object, it will fall at a constant rate. What is this rate called?ANSWER: TERMINAL VELOCITYRound 3 - Page 8TOSS-UP17) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the warm water event originally recognized by anchovy fishermen off the coast of Peru that sometimes occurs near Christmas?ANSWER: EL NIÑOBONUS17) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice By crushing a tablet of medicine before you take it, you are changing the reaction rate by changing which of the following characteristics of the tablet?W) Surface areaX) Amount of reactants Y) Activation energyZ) Km of the reactionANSWER: W) SURFACE AREA TOSS-UP18) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The spring 2011 earthquake in Japan occurred because Japan is located on which of the following?W) A spreading center X) A rift zoneY) A subduction zone Z) A mantle plumeANSWER: Y) A SUBDUCTION ZONEBONUS18) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer It is common for roads in mid latitudes to develop severe potholes after the spring thaw. What form of mechanical weathering is responsible?ANSWER: FREEZING AND THAWING (ACCEPT: FROST ACTION; FROST WEDGING; ICE WEDGING)TOSS-UP19) MATH Short Answer Evaluate 12y/5𝑥 [the fraction with numerator 12 y and denominator 5x] when y=2 and x=0.ANSWER: UNDEFINEDBONUS19) MATH Multiple Choice Between which of the following two whole numbers does √515 [the cube root of 515] fall?W) 5 and 6 X) 6 and 7 Y) 7 and 8 Z) 8 and 9ANSWER: Z) 8 AND 9TOSS-UP20) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following did NOT come from a once-living organism? W) Gasohol X) Crude oil Y) Uranium Z) CharcoalANSWER: Y) URANIUMBONUS20) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following statements best describes a benefit of using alternative energy resources?W) It reduces the amount of fossil fuels that must be used X) It repairs the ozone layerY) It reduces the amount of renewable resources usedZ) It reduces the costs of producing energyANSWER: W) IT REDUCES THE AMOUNT OF FOSSIL FUELS THAT MUST BE USEDRound 3 - Page 10TOSS-UP21) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a source of food for polar bears in the wild?W) Emperor penguins X) Beluga whalesY) WalrusesZ) Ringed sealsANSWER: W) EMPEROR PENGUINSBONUS21) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the organ found in birds and some invertebrates which is used to temporarily store food but also aids in preliminary digestion?ANSWER: CROPTOSS-UP22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A substance with a pH of 2 has what pOH? ANSWER: 12BONUS22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Should oxygen-17 undergo alpha decay, the resulting atom would have which of the following masses in amu?W) 11 X) 13 Y) 15 Z) 17ANSWER: X) 13 Round 3 - Page 11TOSS-UP23) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term for the part of the eye that contains various colored pigments?ANSWER: IRISBONUS23) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A material with which of the following specific heats in joules per kilogram Kelvin will require the least heat to change its temperature?W) 10 X) 50 Y) 100 Z) 1000ANSWER: W) 10 TOSS-UP24) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the name for the hills made from glacial drift and deposited by meltwater from retreating glaciers?W) Kettle X) Drumlin Y) Kame Z) EskerANSWER: Y) KAMEBONUS24) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Disappearing streams, dolines, sink holes, and caves are distinctive features in northern Florida, central Tennessee, and south-central Kentucky and, are indicative of what kind of topography?ANSWER: KARSTRound 3 - Page 12TOSS-UP25) MATH Short Answer What is twenty and 55 hundredths expressed as a decimal, a mixed number in simplest form, and a percent?ANSWER: 20.55, 20 11/20, 2055%25) MATH Multiple Choice For positive values of x, the function f(x) =   2 [the fraction withB O N U S 𝑥 6 𝑥− 𝑥 3numerator x to the sixth minus x cubed and denominator x squared] is which of thefollowing types?W) Quartic X) CubicY) Hyperbolic Z) ParabolicANSWER: W) QUARTICRound 3 - Page 13