ROUND 1

TOSS-UP
1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT part of the human respiratory system?
W) Pharynx [FAR-ingks]
X) Larynx [LAR-ingks]
Y) Esophagus [i-SOF-uh-guhs] Z) Trachea [TRAY-kee-uh]
ANSWER: Y) ESOPHAGUS

BONUS
1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Plasma is the part of human blood that consists mostly of which of the following?
W) Red blood cells
X) White blood cells
Y) Water
Z) Hemoglobin [HEE-muh-gloh-bin]
ANSWER: Y) WATER
 TOSS-UP
2) MATH Short Answer The thickness of a plastic sheet manufactured by Perky Plastics must satisfy: |t � 2| � 0.001 [the absolute value of the quantity t minus 2 is less than or equal to 0.001]. Providing your answer to the nearest thousandth, what is the maximum thickness t, in centimeters, this plastic sheet may have?
ANSWER: 2.001
BONUS
2) MATH Short Answer The perimeter of a rectangle is equal to 280 meters. The ratio of its
length to its width is 5:2. What is the area of the rectangle in square meters?
ANSWER: 4000

TOSS-UP
3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the potential difference in volts between two points, located 2 meters apart, in a constant electric field of 1 volt per meter?
ANSWER: 2
BONUS
3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following cannot be classified within the classical three states of matter?
W) Gasoline
X) Liquid nitrogen Y) Bleach
Z) Liquid crystal
ANSWER: Z) LIQUID CRYSTAL
TOSS-UP
4) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following would be the approximate measure of the length of a soccer field?
W) 1 decameter
X) 10 kilometers
Y) 100 meters
Z) 1000 centimeters
ANSWER: Y) 100 METERS
BONUS
4) MATH Short Answer The volume of cube C is 8 cubic centimeters. Cube D has an edge 3 times the edge of cube C. What is the volume of cube D in cubic centimeters?
ANSWER: 216
Round 1 - Page 2
TOSS-UP
5) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Leaves with an undivided blade are called which of the following?
W) Tendrils X) Spines
Y) Compound Z) Simple
ANSWER: Z) SIMPLE
BONUS
5) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following will allow measurement of a liquid�s volume with the greatest precision?
W) 50 milliliter cylinder graduated in 1 milliliter increments X) 100 milliliter cylinder graduated in 0.5 milliliter increments Y) 100 milliliter cylinder graduated in 1 milliliter increments Z) 200 milliliter cylinder graduated in 5 milliliter increments
ANSWER: X) 100 MILLILITER CYLINDER GRADUATED IN 0.5 MILLILITER INCREMENTS
TOSS-UP
6) ENERGY Short Answer A house built in the United States with passive solar capabilities needs to have its large windows facing which compass direction?
ANSWER: SOUTH
BONUS
6) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following units is most commonly used in the U.S. to compare the energy content of two different fuel sources?
W) BTU X) Barrel Y) Kilowatt Z) Gallon
ANSWER: W) BTU
 Round 1 - Page 3
TOSS-UP
7) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following annelids has a sucker at each end of its body?
W) Earthworm
X) Leech
Y) Bristleworm
Z) Polychaete [POL-i-keet]
ANSWER: X) LEECH
7) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Put the following four stages of development in order from
earliest to latest: 1) larvae [LAHR-vee], 2) adult, 3) egg, 4) pupa. ANSWER: 3, 1, 4, 2 (ACCEPT: EGG, LARVAE, PUPA, ADULT)
TOSS-UP
8) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following types of maps would show the most accurate representation of the entire surface of the Earth?
W) Mercator projection X) Equal-area projection Y) Globe
Z) Contour projection
ANSWER: Y) GLOBE
BONUS
 BONUS
8) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the best explanation of how rift valleys are formed?
W) The scouring of bedrock as glaciers retreat
X) Tectonic divergence
Y) The accumulation of glacial deposits deposited as glaciers retreat Z) A wide river scours out the land then shifts direction
ANSWER: X) TECTONIC DIVERGENCE
Round 1 - Page 4
TOSS-UP
9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the kinetic energy in joules of a 10-kilogram object moving at a velocity of 2 meters per second?
ANSWER: 20
BONUS
9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A glass of water with ice cubes in it has a mass of 300 grams. What will the mass in grams be immediately after the ice has melted?
ANSWER: 300
TOSS-UP
10) MATH Short Answer If both coordinates of a point are negative, in which quadrant in the Cartesian coordinate system would it be located?
ANSWER: III (ACCEPT: THIRD)
BONUS
10)MATH Short Answer If ab=12,a+b=8,and a is greater than b,what is the value of a - b?
ANSWER: 4



TOSS-UP
11) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Identify all of the following four choices that all living things must do to survive: 1) excrete wastes, 2) maintain homeostasis [hoh-mee-uh-STAY-sis], 3) ingest food, 4) metabolize.
ANSWER: 1, 2, 4 (ACCEPT: EXCRETE WASTES, MAINTAIN HOMEOSTASIS, METABOLIZE)
BONUS
11) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true?
W) Some species of Archeabacteria [ahr-ke-bak-TEER-ee-uh] are the oldest organisms on Earth
X) Some species of Archeabacteria are extremophiles
Y) Some species of Eubacteria have a membrane-bound nucleus
Z) Some species of Eubacteria are found in your mouth
ANSWER: Y) SOME SPECIES OF EUBACTERIA HAVE A MEMBRANE-BOUND NUCLEUS
TOSS-UP
12) ENERGY Multiple Choice Emma puts a thermometer into a glass filled with hot water. Why does the mercury inside the thermometer rise?
W) Air bubbles are released
X) Heat from the water makes it expand Y) Heat from the water makes it contract Z) Air pressure above the water pulls it up
ANSWER: X) HEAT FROM THE WATER MAKES IT EXPAND
BONUS
12) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is, to date, the most promising method of disposing of nuclear waste?
W) Combining it with carbon dioxide
X) Storing it underground in a geologic formation Y) Storing it in a low-level disposal vault
Z) Diluting it before pouring it into the ocean
ANSWER: X) STORING IT UNDERGROUND IN A GEOLOGIC FORMATION
 Round 1 - Page 6
TOSS-UP
13) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following types of feather helps birds maintain a constant body temperature?
W) Contour X) Down
Y) Barbed Z) Ribbed
ANSWER: X) DOWN

BONUS
13) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an adaptation in birds that facilitates flight?
W) Hollow bones X) Sharp claws
Y) Smooth feathers Z) Small beaks
ANSWER: W) HOLLOW BONES
 TOSS-UP
14) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer In approximately 5.5 billion years, our Sun will move to which next phase in its life cycle?
ANSWER: RED GIANT
BONUS
14) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following cosmic phenomena gave rise to most of the iron found on Earth?
W) Red giants
X) Supernovae [soo-per-NOH-vee] Y) Quasars [KWAY-zahrs]
Z) Pulsars
ANSWER: X) SUPERNOVAE
Round 1 - Page 7
TOSS-UP
15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A metal spoon, a wooden spoon and a plastic spoon are all placed in hot water. After 15 seconds, which spoon will feel the hottest?
ANSWER: METAL
BONUS
15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What form of electromagnetic radiation causes sunburns?
ANSWER: ULTRAVIOLET (ACCEPT: UVA AND UVB; DO NOT ACCEPT: UVC)
TOSS-UP
16) MATH Short Answer Providing your answer as a fraction in lowest terms, what is the slope of a line that is perpendicular to a line with the equation y = 5x - 2/3 ?
ANSWER: -1/5

BONUS
16) MATH Short Answer What is the greatest integer less than or equal to �888? ANSWER: 29



TOSS-UP
17) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is true?
W) Lightning never strikes the same location twice
X) A car�s rubber tires will protect its occupants from lightning
Y) If outside during a lightning storm, it is best to take a low, crouching position with feet together
Z) Lightning strike victims retain an electrical charge and will shock someone who touches them
ANSWER: Y) IF OUTSIDE DURING A LIGHTNING STORM, IT IS BEST TO TAKE A LOW, CROUCHING POSITION WITH FEET TOGETHER
BONUS
17) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer If you see a flash of lightning and ten seconds pass before you hear a clap of thunder, about how far away to the nearest mile is the thunderstorm?
ANSWER: 2
TOSS-UP
18) ENERGY Short Answer Electric energy is used to power an incandescent lamp. Is the amount of light energy produced more than, less than, or equal to the electrical energy used?
ANSWER: LESS THAN
BONUS
18) ENERGY Short Answer In 1800, Alessandro Volta made the first electric battery by alternating discs of copper and zinc with cloth dampened with a solution of water and salt. What was the name of his invention?
ANSWER: VOLTAIC PILE (ACCEPT: ELECTRIC ORGAN)
 Round 1 - Page 9
TOSS-UP
19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following kinds of mammal teeth are used to bite and cut?
W) Incisors X) Premolars Y) Molars
Z) Grinders
ANSWER: W) INCISORS
BONUS
19) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term for the non-living physical and chemical components of an ecosystem?
ANSWER: ABIOTIC
TOSS-UP
20) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the name of the artificial satellite, launched in 1957, that was a partial cause for the formation of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration?
ANSWER: SPUTNIK
BONUS
20) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The size of a wind-generated wave formed in open ocean depends on which of the following pairs of characteristics of wind?
W) Strength and duration X) Strength and direction Y) Fetch and direction
Z) Fetch and temperature
ANSWER: W) STRENGTH AND DURATION
 Round 1 - Page 10
TOSS-UP
21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of a compound?
W) O2 X) O3 Y) HCl Z) Cl2
ANSWER: Y) HCl
BONUS
21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following properties is NOT a property of a covalent molecular compound?
W) Low melting point
X) Low boiling point
Y) Good electrical conductivity Z) Poor thermal conductivity
ANSWER: Y) GOOD ELECTRICAL CONDUCTIVITY

TOSS-UP
22) MATH Short Answer If an angle measures 34�, what is the measure in degrees of its supplement?
ANSWER: 146°
BONUS
22) MATH Short Answer Given a triangle ABC in which side AB = 10 centimeters, side AC = 10
centimeters, and angle A = 72�, what is the measure in degrees of angle B?
ANSWER: 54°



Round 1 - Page 11
TOSS-UP
23) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In the chemical formula for ammonia, NH3, which of the following does the subscript 3 represent?
W) The number of hydrogen atoms in each molecule of ammonia
X) The number of nitrogen atoms in each molecule of ammonia
Y) The number of nitrogen and hydrogen atoms in each molecule of ammonia Z) The number of ammonia molecules that will bond together
ANSWER: W) THE NUMBER OF HYDROGEN ATOMS IN EACH MOLECULE OF AMMONIA
BONUS
23) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Providing your answer in scientific notation with the correct number of significant digits, what is the sum of 1.2 X 10-3 and 2.7 X 10-4?
ANSWER: 1.5 X 10-3
TOSS-UP
24) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer In Earth's interior, where temperature and pressures are high, what is the term for molten rock?
ANSWER: MAGMA
BONUS
24) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Extremely coarse grained igneous rocks, with minerals larger than 1 inch, are evidence of which of the following?
W) Volcanic rocks with previously formed crystals
X) Volcanic rocks cooled rapidly along ocean floor fissures Y) Magma cooling with high volatile content
Z) Magma cooling quickly to form aplite
ANSWER: Y) MAGMA COOLING WITH HIGH VOLATILE CONTENT
 Round 1 - Page 12
TOSS-UP
25) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following biomes, on average, receives the lowest amount of annual precipitation?
W) Temperate deciduous forest [di-SIJ-oo-uhs] X) Tundra
Y) Taiga
Z) Grasslands
ANSWER: X) TUNDRA
BONUS
25) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following five animals which can be found in a wetlands environment: 1) pronghorn antelope 2) beaver, 3) muskrat, 4) salamander, 5) hedgehog.
ANSWER: 2, 3, 4 (ACCEPT: BEAVER, MUSKRAT, SALAMANDER)
Round 1 - Page 13
