ROUND 4
          TOSS-UP
1) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice An approximate representation or simulation of a system being studied is called which of the following?
W) Hypothesis X) Model
Y) Experiment Z) Scientific law
ANSWER: X) MODEL
BONUS
1) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following best represents the proper order of steps in the scientific process?
W) Test, discuss, observe, hypothesize X) Test, observe, discuss, hypothesize Y) Observe, hypothesize, test, discuss Z) Discuss, observe, hypothesize, test
ANSWER: Y) OBSERVE, HYPOTHESIZE, TEST, DISCUSS
TOSS-UP
2) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is a polyhedron whose base is a polygon and whose other faces meet at a point?
W) Pyramid
X) Cone
Y) Prism
Z) Regular polyhedron
 ANSWER: W) PYRAMID
2) MATH Short Answer What is the surface area, in feet squared and to the nearest integer, of
a sphere with a radius of 1 foot? ANSWER: 13
BONUS
Round 4 - Page 1
TOSS-UP
3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the density in grams per cubic centimeter of a substance that has a mass of 50 grams and a volume of 10 cubic centimeters?
ANSWER: 5
BONUS
3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer If calcium were to combine with bromine to form a neutral molecule, what is the least number of calcium and bromine atoms, respectively, that would be required?
ANSWER: CALCIUM = 1; BROMINE = 2
TOSS-UP
4) ENERGY Multiple Choice The energy used in our households comes through electrical lines originating from which of the following locations?
W) A generation station X) A rectifying bridge
Y) A power supply
Z) A DC to DC converter
ANSWER: W) A GENERATION STATION
BONUS
4) ENERGY Multiple Choice Fuel cells work in which of the following ways?
W) By converting chemical energy into electrical energy X) By processing plant matter to generate electricity
Y) By converting thermal energy into electrical energy Z) By using fossil fuels to generate mechanical energy
ANSWER: W) BY CONVERTING CHEMICAL ENERGY INTO ELECTRICAL ENERGY
 Round 4 - Page 2
TOSS-UP
5) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following organisms has the most recent common ancestor with humans?
W) Orangutan X) Gorilla
Y) Chimpanzee Z) Lemur
ANSWER: Y) CHIMPANZEE
BONUS
5) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What metallic element in hemoglobin [HEE-muh-gloh-bin] binds oxygen?
ANSWER: IRON
TOSS-UP
6) MATH Short Answer A parallelogram has a height of 20 feet. If its area is 600 square feet, what is its base in feet?
ANSWER: 30
BONUS
6) MATH Short Answer Giving your answer as a percent, what is the grade, or slope, of a dirt road that rises 20 feet for a horizontal distance of 400 feet?
ANSWER: 5%
 Round 4 - Page 3
TOSS-UP
7) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer On a velocity graph, what is the acceleration when the line is level and horizontal?
ANSWER: ZERO
BONUS
7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following represents a synthesis reaction?
W) Zn + HCl  →  [yields] ZnCl2 + H2
X) AgNO3 + HCl → AgCl + HNO3
Y) 2KClO3 → 2KCl + 3O2
Z) N2 + 3H2 → 2NH3
ANSWER: Z) N2 + 3H2 → 2NH3
TOSS-UP
8) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is characteristic of all plankton?
W) Microscopic
X) Single-celled
Y) Limited in mobility Z) Photosynthetic
ANSWER: Y) LIMITED IN MOBILITY
BONUS
8) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the name for igneous [IG-nee-uhs] rock that cuts across the structure of adjoining rock, usually as a result of magma intrusion?
ANSWER: DIKE
Round 4 - Page 4
TOSS-UP
9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice It is impossible for a sound wave to travel through which of the following?
W) Water
X) Air
Y) A vacuum Z) Wood
ANSWER: Y) A VACUUM
BONUS
9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true?
W) Stirring a solution will decrease the rate at which a solid solute dissolves
X) For most solid solutes, increasing the temperature of the solvent speeds up the dissolution rate
Y) Decreasing the surface area of the solute decreases the dissolution rate
Z) For a gaseous solute, cooling the solvent increases the dissolution rate
ANSWER: W) STIRRING A SOLUTION WILL DECREASE THE RATE AT WHICH A SOLID SOLUTE DISSOLVES
TOSS-UP
10) ENERGY Short Answer If a single phase circuit contains at least one live wire, what is the minimum number of wires needed in a three phase system?
ANSWER: THREE
BONUS
10) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is a characteristic of appliances labeled under the Energy Star logo?
W) They consume 10-15% less energy than required by federal standards X) They consume 20-30% less energy than required by federal standards Y) They convert 30% of the electrical energy into mechanical energy
Z) They have an energy loss of around 20-30%
ANSWER: X) THEY CONSUME 20-30% LESS ENERGY THAN REQUIRED BY FEDERAL STANDARDS
 Round 4 - Page 5
TOSS-UP
11) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following hormones induces glucose uptake by cells after food consumption?
W) Glucagon [GLOO-kuh-gon]
X) Glucuronidase [gloo-koh-ROH-nee-dayz] Y) Insulin
Z) Thyroxin [thy-ROK-seen]
ANSWER: Y) INSULIN
BONUS
11) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What plant hormone causes tree leaves to fall in the autumn?
ANSWER: ABSCISIC ACID (ALSO ACCEPT ABA, ABSCISIN II, OR DORMIN)
TOSS-UP
 12) MATH Short Answer Providing your answer in terms of pi and in centimeters, what is the circumference of a circular disk whose area is 100� square centimeters?
ANSWER: 20�
BONUS
12) MATH Short Answer What is the height in centimeters of a trapezoid for which the two bases measure 13 centimeters and 27 centimeters, and its area is equal to 400 square centimeters?
ANSWER: 20
Round 4 - Page 6
TOSS-UP
13) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer The largest shield volcano in our solar system, Olympus Mons, is located on which planet?
ANSWER: MARS
BONUS
13) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice On which of the following types of volcanoes is scoria commonly found?
W) Shield volcano
X) Composite volcano Y) Cinder cone
Z) Fissure vents
ANSWER: Y) CINDER CONE
 TOSS-UP
14) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Down syndrome is a condition associated with which of the following genetic abnormalities?
W) Duplication of chromosome 3 X) Trisomy 21
Y) No sex chromosome
Z) Monosomy 7
ANSWER: X) TRISOMY 21
BONUS
14) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice The human disease malaria is caused by which of the following types of pathogen?
W) Prion
X) Virus
Y) Protist
Z) Bacterium
ANSWER: Y) PROTIST
Round 4 - Page 7
TOSS-UP
15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following forms of RNA carries genetic information from the nucleus to the ribosomes [ry-buh-sohms]?
W) Regulatory X) Messenger Y) Transfer
Z) Micro
ANSWER: X) MESSENGER
BONUS
15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following correctly lists two of the three types of rocks in the rock cycle?
W) Igneous and metamorphic
X) Metamorphic and megamorphic Y) Sedimentary and morphometric Z) Morphometric and sedimentary
ANSWER: W) IGNEOUS AND METAMORPHIC
TOSS-UP
16) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the name of the large transform boundary found in western California?
ANSWER: SAN ANDREAS FAULT
BONUS
16) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following cloud types is most commonly associated with major thunderstorms?
W) Nimbostratus [nim-boh-STRAT-uhs]
X) Cumulonimbus [kyoo-myuh-loh-NIM-buhs] Y) Cirrus [SIR-uhs]
Z) Stratus
ANSWER: X) CUMULONIMBUS
 Round 4 - Page 8
TOSS-UP
17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following characteristics is NOT related to sound?
W) Wavelength X) Speed
Y) Mass
Z) Amplitude
ANSWER: Y) MASS
BONUS
17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice How is the magnetism of an electromagnet turned on and off?
W) With a galvanometer
X) Adding more turns in the coil
Y) Reversing the direction of the current
Z) Turning the current through the coil on and off
ANSWER: Z) TURNING THE CURRENT THROUGH THE COIL ON AND OFF
TOSS-UP
18) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes a carbon footprint?
W) A footprint that is left when someone steps on carbon
X) The emission of greenhouse gases caused by a product or individual
Y) A monetary credit awarded to people who reduce their greenhouse gas emissions Z) A factor that does not merit consideration when buying energy efficient appliances
ANSWER: X) THE EMISSION OF GREENHOUSE GASES CAUSED BY A PRODUCT OR INDIVIDUAL
BONUS
18) ENERGY Multiple Choice Beside batteries, which of the following is another way to store energy from renewable energy systems for later use?
W) Ultra inductors X) Tesla coils
Y) Ultra capacitors Z) Fuel cells
ANSWER: Y) ULTRA CAPACITORS
 Round 4 - Page 9
TOSS-UP
19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following molecules gives carrots their orange color?
W) Vitamin A
X) Carotene
Y) Lycopene [LY-kuh-peen] Z) Vitamin C
ANSWER: X) CAROTENE
BONUS
19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Standardized terms are used to describe locations on an organism's body. Which of the following terms refers to the region of the body with the stomach?
W) Ventral X) Dorsal Y) Posterior Z) Anterior
ANSWER: W) VENTRAL
TOSS-UP
20) MATH Short Answer Given a triangle FGE, such that GT is one of its medians, if TE = 8, what is the length of FE?
ANSWER: 16
BONUS
20) MATH Short Answer Given the parallelogram with vertices (2, 6), (8, 6), and (7, 2), what are the coordinates of the fourth vertex if the sum of those two coordinates is as small as possible?
ANSWER: (1, 2)
TOSS-UP
21) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following terms is known as the set of alleles present in an organism?
W) Genotype X) Trait
Y) Gene
Z) Phenotype
ANSWER: W) GENOTYPE
BONUS
21) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Providing your answer as a decimal, how much energy in kilowatt hours is needed to run a 50 watt light bulb for 5 hours?
ANSWER: 0.25
TOSS-UP
22) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What type of weathering is defined by disintegration of rock into smaller and smaller fragments, each with the same properties of the original?
ANSWER: MECHANICAL
BONUS
22) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the name of a rock or boulder that differs from the surrounding rock and is believed to have been brought from a distance through glacial action?
ANSWER: ERRATIC
 Round 4 - Page 11
TOSS-UP
23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following elements is a metalloid?
W) Silicon X) Calcium Y) Iron
Z) Argon
ANSWER: W) SILICON
BONUS
23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements best describes the properties of semiconductors?
W) They are more conductive than metals but less conductive than nonmetal insulators X) Their conductivity is the same as metals
Y) Impurities make them less conductive than metals and nonmetals
Z) They are less conductive than metals but more conductive than insulators
ANSWER: Z) THEY ARE LESS CONDUCTIVE THAN METALS BUT MORE CONDUCTIVE THAN INSULATORS
TOSS-UP
24) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following proportions is NOT correct?
W) 15/9 = 5/3
X) 30/50 =600/1000
Y) 8/24 =4/16
Z) 4.2/8.4=5/10
ANSWER:Y) 8/24 = 4/16
BONUS
24) MATH Short Answer The length of rectangle A is 24 centimeters, and the length of rectangle B is 96 centimeters. Given that the two rectangles are similar, what is the ratio of the area of A to the area of B?
ANSWER: 1:16 (ACCEPT: 1/16)
TOSS-UP
25) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following organs is the first to lose its function under hypoxic conditions?
W) Heart X) Brain Y) Liver Z) Lungs
ANSWER: X) BRAIN
BONUS
25) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer You have isolated a pathogen which contains RNA surrounded by a protein coat, but which lacks other cellular organelles. What type of pathogen is it?
ANSWER: VIRUS (ACCEPT: RETROVIRUS)
Round 4 - Page 13
