ROUND 9TOSS-UP1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following birds depends almost entirely on man-made nesting boxes in the eastern United States?W) Yellow-bellied sapsucker X) Purple martinY) Blue jayZ) Red-breasted nuthatchANSWER: X) PURPLE MARTINBONUS1) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true about the Iberian lynx?W) It is one of the most endangered cat species in the worldX) It can leap more than 19 feet horizontally and more than 9 feet vertically Y) Its favorite food is rabbitZ) It has a characteristic beard around its faceANSWER: X) IT CAN LEAP MORE THAN 19 FEET HORIZONTALLY AND MORE THAN 9 FEET VERTICALLYTOSS-UP2) MATH Short Answer A colony of bacteria is growing in a culture under controlled conditions with a doubling period of two days. If, on a given day, there are 100 bacteria present, how many bacteria will there be 8 days later? ANSWER: 1600BONUS2) MATH Short Answer What is the vertex form of the equation y = x2 + 16x + 71? ANSWER:y=(x+8)2 +7Round 9Page 1TOSS-UP3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A mass with velocity v accelerates when a force is applied to it. This is an illustration of which of Newton’s laws of motion?ANSWER: SECONDBONUS3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following compounds is binary?W) Molecular oxygen X) Calcium chloride Y) Sulfuric acidZ) Copper (II) nitrateANSWER: X) CALCIUM CHLORIDETOSS-UP4) MATH Short Answer Find g(1) [g of 1] when g(a) = 3^(3𝑎−2) [g of a equals 3 to the power of the quantity 3 a minus 2].ANSWER: 3BONUS4) MATH Short Answer Providing your answer in simplest radical form, where does the graph of y=2x^2 – 5x–1 cross thex-axis?ANSWER: (5 + √33)/4 AND (5 – √33)/4TOSS-UP5) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following elements has the same Lewis dot structure as sulfur?W) Phosphorus X) OxygenY) ChlorineZ) MagnesiumANSWER: X) OXYGENBONUS5) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Place the following four phases of cell division in order from first to last: 1) anaphase, 2) prophase, 3) metaphase, 4) telophase.ANSWER: 2, 3, 1, 4 (ACCEPT: PROPHASE, METAPHASE, ANAPHASE, TELOPHASE)TOSS-UP6) ENERGY Multiple Choice Hydroelectric energy accounts for which of the following approximate proportions of the total energy consumed annually in the United States? W) 1% X) 8% Y) 30% Z) 65%ANSWER: X) 8%BONUS6) ENERGY Short Answer What phenomenon is demonstrated when liquids heated inside a microwave oven are removed, do not appear to boil, but then suddenly and without warning, erupt?ANSWER: SUPERHEATINGRound 9 Page 3TOSS-UP7) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the common name of the fungus that is rapidly killing many amphibians [am-FIB-ee-uhns] across Central and South America?ANSWER: CHYTRID7) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following does NOT characterize dicotyledon[dy-kot-l-EEd-n] plants?W) Parallel veins on leaf X) Tap rootsY) Many leavesZ) 4 or 5 flower petalsANSWER: W) PARALLEL VEINS ON LEAFTOSS-UPBONUS 8) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What satellite of Jupiter is considered to be the most volcanically active body in our solar system?ANSWER: IOBONUS8) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the adiabatic lapse rate of a dry air parcel for every kilometer it rises?W) 5° Fahrenheit X) 5° CelsiusY) 10° Fahrenheit Z) 10° CelsiusANSWER: Z) 10° CELSIUSRound 9Page 4TOSS-UP9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Given that g is 10 meters per second squared, how much work in joules is done by gravity when an object with mass of 100 grams falls 5 meters?ANSWER: 5BONUS9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice How do alkali metals differ from alkaline [AL-kuh-lyn] earth metals?W) Alkali metals have one electron in their outer shells; alkaline earth metals have two X) Alkali metals do not conduct electricity; alkaline earth metals doY) Alkali metals are highly reactive; alkaline earth metals are notZ) Alkali metals are malleable [MAL-ee-uh-buhl]; alkaline earth metals are ductileANSWER: W) ALKALI METALS HAVE ONE ELECTRON IN THEIR OUTER SHELLS; ALKALINE EARTH METALS HAVE TWOTOSS-UP10) MATH Short Answer What is the determinant of the 2 by 2 matrix [first rownegative 5, 3 and second row 4, 2]?ANSWER: -22 BONUS10) MATH Short Answer Rebekah wants to fill a spherical piñata with candy. If the radius of her piñata is 6 inches, providing your answer in terms of pi, what is the volume in cubic inches of her piñata?ANSWER: 288πTOSS-UP11) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Considering just the human ABO blood antigens, how many different blood types are possible?ANSWER: 4BONUS11) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice An environmental toxin introduced into a eukaryotic [yoo-KAR-ee-oh-tik] cell prevents the cell from producing ribosomes [RY-buh-sohms], yet DNA replication still occurs. From this information, which of the following enzymes is likely affected?W) DNA polymerase [POL-uh-muh-rays]X) RNA polymeraseY) HelicaseZ) PrimaseANSWER: X) RNA POLYMERASETOSS-UP12) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the main disadvantage of hydroelectric dams?W) They increase the potential for floodingX) They consume more energy than they produceY) They disrupt previously existing ecosystems Z) They add pollutant byproducts to the waterANSWER: Y) THEY DISRUPT PREVIOUSLY EXISTING ECOSYSTEMSBONUS12) ENERGY Short Answer What is the term for the process of carbon capture and storage by depositing it in underground reservoirs?ANSWER: CARBON SEQUESTRATIONTOSS-UP13) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Assuming Mendelian [men-DEE-lee-uhn] genetics, when two organisms with the genotype Aa [big A, little a] are crossed, what proportion of their offspring will express the “big A” phenotype?ANSWER: 3/4 (ACCEPT: 75%)BONUS13) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the largest songbird in North America?W) Cedar waxwing X) Northern oriole Y) Common raven Z) Indigo buntingANSWER: Y) COMMON RAVEN TOSS-UP14) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer If magma is cooled slowly, what generalization could you make about crystal size?ANSWER: LARGER CRYSTALS (ACCEPT: BIGGER, INCREASED)BONUS14) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following types of horizontal magma intrusion is lens-shaped?W) DikeX) SillY) Laccolith [LAK-uh-lith] Z) Batholith [BATH-uh-lith]ANSWER: Y) LACCOLITHRound 9Page 7TOSS-UP15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer When the speed of sound in air is 344 meters per second, what is the wavelength in meters of a sound wave of frequency 172 hertz?ANSWER: 2BONUS15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true of halogens?W) They are nonreactive metals at room temperatureX) They only need one electron to fill their outer energy levelY) They can be used for disinfection of water and for preventing diseases of the thyroid gland Z) They naturally form diatomic moleculesANSWER: W) THEY ARE NONREACTIVE METALS AT ROOM TEMPERATURETOSS-UP16) MATH Short Answer Identify all of the following four statements that are always true about a square: 1) it is a rectangle; 2) it is a rhombus; 3) it is a parallelogram; 4) it is a quadrilateral. ANSWER: ALL16) MATH Short Answer What is the slope of a line perpendicular to the line passing throughthe points with coordinates (-6, 0) and (-2, 3)? ANSWER: -4/3BONUSRound 9 Page 8TOSS-UP17) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following deposits minerals in the deep ocean?W) VolcanoesX) Dissolved gasesY) PrecipitationZ) Underground streamsANSWER: Y) PRECIPITATIONBONUS17) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Earth’s magnetic field is most heavily influenced by electric currents within which of the following layers of the Earth?W) Inner coreX) Outer coreY) Athenosphere Z) MantleANSWER: X) OUTER CORE TOSS-UP18) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following will save the most energy per load of laundry using an electric washing machine?W) Using eco-friendly detergentsX) Using the cold water setting on the washer Y) Skipping the spin cycleZ) Running small loads when possibleANSWER: X) USING THE COLD WATER SETTING ON THE WASHERBONUS18) ENERGY Short Answer What term is used to describe the total estimated amount of producible oil in an oil reservoir [REZ-er-vwohr]?ANSWER: OIL RESERVESRound 9 Page 9TOSS-UP19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a genetic disorder caused by aneuploidy [an-yoo-PLOI-dee]?W) Cystic fibrosisX) Down syndromeY) Muscular dystrophy Z) PolioANSWER: X) DOWN SYNDROMEBONUS19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice You have discovered a new bacterium. You notice that this bacterium can use light to create ATP, but is reliant on other prokaryotes [proh-KAR-ee-ohts] to obtain organic carbon. The bacterium is most likely which of the following?W) Photoautotrophic X) Chemoautotrophic Y) Photoheterotrophic Z) ChemoheterotrophicANSWER: Y) PHOTOHETEROTROPHICTOSS-UP20) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the most abundant element in Earth’s crust? ANSWER: OXYGENBONUS20) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following processes is a type of chemical weathering?W) Mineral dissolution X) Frost-wedgingY) Pressure unloading Z) Organism actionANSWER: W) MINERAL DISSOLUTION Round 9Page 10TOSS-UP21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer If a chemical reaction occurs spontaneously, what is the sign of its Gibbs free energy change?ANSWER: NEGATIVEBONUS21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer When magnesium and fluorine react, what type of bond is formed?ANSWER: IONICTOSS-UP22) MATH Short Answer What is the interior angle sum in degrees in a regular dodecagon? ANSWER: 1800° (ACCEPT: 1800 WITHOUT DEGREE SIGN)BONUS 22) MATH Short Answer A ball bounces to half its height when dropped from a 20 foot porch. What is the total distance, in feet, the ball will have traveled when it hits the ground for the third time?ANSWER: 50Round 9 Page 11TOSS-UP23) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer If a DNA double strand contains seven A-T pairs and fourteen C-G pairs, assuming all nucleotides are read, how many amino acids are formed?ANSWER: 7BONUS23) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Of the following, which is NOT considered a type of vascular tissue in plants?W) Sclerenchyma [skli-RENG-kuh-muh] X) Parenchyma [puh-RENG-kuh-muh] Y) Xylem [ZY-luhm]Z) Phloem [FLOH-em]ANSWER: W) SCLERENCHYMATOSS-UP24) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following types of electromagnetic energy is least likely to make it through Earth’s atmosphere? W) X-raysX) Microwave radiation Y) Ultraviolet radiation Z) Radio wavesANSWER: W) X-RAYSBONUS24) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following was NOT cited by Wegner as evidence for continental drift?W) The continents fit togetherX) Fossils are similar on South America and AfricaY) Matching paleoclimate indicators on South America and AfricaZ) Similar bathymetry of the sea floor on opposite sides of the Mid-Atlantic RidgeANSWER: Z) SIMILAR BATHYMETRY OF THE SEA FLOOR ON OPPOSITE SIDES OF THE MID-ATLANTIC RIDGERound 9 Page 12TOSS-UP25) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In the human body, which of the following processes is considered to be anabolic?W) Glycolysis [gly-KOL-uh-sis]X) The breakdown of fatty acids in the process of beta oxidationY) The synthesis of glycogen [GLY-kuh-juhn] in the liver from glucose Z) The breakdown of polypeptides [pol-ee-PEP-tyds] in the stomachANSWER: Y) THE SYNTHESIS OF GLYCOGEN IN THE LIVER FROM GLUCOSEBONUS25) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A person has to push with greater force to begin moving a heavy crate across the floor. However, once the crate has begun to move, the person can push with less force in order to move the object across the floor at a constant rate. Which of the following best explains such a phenomenon?W) The coefficient of static friction is greater than the coefficient of kinetic friction, resulting in a greater frictional force before the object has begun to moveX) The coefficient of static friction is greater than the coefficient of kinetic friction, resulting in a greater frictional force after the object has begun to moveY) The coefficient of kinetic friction is greater than the coefficient of static friction, resulting in a greater frictional force before the object has begun to moveZ) The coefficient of kinetic friction is greater than the coefficient of static friction, resulting in a greater frictional force after the object has begun to moveANSWER: W) THE COEFFICIENT OF STATIC FRICTION IS GREATER THAN THE COEFFICIENT OF KINETIC FRICTION, RESULTING IN A GREATER FRICTIONAL FORCE BEFORE THE OBJECT HAS BEGUN TO MOVERound 9 Page 13