ROUND 12          TOSS-UP1) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a prosimian [proh-SIM-ee- uhn]?W) Orangutan X) PandaY) IguanaZ) LemurANSWER: Z) LEMURBONUS1) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Given that up is positive and that g is 10 meters per second squared, if a ball is thrown vertically upward with an initial velocity of 20 meters per second, what will be its velocity in meters per second after 3 seconds?ANSWER: -10TOSS-UP2) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true about the jet stream?W) It is found at the altitude at which winds are the strongestX) It is strongest when there is a large temperature contrast between two air massesY) It is usually composed of easterly windsZ) It is caused by a combination of the Earth’s rotation on its axis and atmospheric heatingANSWER: Y) IT IS USUALLY COMPOSED OF EASTERLY WINDSBONUS2) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following NASA missions has a primary objective to map variations in Earth’s gravity field?W) GRACE X) LAGEOS Y) Nimbus Z) SMAPANSWER: W) GRACE Round 12 - Page 1TOSS-UP3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What term describes a thermodynamic process that is constantly in equilibrium, such that an infinitesimal change can lead to a redirection of that process without any release or loss of energy?ANSWER: REVERSIBLEBONUS3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is coherent light?W) Polarized light that has passed through a coherent filterX) Light of one wavelength, traveling in one direction, with crests and troughs alignedY) Light of one wavelength, spreading out in all directions, and vibrating in several planes Z) Light made up of waves that vibrate in only one planeANSWER: X) LIGHT OF ONE WAVELENGTH, TRAVELING IN ONE DIRECTION, WITH CRESTS AND TROUGHS ALIGNEDTOSS-UP4) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following reflects the approximate percentage range of coal produced from surface mines as a fraction of total coal production in the U.S.? W) 10-20%X) 30-40%Y) 40-50%Z) More than 60%ANSWER: Z) MORE THAN 60%BONUS4) ENERGY Multiple Choice Burning rock refers to which of the following energy sources?W) CoalX) Oil shale Y) Tar sands Z) PeatANSWER: X) OIL SHALERound 12 - Page 2TOSS-UP5) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer On a DNA electrophoresis [e-lek-troh-fuh-REE-sis] gel, what moves the DNA from one end to the other?ANSWER: AN ELECTRICAL CURRENT (ACCEPT: ELECTRICAL FIELD, ELECTRICITY, POWER SOURCE, VOLTAGE DIFFERENCE)BONUS5) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Parasitic flatworms, commonly called flukes, that infect the internal organs of their hosts are in which of the following classes?W) Turbellarians [tur-buh-LAIR-ee-uhns] X) Trematoda [trem-uh-TOH-duh]Y) Cestoda [ses-TOHD-uh]Z) Nematoda [nem-uh-TOH-duh]ANSWER: X) TREMATODATOSS-UP6) MATH Short Answer If the height of a pyramid is doubled, but the base remains unchanged, what happens to its volume? ANSWER: DOUBLESBONUS6) MATH Short Answer A tour bus traveled 3 kilometers east, proceeded 12 kilometers south, then 7 kilometers west, and finally 7 kilometers north. In simplest form, how far in kilometers is it from its starting point?ANSWER: √41 Round 12 - Page 3TOSS-UP7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The ABO blood classification system is determined by which of the following types of biological molecules on the surface of red blood cells?W) Nucleic acids X) Carbohydrates Y) ProteinsZ) LipidsANSWER: X) CARBOHYDRATESBONUS7) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What are the numbers, respectively, of protons, neutrons, and electrons in an isotope of titanium with a mass number of 50?ANSWER: PROTONS = 22; ELECTRONS = 22; NEUTRONS = 28TOSS-UP8) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Compared to continental crust, oceanic crust melts at which of the following?W) Lower temperaturesX) The same temperatureY) Higher temperaturesZ) Higher pressures and temperaturesANSWER: Y) HIGHER TEMPERATURESBONUS8) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following sets of two variables controls how fast a soil forms?W) Type of parent rock and climate X) Type and age of parent rockY) Temperature and pressureZ) Residual and transported soilANSWER: W) TYPE OF PARENT ROCK AND CLIMATE Round 12 - Page 4TOSS-UP9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Stating your answer in kilojoules per mole, what is the change in Gibbs free energy for a reaction at equilibrium?ANSWER: 0BONUS9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following actions would NOT change the strength of an air core electromagnet?W) Increasing the amount of currentX) Changing the current’s directionY) Inserting an iron core inside the loop Z) Increasing the number of loopsANSWER: X) CHANGING THE CURRENT’S DIRECTIONTOSS-UP10) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following types of light bulbs is most energy efficient? W) Fluorescent X) Incandescent Y) HalogenZ) White L.E.D.ANSWER: Z) WHITE L.E.D.BONUS10) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes why horizontal axis turbines produce more power than vertical axis turbines?W) Horizontal turbines are facing the wind at all timesX) The power coefficient for a horizontal turbine is twice the power coefficient of a vertical turbineY) Vertical turbines are placed at lower heightsZ) The Betz limit specifies that power extracted from the wind for vertical axis turbines is limited to 57%ANSWER: X) THE POWER COEFFICIENT OF A HORIZONTAL TURBINE IS TWICE THE POWER COEFFICIENT OF A VERTICAL TURBINERound 12 - Page 5TOSS-UP11) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice How many net molecules of ATP does glycolysis [gly- KOL-uh-sis] produce?W) 2 X) 3 Y) 4 Z) 6ANSWER: W) 211) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true about theplant Mimosa pudica [mee-MO-suh POO-dee-kuh]?W) It is an herbX) Its leaves fold inward and droop when it is touched or shakenY) It is native to AfricaZ) Aqueous [AY-kwee-uhs] extracts of its roots inhibit cobra venomANSWER: Y) IT IS NATIVE TO AFRICATOSS-UPBONUS 12) MATH Short Answer What values cannot be part of the domain for the following function: 𝑥(𝑥 − 2)f(x) = (𝑥 + 3)(𝑥 − 5) [f of x equals the fraction with numerator x times the quantity x minus 2 and denominator open parenthesis, x plus 3, close parenthesis, open parenthesis, x minus 5, close parenthesis]? ANSWER: -3 AND 512) MATH Short Answer You have a sugar cone that has a radius of 3 inches, and a height of 8 inches. You drop a perfect sphere of ice cream with a radius of 3 inches onto the cone so that the ball of ice cream is now half in the cone, half out. Providing your answer in terms of pi, what is the volume in cubic inches of the air space left in the cone?ANSWER: 6πBONUSRound 12 - Page 6TOSS-UP13) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Many lakes in agricultural regions are eutrophic [yoo-TRO-fik] due to which of the following?W) Excessive nutrientsX) Minimal algae growthY) Increased number of irrigation wells Z) Excessive sunlightANSWER: W) EXCESSIVE NUTRIENTSBONUS13) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true about the recently discovered circumbinary planet?W) It orbits two starsX) It is about 200 light years from EarthY) It was detected by the James Webb space telescope Z) It is cold and gaseousANSWER: Y) IT WAS DETECTED BY THE JAMES WEBB SPACE TELESCOPETOSS-UP14) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice An individual with Turner syndrome has which of the following genotypes? W) XO X) XYY Y) XXY Z) XXYYANSWER: W) XOBONUS14) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What polysaccharide [pol-ee-SAK-uh-ryd], found in yogurt, chocolate milk, toothpaste, and deodorant, comes from algae or seaweed, and can be used in the place of animal-based products like gelatin?ANSWER: CARRAGEENANRound 12 - Page 7TOSS-UP15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following can astronomers use to directly measure the distance between a star and Earth?W) Parallax X) Brightness Y) Blue shift Z) SizeANSWER: W) PARALLAXBONUS15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice During the March equinox, at which of the following latitudes is the Sun’s noon position directly overhead?W) 46.5° North X) 23.5° North Y) 23.5° South Z) 0°ANSWER: Z) 0° TOSS-UP16) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following ocean life zones contains the least variety of ocean life?W) IntertidalX) NeriticY) Bathyal [BATH-ee-uhl] Z) AbyssalANSWER: Z) ABYSSALBONUS16) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What weather phenomenon has the following characteristics: 1) large-scale wind circulation around a central region of high atmospheric pressure; 2) it circulates clockwise in the Northern Hemisphere and counterclockwise in the Southern Hemisphere; 3) it usually advances at 20 to 30 miles per hour.ANSWER: ANTICYCLONERound 12 - Page 8TOSS-UP17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In thermodynamics, the change in enthalpy [EN- thal-pee] of a process can be equated with heat transferred if which of the following quantities is held constant?W) VolumeX) PressureY) Temperature Z) EntropyANSWER: X) PRESSUREBONUS17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A car is moving along a road when the passenger side front tire hits a snow drift. Identify all of the following that happens to the motion of the car: 1) It speeds up, 2) It slows down, 3) It veers towards the right, 4) It veers towards the left.ANSWER: 2 AND 3TOSS-UP18) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following fuels is cooled cryogenically to -260° Fahrenheit?W) Compressed coal X) Liquefied shale gas Y) Liquefied natural gas Z) Purified gasolineANSWER: Y) LIQUEFIED NATURAL GASBONUS18) ENERGY Short Answer What are the two gases that municipal solid waste produces in large concentrations?ANSWER: CARBON DIOXIDE, METHANETOSS-UP19) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer A sea cucumber is an example of an organism that displays what type of symmetry?ANSWER: RADIAL (ACCEPT: PENTAMOROUS, BILATERAL)BONUS19) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Identify all of the following five organisms that are considered sac fungi: 1) morel mushroom, 2) powdery mildew, 3) blue-green mold, 4) puffball, 5) stem rot.ANSWER: 1, 2, 3 (ACCEPT: MOREL MUSHROOM, POWDERY MILDEW, BLUE-GREEN MOLD)TOSS-UP 20) MATH Short Answer Triangle CAT has sides measuring 6 inches, 8 inches, and 10 inches. Triangle DOG has sides measuring 3 inches, 4 inches, and 5 inches. In either order, what is the ratio of the measures of the smallest angles in the two triangles?BONUSANSWER: 1 TO 1 (ACCEPT: 1)20) MATH Multiple Choice The distance between the points (11, 1) and (-3.5, 16.5) is betweenwhich of the following pairs of numbers?W) 20 and 21 X) 21 and 22 Y) 22 and 23 Z) 23 and 24ANSWER: X) 21 AND 22TOSS-UP21) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the process of coating a corrosive metal with a thin layer of zinc?ANSWER: GALVANIZATIONBONUS21) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name all of the following four cells or organisms that may contain chloroplasts: 1) chlamydomonas [kla-mid-uh-MOH-nas], 2) plasmodium, 3) diatoms, 4) spirogyra [spy-ruh-JY-ruh].ANSWER: 1, 3, 4 (ACCEPT: CHLAMYDOMONAS, DIATOMS, SPIROGYRA)TOSS-UP22) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What planet in our solar system has retrograde rotation?ANSWER: VENUS (ALSO ACCEPT URANUS)BONUS22) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the name of the largest calving glacier in North America?ANSWER: HUBBARDTOSS-UP23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice According to molecular orbital theory, which of the following molecules contains pi bonds?W) AmmoniaX) Molecular hydrogen Y) Molecular nitrogen Z) WaterANSWER: Y) MOLECULAR NITROGENBONUS23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following molecules contains the largest bond angle?W) Sulfur hexafluoride [hek-suh-FLOHR-yd] X) WaterY) Carbon dioxideZ) Boron trifluorideANSWER: Y) CARBON DIOXIDE24)MATH Short Answer If5x+3y=8and6x+2y=10,whatisy–x? ANSWER: -2BONUSTOSS-UP24) MATH Short Answer An aquarium is 12 inches long, 10 inches wide, and 10 inches deep. It is filled with 8 inches of water. A rock is dropped into the water, and the water level rises 2 inches. What is the volume of the rock in cubic inches?ANSWER: 240Round 12 - Page 12TOSS-UP25) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice A trans-Pacific flight passenger experiences difficulty adjusting to the difference in time zones. Which of the following supplements may ease the symptoms of jet lag?W) Melatonin X) Progestin Y) CortisolZ) ThymosinANSWER: W) MELATONINBONUS25) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What are the three basic shapes of bacteria?ANSWER: COCCUS (ACCEPT: SPHERE OR OVAL), BACILLUS (ACCEPT: ROD), SPIRALRound 12 - Page 13