ROUND 7          TOSS-UP1) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the purpose of cones in gymnosperms? ANSWER: SEXUAL REPRODUCTIONBONUS1) BIOLOGY Short Answer Name the plant type that has one seed leaf when it germinates, leaf veins that are parallel to each other, and includes plants such as corn, wheat, lilies, daffodils, and palms.ANSWER: MONOCOTS [ACCEPT: MONOCOTYLEDON (read as: moh-noh-koh-ti-LEE-dohn)]________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP2) MATH Short Answer The lengths of two sides of a triangle are 4 and 9. If the triangle is isosceles, what is the length of the third side?ANSWER: 9BONUS2) MATH Short Answer Rebekah wants to fill a spherical piñata with candy. If the radius of her piñata is 6 inches, what is the volume in cubic inches of her piñata in terms of pi?ANSWER: 288πRound 7 Page 1TOSS-UP3) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What ice sheet on Earth contains the largest volume of ice?ANSWER: EAST ANTARCTIC ICE SHEETBONUS3) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The West Antarctic Ice Sheet and the East Antarctic Ice Sheet are separated by what mountain range?W) Transantarctic Mountains X) Admiralty MountainsY) Shackleton RangeZ) East Antarctic RangesANSWER: W) TRANSANTARCTIC MOUNTAINS________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP4) MATH Short Answer If the volume of a cube is 64 cubic centimeters, then what is the surface area of the cube in square centimeters?ANSWER: 96BONUS4) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following categories of statistical plots displays the first, second, and third quartiles for the data that it represents?W) Box plot X) Scatter plot Y) HistogramZ) Pie chartANSWER: W) BOX PLOTRound 7Page 2TOSS-UP5) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice What are the products for the complete combustion of methane?W) Carbon and hydrogenX) Carbon dioxide and hydrogen Y) Carbon monoxide and water Z) Carbon dioxide and waterANSWER: Z) CARBON DIOXIDE AND WATERBONUS5) CHEMISTRY Short Answer For the complete combustion of butane, butane plus oxygen produces carbon dioxide and water vapor. What is the balanced equation for the combustion of butane?ANSWER: 2C4H10 + 13O2   (read as: yields) 8CO2 + 10H2O ________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) PHYSICS Multiple Choice The mass of a raindrop is 4 milligrams. Which of the following represents the correct mass in grams of the raindrop?W) 4 × 10-3 X) 4 × 10-1 Y) 4 × 103 Z) 4 × 106ANSWER: W) 4 × 10-3BONUS6) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A freely falling object has a constant acceleration of 9.8 meters per second squared. Which of the following is correct?W) The object’s displacement changes by 9.8 meters every second squaredX) The object’s acceleration increases by 9.8 meters per second squared each second Y) The object travels 9.8 meters each secondZ) The object’s speed increases by 9.8 meters per second each secondANSWER: Z) THE OBJECT’S SPEED INCREASES BY 9.8 METERS PER SECOND EACH SECONDRound 7 Page 3TOSS-UP7) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice In which sphere is the “bad” ozone, a volatile compound that contributes to smog, located?W) Stratosphere X) BiosphereY) Troposphere Z) LithosphereANSWER: Y) TROPOSPHEREBONUS7) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer In which sphere is the “good” ozone that absorbs harmful ultraviolet rays located?ANSWER: STRATOSPHERE________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP8) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Ducklings learn to recognize and follow the first moving object that they see, usually their mother. What is this behavior called?W) InstinctX) ImprintingY) Remote sensingZ) Classical conditioningANSWER: X) IMPRINTINGBONUS8) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice A pigeon is placed in a box. Sooner or later, the pigeon accidentally presses a button or lever that releases food. Eventually, the pigeon learns how to press the button whenever it wants food. This kind of learning is called:W) HabituationX) Classical conditioning Y) Insight learningZ) Operant conditioningANSWER: Z) OPERANT CONDITIONINGRound 7Page 4TOSS-UP9) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Determine the solubility product constant (or Ksp) of silver bromide, given that its molar solubility is 5.71   10-7 moles per liter.W) 3.26   10-13 X) 5.71   10-7 Y) 1.14   10-6 Z) 2.14   10-4ANSWER: W) 3.26   10-13BONUS9) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Which of the following are strong bases in aqueous solution: 1) potassium hydroxide, 2) ammonia, 3) sodium chloride, 4) calcium hydroxide, or 5) beryllium hydroxide?ANSWER: POTASSIUM HYDROXIDE AND CALCIUM HYDROXIDE (ACCEPT: 1 AND 4)________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is most likely a descendent of dinosaurs?W) FrogX) Cockroach Y) TurtleZ) RobinANSWER: Z) ROBINBONUS10) BIOLOGY Short Answer Oxygen-rich blood leaves the left ventricle to enter the largest blood vessel in the body. What is this blood vessel called?ANSWER: AORTARound 7 Page 5TOSS-UP11) PHYSICS Multiple Choice A poorly designed fishing bob does not float in a sucrose solution. Which of the following actions could be taken so the fishing bob would float?W) Increase the volume of the solutionX) Decrease the volume of the solutionY) Increase the concentration of the solution Z) Decrease the concentration of the solutionANSWER: Y) INCREASE THE CONCENTRATION OF THE SOLUTIONBONUS11) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Water tank A has width W1 and tank B has width W2, where W1 > W2. The two water tanks are the same height, H. If both tanks are completely filled with water, which of the following is true about the water pressure at the bottom of the tank?W) Pressure cannot be determinedX) The pressure is greater in tank A Y) The pressure is greater in tank B Z) Both tanks have the same pressureANSWER: Z) BOTH TANKS HAVE THE SAME PRESSURE________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP12) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the most abundant element in the universe? ANSWER: HYDROGENBONUS12) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Our solar system formed approximately how many billion years ago?W) 2 X) 3 Y) 5 Z) 7ANSWER: Y) 5Round 7Page 6TOSS-UP13) MATH Short Answer Given the function y = 4x -x^2, what is the largest possible value for y? ANSWER: 4BONUS13) MATH Short Answer Express the following in standard polynomial form: (3x+2)^3  (read as: the quantity 3x plus 2 cubed)ANSWER: 27x^3 + 54x^2 + 36x + 8________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP14) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice In the 1980s, Europeans began to be diagnosed with mad cow disease, a disease which affects the brain. What is the type of infectious agent that causes this disease?  W) Virus X) Bacteria Y) Fungi Z) PrionANSWER: Z) PRIONBONUS14) BIOLOGY Short Answer The prions that cause mad cow disease lack DNA. What does current research suggest that prions are?ANSWER: ABNORMAL ISOFORM PROTEINS (ACCEPT: MISSHAPED ISOFORM PROTEINS, ABNORMAL PROTEINS)Round 7 Page 7TOSS-UP15) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice What is the mass of an electron relative to a proton?W) 9.1 x 10-31 X) 8.2 x 10-14 Y) 1/1836Z) 0.51ANSWER: Y) 1/1836BONUS15) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Sulfuric acid is used to neutralize a solution of sodium hydroxide. Calculate the number of moles of sodium hydroxide required to completely neutralize two moles of sulfuric acid.ANSWER: 4________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following describes an electromagnet?W) Straight wire carrying a currentX) Current-carrying wire wrapped around a core Y) Permanent bar magnetZ) Rock that is iron attractingANSWER: X) CURRENT-CARRYING WIRE WRAPPED AROUND A COREBONUS16) PHYSICS Short Answer A voltage difference of 10 volts delivers how much power, in watts, to a 1-ohm resistor?ANSWER: 100Round 7 Page 8TOSS-UP17) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a strong acid?W) Hydrofluoric acid X) Hydrochloric acid Y) Hydrobromic acid Z) Hydroiodic acidANSWER: W) HYDROFLUORIC ACIDBONUS17) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following would be the resulting pH from the reaction of equal amounts of a strong acid with a strong base?W) Less than 7X) Equal to 7Y) More than 7Z) The reaction is independent of the pHANSWER: X) EQUAL TO 7________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP18) MATH Short Answer Where do the lines y = (2x/3) + 5 and 3y = 2x - 21 intersect? ANSWER: THEY DON’T (ACCEPT: THEY’RE PARALLEL, NULL SET, EMPTY SET)BONUS18) MATH Short Answer Where do the lines 3x - 4y =12 and 5x + 4y =20 intersect? ANSWER: (4,0) ALSO ACCEPT: X = 4 AND Y = 0Round 7Page 9TOSS-UP19) ENERGY Multiple Choice The largest reserve of energy in the United States is in which of the following?W) Natural gas X) CoalY) NuclearZ) Offshore oilANSWER: X) COALBONUS19) ENERGY Multiple Choice The Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) produces about what percentage of the world’s crude oil?W) 20% X) 40% Y) 60% Z) 80%ANSWER: X) 40%________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer The world’s largest desert is on which continent? ANSWER: ANTARCTICABONUS20) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What property of many meteors makes Antarctica a good place to go meteor hunting?ANSWER: DARK COLORRound 7 Page 10TOSS-UP21) PHYSICS Multiple Choice What type of collision occurs when two objects collide and stick together?W) Partially elastic X) Perfectly elastic Y) Partially inelastic Z) Perfectly inelasticANSWER: Z) PERFECTLY INELASTICBONUS21) PHYSICS Multiple Choice For all collisions, all of the following properties are conserved except:W) Total massX) Center of mass Y) Kinetic energy Z) MomentumANSWER: Y) KINETIC ENERGY________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP22) ENERGY Short Answer What is the final three-carbon product of glycolysis? ANSWER: PYRUVATE (read as: py-RUH-vayt) [ACCEPT: PYRUVIC (read as: py-RUH-vik)ACID, CH3COCO2H]BONUS22) ENERGY Short Answer Which acidic compound is the major product of fermentation in skeletal muscle?ANSWER: LACTIC ACIDRound 7 Page 11TOSS-UP23) MATH Short Answer Two triangles are similar. If the smaller one has a perimeter of 18 and the ratio between them is 5:3 (read as: 5 to 3), what is the perimeter of the larger triangle?ANSWER: 30BONUS23) MATH Short Answer If all of the interior angles of a polygon sum to 3060 degrees, how many sides does the polygon have?ANSWER: 19________________________________________________________________________TOSS-UP24) ENERGY Multiple Choice Ocean thermal energy conversion systems convert solar radiation to electric power. Which of the following describes the source of energy in ocean thermal energy conversion systems?W) Magma below the ocean floorX) Oceanic thermal ventsY) Wave motionZ) The difference in temperatures between surface and deep watersANSWER: Z) THE DIFFERENCE IN TEMPERATURES BETWEEN SURFACE AND DEEP WATERSBONUS24) ENERGY Multiple Choice What is the minimum temperature difference, in degrees Celsius, needed to develop an ocean thermal energy conversion system?W) 10 ̊ X) 15 ̊ Y) 20 ̊ Z) 25 ̊ANSWER: Y) 20 ̊Round 7Page 12TOSS-UP25) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following describes Jupiter's great red spot?W) A stormX) An auroraY) A magnetotail Z) A volcanoANSWER: W) A STORM25) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Saturn's rings are made mostly of: ANSWER: ICEBONUSRound 7Page 13