ROUND 5
          TOSS-UP
1) ENERGY Multiple Choice Bioplastics are plastics derived from plant sources, rather than petroleum. Which of the following is NOT a way in which bioplastics can be made?
W) Intracellular production by the fermentation of a feedstock
X) Engineering a crop to grow the plastic within the plant itself
Y) Fermentation of a cereal to make precursors, which would then be processed into bioplastics Z) Fermentation of the waste water from the conventional manufacture of corn syrup
ANSWER: Z) FERMENTATION OF THE WASTE WATER FROM THE CONVENTIONAL MANUFACTURE OF CORN SYRUP
BONUS
1) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT an accurate representation of a limitation on the production and use of bioplastics?
W) Using crops to produce plastic diverts plants from the food supply X) Bioplastics are unlikely to disintegrate in a landfill
Y) Bioplastics produce a variety of pollutants when burned
Z) Individuals at home would find it difficult to compost bioplastics
ANSWER: Y) BIOPLASTICS PRODUCE A VARIETY OF POLLUTANTS WHEN BURNED
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
2) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Name the following compound: N2O4.
ANSWER: DINITROGEN TETROXIDE (ALSO ACCEPT: NITROGEN TETROXIDE,
NITROGEN PEROXIDE)
BONUS
2) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the equation for the combustion of octane? ANSWER: 2C8H18 + 25O2 18H2O + 16CO2
 Round 5
Page 1
TOSS-UP
3) MATH Multiple choice Psoriasis, a chronic skin disorder caused by the immune system, affects 1% to 2% of Caucasians. If there are 16,098,000 Caucasians in New York State, about how many would be expected to have psoriasis?
W) Between 16,000 and 32,000
X) Between 160,000 and 325,000
Y) Between 1,600,000 and 3,220,000 Z) 241,470
ANSWER: X) BETWEEN 160,000 AND 325,000
BONUS
3) MATH Short Answer What is 224% of 17? Provide your answer as a decimal to the nearest integer.
ANSWER: 38
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
4) PHYSICS Multiple Choice When we measure the distance traveled by an object moving from one point to another, which of the following is always true?
W) Magnitude of displacement is greater than or equal to distance X) Magnitude of displacement equals distance
Y) Magnitude of displacement is greater than distance
Z) Magnitude of displacement is less than or equal to distance
ANSWER: Z) MAGNITUDE OF DISPLACEMENT LESS THAN OR EQUAL TO DISTANCE
BONUS
4) PHYSICS Short Answer Jos� and Rosie were spelunking in the caves in the Black Hills of South Dakota. They crawled through a multitude of passages, traveling a net 3 kilometers westward, 4 kilometers south, and 50 meters up. What was magnitude of their overall displacement to the nearest kilometer?
ANSWER: 5
Round 5 Page 2
TOSS-UP
5) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice In the last 4 billion years, the average brightness of the Sun has:
W) Increased
X) Decreased
Y) Stayed the same
Z) Increased, then decreased
ANSWER: W) INCREASED
BONUS
5) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What are explosive events associated with sunspots that cause spectacular auroras in Earth�s upper atmosphere near its magnetic poles?
ANSWER: SOLAR FLARES
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
6) PHYSICS Short Answer The Lorentz force acting on a particle moving in electric and magnetic fields depends on what two characteristics of the particle?
ANSWER: CHARGE AND VELOCITY (DO NOT ACCEPT: SPEED)
BONUS
6) PHYSICS Short Answer The interior light in a car is left on for three hours. The light draws 1 ampere from the battery. How many coulombs flowed through the light?
ANSWER: 10,800
Round 5 Page 3
TOSS-UP
7) ENERGY Multiple Choice Where is most of the uranium used in the United States mined?
W) United States X) Middle East
Y) Africa
Z) South America
ANSWER: W) UNITED STATES
BONUS
7) ENERGY Short Answer Uranium is usually found in trace concentrations, so it generally has to be extracted from uranium ore. Name the term for concentrated uranium oxide, which can vary in color from yellow, orange, and dark green to brown and black, produced from uranium ore in the uranium recovery process.
ANSWER: YELLOWCAKE (ACCEPT: U3O8, TRIURANIUM OCTOXIDE)
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
8) MATH Short Answer For which values of g is the following inequality true: 6g + 4 > 9g - 11? ANSWER: g < 5
BONUS
8) MATH Multiple Choice If f(x) (read as: f of x) represents the function whose graph is the standard normal distribution curve, then how do the inflection points on the curve for 2f(x) (read as: 2 f of x) compare to those of f(x)?
W) Both curves have the same inflection points
X) The 2f(x) inflection points are twice as far apart but the same height
Y) The 2f(x) inflection points are twice as high but the same distance apart Z) The 2f(x) inflection points are both twice as far apart and twice as high
ANSWER: Y) THE 2F(X) INFLECTION POINTS ARE TWICE AS HIGH BUT THE SAME DISTANCE APART
Round 5 Page 4
TOSS-UP
9) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following forms of energy does NOT require bulk motion of physical matter through space?
W) Radiant
X) Nuclear
Y) Electrical
Z) Hydropower
ANSWER: W) RADIANT

BONUS
9) ENERGY Short Answer Ionizing radiation, which can penetrate cells and create ions in cell contents, is generated by which two kinds of electromagnetic radiation?
ANSWER: X-RAYS AND GAMMA RAYS
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
10) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of these atmospheric layers is furthest from the Earth's surface?
W) Stratosphere X) Mesosphere Y) Thermosphere Z) Troposphere
ANSWER: Y) THERMOSPHERE
BONUS
10) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer What is the name of the atmospheric layer that is the closest to the ground?
ANSWER: TROPOSPHERE
Round 5 Page 5
TOSS-UP
11) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Spiders can build webs without a parent showing them how, and baby birds can beg for food from the moment they are hatched. These are examples of:
W) Imprinting
X) Stimulus and response Y) Instinct
Z) External motivations
ANSWER: Y) INSTINCT
BONUS
11) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Honeybees leave the hive to find food. Upon finding food, honeybees return to the hive and dance to tell others how to find the food. This behavior is an example of:
W) Classical conditioning X) Migration
Y) Insight learning
Z) Visual communication
ANSWER: Z) VISUAL COMMUNICATION
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
12) MATH Short Answer Solve the following equation for x: log2 x = 5 (read as: log base 2 of x equals 5).
ANSWER: 32
BONUS
12) MATH Short Answer Consider the polynomial 5x2 + 13x + 10. How many and what kind of roots does it have?
ANSWER: TWO COMPLEX ROOTS
Round 5 Page 6
TOSS-UP
13) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a greenhouse gas?
W) Helium
X) Methane
Y) Carbon dioxide Z) Water vapor
ANSWER: W) HELIUM
14) MATH Short Answer What is the point of intersection of these two lines: y = -2x + 3 and y = 3x - 7?
ANSWER: (2, -1)
BONUS
13) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer There are many sources and sinks on Earth for carbon dioxide. Give the most biologically significant source and sink, respectively.
ANSWER: RESPIRATION AND PHOTOSYNTHESIS (IN THIS ORDER) ALSO ACCEPT: SOURCE IS RESPIRATION AND SINK IS PHOTOSYNTHESIS (IN ANY ORDER)
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
14) MATH Multiple Choice If 14 is a factor of the whole number x, which of the following also must be a factor of x?
W) 4 X) 7 Y) 10 Z) 28
ANSWER: X) 7
BONUS
Round 5
Page 7
TOSS-UP
15) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is standard temperature, in Kelvin, as defined in ideal gas equations?
ANSWER: 273 KELVIN
BONUS
15) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice To calculate the pressure within a known volume of gas, which of the following pieces of information is NOT needed?
W) Temperature X) Specific gravity Y) Moles of gas Z) Gas constant
ANSWER: X) SPECIFIC GRAVITY
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
16) PHYSICS Short Answer Lynne is standing still on a sidewalk. What is the name of the concept which describes why the siren of an approaching fire truck has a higher frequency than that of a fire truck that is stopped?
ANSWER: DOPPLER SHIFT (ACCEPT: DOPPLER EFFECT)
BONUS
16) PHYSICS Short Answer Which theory attempts to unify physics by producing all known forces and particles as different vibrations of a single substance?
ANSWER: STRING THEORY
Round 5 Page 8
TOSS-UP
17) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer A map composed of constant elevation lines is known as what kind of map?
ANSWER: TOPOGRAPHIC
BONUS
17) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice What quality is represented by isobars when looking at a weather map?
W) Pressure
X) Temperature
Y) Cloud height
Z) Water vapor content
ANSWER: W) PRESSURE
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
18) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice When you touch a hot object and quickly draw your hand away, this is known as:
W) The withdrawal impulse X) The withdrawal reflex
Y) A reflexive habit
Z) Learned withdrawal
ANSWER: X) THE WITHDRAWAL REFLEX
BONUS
18) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice A withdrawal reflex is initiated by skin receptors that detect external stimuli. The sensory neurons then pass the message on to the spinal cord, where the sensory nerve terminals synapse with which of the following?
W) Synaptic neurons X) Intersynapses
Y) Sensory synapse Z) Interneurons
ANSWER: Z) INTERNEURONS
Round 5
Page 9
TOSS-UP
19) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What best describes a solid whose atoms are arranged in a regular pattern?
ANSWER: CRYSTAL
BONUS
19) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice The unit cell in a crystal system may have one of several forms. Which of the following describes a cubic unit cell with one identical particle in the center of the cell?
W) Simple cubic
X) Orthohombic
Y) Triclinic
Z) Body-centered cubic
ANSWER: Z) BODY-CENTERED CUBIC
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
20) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Adenosine triphosphate (ATP) and glucose are both examples of substances containing what kind of energy?
W) Heat
X) Kinetic
Y) Chemical Z) Mechanical
ANSWER: Y) CHEMICAL
BONUS
20) BIOLOGY Short Answer What happens when the third phosphate group is removed from ATP by hydrolysis, forming ADP and phosphate?
ANSWER: ENERGY IS RELEASED
Round 5 Page 10
TOSS-UP
21) PHYSICS Multiple Choice What is the process by which nuclear fission produces energy?
W) Combining lighter nuclei into heavier nuclei
X) Increasing the number of protons a nucleus contains Y) Changing an electron's spin state following excitation Z) Splitting heavier nuclei into lighter nuclei
ANSWER: Z) SPLITTING HEAVIER NUCLEI INTO LIGHTER NUCLEI
BONUS
21) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a challenge in using nuclear fusion as a controlled generator of power?
W) The fuels needed for fusion reactions are expensive and difficult to find
X) Containing the reaction once it has started is difficult
Y) Materials used to contain fusion reactions are affected by the high radiation levels Z) Extremely high temperatures are needed to start the reaction
ANSWER: W) THE FUELS NEEDED FOR FUSION REACTIONS ARE EXPENSIVE AND DIFFICULT TO FIND
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
22) EARTH AND SPACE Multiple Choice The core of the Earth is primarily made of iron and which additional element?
W) Mercury X) Nickel Y) Zinc
Z) Barium
ANSWER: X) NICKEL
BONUS
22) EARTH AND SPACE Short Answer Put the following terms in order from the center of the Earth to the surface: mantle, crust, outer core, inner core.
ANSWER: INNER CORE, OUTER CORE, MANTLE, CRUST
Round 5 Page 11
TOSS-UP
23) MATH Short Answer What is  3/4 + (-5/6) as a fraction in simplest form? ANSWER: -1/12
BONUS
23) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following numbers is relatively prime with 15?
W) 348 X) 350 Y) 352 Z) 354
ANSWER: Y) 352
________________________________________________________________________
TOSS-UP
24) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the name for a segment of DNA that carries instructions for synthesizing proteins?
ANSWER: GENE
BONUS
24) BIOLOGY Short Answer What process is best described as the fusion of gametes to produce a new organism?
ANSWER: FERTILIZATION
 Round 5 Page 12
TOSS-UP
25) CHEMISTRY Short Answer A pH of of 2 has what pOH? ANSWER: 12
BONUS
25) CHEMISTRY Short Answer If the electromotive force of the anode in a galvanic cell is -0.76 volts and the electromotive force of the cathode is 0.34 volts, calculate the electromotive force of the cell in volts. Provide your answer as a decimal to the nearest hundredth.
ANSWER: +1.10 (DO NOT ACCEPT: -1.10)
Round 5 Page 13
