ROUND 11 TOSS-UP1) MATH Multiple Choice A quadrilateral may be inscribed in a circle if and only if which of the following is true?W) It is a rectangleX) It is a squareY) It is equilateralZ) Its opposite angles are supplementaryANSWER: Z) ITS OPPOSITE ANGLES ARE SUPPLEMENTARYBONUS1) MATH Short Answer If the range of the set of five numbers {4, 3, x, 9, and 8} is 12, what are the possible values of x?ANSWER: 15 AND -3 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP2) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, identify all of the following five animals that are odd-toed ungulates: 1) horse, 2) zebra, 3) onager, 4) alpaca, 5) tapir.ANSWER: HORSE, ZEBRA, ONAGER, AND TAPIR (ACCEPT: 1, 2, 3, AND 5)BONUS2) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer All the nitrogenous bases from a DNA molecule are removed. Of the nitrogenous base molecules, 27% were guanine (read as: GWAH-neen) molecules. Approximately what percentage of the nitrogenous base molecules were thymine molecules?ANSWER: 23%          Round 11 Page 1TOSS-UP3) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the large oceanic circulation system that moves cold salty water from the surface to the bottom of the ocean near Greenland?ANSWER: NORTH ATLANTIC DEEP OCEAN CURRENT (ACCEPT: THERMOHALINE CIRCULATION, GREAT OCEAN CONVEYER)BONUS3) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer Unlike algae in lakes, marine algae are more likely to grow rapidly after what element is added to their natural environment?ANSWER: IRON _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP4) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following elements would be the MOST metallic?W) IronX) CopperY) TitaniumZ) GermaniumANSWER: Y) TITANIUMBONUS4) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer An object with a mass of 5 kilograms travels around a horizontal circle with a radius of 2 meters at a speed of 3 meters per second in the counterclockwise direction. In meters per second squared, what is the centripetal acceleration, in terms of both magnitude and direction, when the direction of the velocity is north?ANSWER: 4.5 WESTRound 11 Page 2TOSS-UP5) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Name the biome characterized by low precipitation, variable temperatures, and soils rich in minerals but poor in organic material.ANSWER: DESERTBONUS5) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements best describes the primary difference between animal centrosomes and plant centrosomes?W) Plant centrosomes have a rough exterior made of cellulose X) Animal centrosomes use microfilamentsY) Plant centrosomes do not have centriolesZ) Animal centrosomes are in the cytoplasmANSWER: Y) PLANT CENTROSOMES DO NOT HAVE CENTRIOLES _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of analogous structures resulting from convergent evolution?W) Feathers on a bird to feathers on a dinosaurX) Forelimbs on a human to forelimbs on a chimpanzee Y) Flippers on a dolphin to forelimbs on a humanZ) Webbed feet on a duck to webbed feet on a frogANSWER: Z) WEBBED FEET ON A DUCK TO WEBBED FEET ON A FROGBONUS6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer A certain isotope of oxygen is unstable and emits a positron to form a stable isotope of another atom. Name the element produced.ANSWER: NITROGENRound 11 Page 3TOSS-UP7) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following best represents the sum of the reciprocals of all positive integers?W) 2X) π2/6 Y) 9Z) InfinityANSWER: Z) INFINITYBONUS7) MATH Multiple Choice A cylindrical tin can has a diameter of 4 inches and a height of 5 inches. Approximately how much more volume, in cubic inches, would it have if the diameter were increased to 6 inches?W) 63 X) 79 Y) 141 Z) 157ANSWER: X) 79 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the chemical formula for iron (III) oxide? ANSWER: Fe2O3BONUS8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following kinds of reaction does the following equation exemplify: CH2S + 6 F2 → (read as: yields) CF4 + 2 HF + SF6 + heat?W) Acid-baseX) Phase changeY) Oxidation reduction Z) Double displacementANSWER: Y) OXIDATION REDUCTIONRound 11Page 4TOSS-UP9) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term for the wave of muscular contractions that propels food down the esophagus (read as: i-SOH-fah-guhs)?ANSWER: PERISTALSISBONUS9) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a relatively short fragment of DNA created on the lagging strand during DNA replication?W) DNA polymerase X) Okazaki fragment Y) Thymine dimerZ) Flap endonucleaseANSWER: X) OKAZAKI FRAGMENT _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer A hormone enters the blood stream and binds to specific receptors; what is the general name for a cell that expresses the receptor for a given hormone?ANSWER: TARGET CELLBONUS10) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer For a certain trait, there are three alleles, A, B, and C, and each locus contains 2 alleles. The frequency of allele A is 0.4 and the frequency of allele B is 0.1. What percentage of the population has either allele B or allele C present in their genome?ANSWER: 84%Round 11 Page 5TOSS-UP11) MATH Multiple Choice The line with equation y = −3x + 10 has points in every quadrant EXCEPT:W) I X) II Y) III Z) IVANSWER: Y) IIIBONUS11) MATH Short Answer How many vertices and edges, respectively, does a regular octahedron have?ANSWER: VERTICES = 6, EDGES = 12 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP12) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is at the base of the hydrothermal vent community food chain?W) Symbiotic phytoplankton X) Chemosynthetic archaea Y) Marine snowZ) Photosynthetic bacteriaANSWER: X) CHEMOSYNTHETIC ARCHAEABONUS12) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term for the sequences of rocks that make up the ocean floor and are composed from top to bottom of pillow basalts, sheeted dikes, gabbro, and peridotite (read as: peh-RI-doh-tyt)?ANSWER: OPHIOLITE (ACCEPT: OPHIOLITE SERIES)Round 11 Page 6TOSS-UP13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following groups consists entirely of allotropes of carbon?W) Lonsdaleite (read as: lohnz-day-LEET), graphene, and fullerene X) Crystal, diamond, and graphiteY) Graphite, graphene, and crystalZ) Fullerene, lonsdaleite (read as: lohnz-day-LEET), and alamositeANSWER: W) LONSDALEITE, GRAPHENE, AND FULLERENEBONUS13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Providing your answer in scientific notation with two significant digits, a coulomb of charge is equal to the electrical charge of how many electrons?ANSWER: 6.2 x 1018 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP14) ENERGY Multiple Choice The U.S. Energy Information Administration is projecting that primary energy consumption of which of the following energy sources will grow by more than 4% per year between 2007 and 2035?W) CoalX) Natural gas Y) NuclearZ) Liquid biofuelsANSWER: Z) LIQUID BIOFUELS14) ENERGY Short Answer What country has the world’s largest offshore wind farm? ANSWER: UNITED KINGDOMBONUSRound 11Page 7TOSS-UP15) MATH Short Answer What is the product of complex numbers (2 + 3i)(2 − 3i) (read as: the quantity 2 plus 3 i times the quantity 2 minus 3 i)?ANSWER: 13BONUS15) MATH Short Answer Sue leaves for school at 7 a.m., walking at a rate of 4 miles per hour. Her sister, Mary, leaves home at 7:30 a.m., riding her bike at a rate of 8 miles per hour. At what time will Mary meet up with Sue?ANSWER: 8:00 a.m. _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the layer of the ocean in which temperature changes rapidly with depth?ANSWER: THERMOCLINEBONUS16) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the process by which physical and chemical changes occur in a sediment after it has been deposited and buried?ANSWER: DIAGENESISRound 11 Page 8TOSS-UP17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a substance that can accept a pair of electrons from another substance?W) Brønsted acid X) Brønsted base Y) Lewis acidZ) Arrhenius baseANSWER: Y) LEWIS ACIDBONUS17) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following states that no two electrons can have the same four quantum numbers?W) Pauli exclusion principleX) Aufbau principleY) Hund’s ruleZ) Heisenberg uncertainty principleANSWER: W) PAULI EXCLUSION PRINCIPLETOSS-UP18) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice A crystal’s habit that is plant-like in shape is called which of the following?W) Dendritic X) Bladed Y) Massive Z) ReniformANSWER: W) DENDRITICBONUS18) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, identify all of the following four choices that can appear as silicate mineral structures: 1) single chain, 2) double chain, 3) sheet, 4) three-dimensional framework.ANSWER: SINGLE CHAIN, DOUBLE CHAIN, SHEET, THREE-DIMENSIONAL FRAMEWORK (ACCEPT: 1, 2, 3, AND 4 OR ALL)Round 11 Page 9TOSS-UP19) ENERGY Short Answer What three-dimensional figure has the minimum surface area for a given volume, thus minimizing the leakage of neutrons in fission reactions?ANSWER: SPHEREBONUS19) ENERGY Short Answer A wind turbine obtains its power input by converting the force of the wind into a torque acting on the rotor blades. Name two of the three variables that affect the amount of energy transferred from the wind to the rotor.ANSWER: (ACCEPT TWO) DENSITY OF THE AIR, ROTOR (ACCEPT: BLADE) AREA, WIND SPEED_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer With which protein does actin associate in order to produce a muscular contraction?ANSWER: MYOSINBONUS20) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What adjective is used to describe fungi which appear to use the pigment melanin to convert gamma radiation into chemical energy for growth?ANSWER: RADIOTROPHICRound 11 Page 10TOSS-UP21) MATH Short Answer If each side of a rectangle is decreased by 10%, by what percentage is the area decreased?ANSWER: 19%BONUS21) MATH Short Answer The lengths of three sides of a triangle are represented by 2x   5, 5x + 3, and 4x + 9. Providing your answer as an improper fraction in simplest form, if the perimeter is 50 units, what is the length of the shortest side?ANSWER: 31/11 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP22) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT one of the events that occurs during translation?W) Binding to a promoter X) TerminationY) InitiationZ) ElongationANSWER: W) BINDING TO A PROMOTERBONUS22) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term for the durable process by which a cell directs the secretory vesicles to excrete their contents through the cell membrane?ANSWER: EXOCYTOSIS (ACCEPT: REVERSE PINO-CYTOSIS)Round 11 Page 11TOSS-UP23) ENERGY Multiple Choice In the United States, where is spent nuclear fuel currently stored?W) At a nuclear waste facility in Prairie Island, MinnesotaX) At a nuclear waste facility in Yucca Mountain, NevadaY) At a nuclear waste facility in Waterford, ConnecticutZ) In temporary storage at nuclear power plants around the countryANSWER: Z) IN TEMPORARY STORAGE AT NUCLEAR POWER PLANTS AROUND THE COUNTRYBONUS23) ENERGY Short Answer A 5 kilogram mass is held against a spring, compressing it by 1 meter; the spring constant is 500 newtons per meter. What is the maximum speed, in meters per second, the mass can achieve when the spring decompresses?ANSWER: 10TOSS-UP24) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following BEST describes a cathode ray?W) A device that emits light through a process of optical amplification based on the stimulated emission of photonsX) An electrode through which electric current flows out of a polarized electrical deviceY) A stream of electrons observed in vacuum tubesZ) An electrode through which electric current flows into a polarized electrical deviceANSWER: Y) A STREAM OF ELECTRONS OBSERVED IN VACUUM TUBESBONUS24) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A projectile is fired from a gun at an angle of 45o with respect to the horizontal. Given that g is 10 meters per second squared, what is the magnitude and direction of the acceleration, in meters per second squared, of the projectile when it reaches its maximum height?ANSWER: 10 DOWNWARDSTOSS-UP25) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a cartilaginous fish?W) Skate X) EelY) Ray Z) SharkANSWER: X) EELBONUS25) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following makes 3-dimensional protein studies difficult?W) Proteins never fold properly outside their native cellX) Chaperonins are required for some proteins to foldY) Proteins lose their 3D structure once you remove them from the cell Z) Contaminating chaperonins will degrade proteinsANSWER: X) CHAPERONINS ARE REQUIRED FOR SOME PROTEINS TO FOLDRound 11Page 13