ROUND 2TOSS-UP1) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a carbonate?          W) DolomiteX) AragoniteY) Malachite (read as: MAH-lah-kyt) Z) LabradoriteANSWER: Z) LABRADORITEBONUS1) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following moons has the highest surface albedo?W) PhobosX) EuropaY) IoZ) Enceladus (read as: ehn-SEHLL-ah-duhs)ANSWER: Z) ENCELADUS _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer If the voltage across a 3-ohm resister is 6 volts, what is the current, in amperes, flowing through the circuit?ANSWER: 2BONUS2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an intensive property?W) MassX) VolumeY) LengthZ) Melting pointANSWER: Z) MELTING POINTRound 2Page 1TOSS-UP3) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a type of fine-grained igneous rock?W) Rhyolite (read as: RY-oh-lyt)X) Peridotite (read as: peh-RI-doh-tyt) Y) KomatiteZ) BasaltANSWER: X) PERIDOTITEBONUS3) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What type of geomorphic feature forms on the outside of a river bend?ANSWER: CUT BANK (ACCEPT: RIVER CLIFF) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP4) ENERGY Multiple Choice During which of the following periods were coals generally lignite deposits still containing significant volatile material?W) Carboniferous X) PermianY) SecondaryZ) TertiaryANSWER: Z) TERTIARYBONUS4) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true about solar dish- engine systems?W) Direct-beam energy is concentrated at a focal point on a dish made of mirrorsX) The concentrated solar beam is converted to heat that is transferred to an engine Y) Mercury or copper are commonly used as heat transfer mediaZ) The engine uses heat to create mechanical power that drives a generatorANSWER: Y) MERCURY OR COPPER ARE COMMONLY USED AS HEAT TRANSFER MEDIARound 2 Page 2TOSS-UP5) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Which bivalve has complex eyes, including a lens and retina? ANSWER: SCALLOPBONUS5) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer According to biological classification, what is the order of rabbits?ANSWER: LAGOMORPHA _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following is perpendicular to the line y = -2x + 6?W) 2y = x + 4 X) x + 2y = 4 Y) y = 2x – 6Z) y = -1x – 6 2ANSWER: W)2y=x+4 BONUS6) MATH Short Answer In simplest radical form, what is the area, in square units, of a right triangle with a hypotenuse length of 12 and one leg with a length of 6?ANSWER: 18 3  Round 2 Page 3TOSS-UP7) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the genus of the bacteria that causes typhoid fever? ANSWER: SALMONELLABONUS7) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following organisms is NOT a thallophyte (read as: THAH-loh-fyt)?W) Entamoeba (read as: ehn-tah-MEE-bah) X) CladophoraY) Chara (read as: KAH-rah)Z) UlothrixANSWER: W) ENTAMOEBA _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP8) ENERGY Short Answer In a building, what is usually the leakiest site when it comes to energy, both in terms of losing heat in the winter and also gaining heat in the summer?ANSWER: WINDOWBONUS8) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true about honeybee flight?W) They flap their wings very quicklyX) Their wings beat over a very short arcY) When they want to generate more power, they increase the arc of their wing strokes Z) Their flight muscles are physiologically very similar to those of fruit fliesANSWER: Z) THEIR FLIGHT MUSCLES ARE PHYSIOLOGICALLY VERY SIMILAR TO THOSE OF FRUIT FLIESRound 2Page 4TOSS-UP9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following elements is NOT diatomic in its natural state?W) SulfurX) Nitrogen Y) Hydrogen Z) ChlorineANSWER: W) SULFURBONUS9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the maximum number of electrons that an n = 4 shell can accommodate?ANSWER: 32 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following statements is NOT true about most carp?W) They possess Weberian ossiclesX) They have teeth on their inferior pharyngeal bones Y) They are highly tolerant of salt waterZ) They have a wide geographical rangeANSWER: Y) THEY ARE HIGHLY TOLERANT OF SALT WATERBONUS10) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of a method of fertilization in which the ovum is fertilized within a fallopian tube of a fertile female donor for transplantation into an infertile recipient?ANSWER: IN VIVO FERTILIZATIONRound 2 Page 5TOSS-UP11) MATH Short Answer Thirty percent of the days of each month have been designated as vacation days. To the nearest day, how many days of vacation should be in April?ANSWER: 9BONUS11) MATH Short Answer The sum of 3 consecutive integers is 21. What is their product? ANSWER: 336_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP12) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer When measuring the volume of a liquid in a graduated cylinder, what is the name of the curve at the surface of the liquid?ANSWER: MENISCUSBONUS12) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer By number, identify all of the following three statements that are NOT true about tornado safety: 1) you should open windows if a tornado is approaching; 2) highway overpasses provide safe shelters from tornadoes; 3) rivers form a barrier to tornadoes.ANSWER: 1, 2, AND 3 OR ALLRound 2 Page 6TOSS-UP13) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following objects is likely to have the lowest albedo?W) Weathered granite X) Sea iceY) Fresh basaltZ) Rainforest canopyANSWER: Y) FRESH BASALTBONUS13) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following describes when flooding is most likely to occur as the result of a slow moving, relatively long term, moderate rain event?W) After the rain has endedX) After it has been raining for about an hour Y) After it has been raining for a few hours Z) At the beginning of the rainstormANSWER: W) AFTER THE RAIN HAS ENDED _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP14) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, identify all of the following four organs directly involved in excretory system processes: 1) lungs, 2) heart, 3) skin, 4) kidneys.ANSWER: LUNGS, SKIN, AND KIDNEYS (ACCEPT: 1, 3, AND 4)BONUS14) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the air mass that forms over North Africa during the summer, carrying dust from Africa long distances?ANSWER: SAHARAN AIR LAYER (ACCEPT: S.A.L.)Round 2 Page 7TOSS-UP15) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following characteristics is NOT true of the herbicide Paraquat?W) It is quick actingX) It is non-selective, killing a wide range of annual grasses and broad-leaved weeds Y) It is linked to the development of Parkinson’s diseaseZ) It remains biologically active in the soil for approximately 60 daysANSWER: Z) IT REMAINS BIOLOGICALLY ACTIVE IN THE SOIL FOR APPROXIMATELY 60 DAYSBONUS15) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, identify all of the following four choices that are examples of birth defects: 1) spina bifida, 2) hypospadias (read as: hy-poh-SPAY-dee- ahs), 3) Tay-Sachs, 4) phenylketonuria (read as: fee-nil-kee-tohn-UHR-ee-ah).ANSWER: SPINA BIFIDA, HYPOSPADIAS, TAY-SACHS, PHENYLKETONURIA (ACCEPT: 1, 2, 3, AND 4 OR ALL)_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, range the following four biomes from highest to lowest average temperature: 1) taiga, 2) tropical rainforest, 3) tundra, 4) temperate deciduous (read as: di-SI-juh-uhs) forest.ANSWER: TROPICAL RAIN FOREST, TEMPERATE DECIDUOUS FOREST, TAIGA, TUNDRA (ACCEPT: 2, 4, 1, 3)BONUS16) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, identify all of the following four animals that are NOT filter feeders: 1) mysid, 2) krill, 3) whale shark, 4) crab spider.ANSWER: CRAB SPIDER (ACCEPT: 4)Round 2 Page 8TOSS-UP17) MATH Short Answer Given the graph of a quadratic polynomial function, what is the minimum number of ordered pairs on the graph needed in order to determine the coefficients of the polynomial?ANSWER: 3BONUS17) MATH Short Answer Fred is twice as old as Marco and Marco is 4 years older than Ray. If Larz is 2 years older than Fred, and Ray is 6 years old, how old is Larz?ANSWER: 22 YEARS OLD _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP18) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following elements has chemical properties similar to oxygen?W) Nitrogen X) Fluorine Y) SulfurZ) NeonANSWER: Y) SULFUR18) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the IUPAC name for Sr(OH)2? ANSWER: STRONTIUM HYDROXIDEBONUSRound 2Page 9TOSS-UP19) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice The aurora borealis, or northern lights, would not be observed if Earth lacked which of the following?W) Oxygen in its atmosphere X) A moonY) A magnetic fieldZ) High altitude cloudsANSWER: Y) A MAGNETIC FIELDBONUS19) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer A convergent fault, such as the large one at the front of the Himalayan Mountains, forms in which type of stress environment?ANSWER: COMPRESSION _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the second most abundant mineral in the Earth’s continental crust, composed only of silicon and oxygen?ANSWER: QUARTZBONUS20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the scientific order of frogs? ANSWER: ANURARound 2 Page 10TOSS-UP21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the empirical formula of C6H12O6? ANSWER: CH2OBONUS21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, rank the speed of sound through the following three mediums from fastest to slowest at 25° Celsius: 1) aluminum, 2) air, 3) water.ANSWER: ALUMINUM, WATER, AIR (ACCEPT: 1, 3, 2) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP22) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Mars is observed to have a very thin atmosphere compared to Earth. Which of the following statements does NOT help explain this difference?W) Mars is further from the Sun than EarthX) Mars is smaller than EarthY) Mars has less geothermal activity than Earth Z) Mars is cooler than EarthANSWER: W) MARS IS FURTHER FROM THE SUN THAN EARTHBONUS22) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What do hatchured lines on a topographic map indicate?ANSWER: A DEPRESSIONRound 2 Page 11TOSS-UP23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Although none of the following are concrete proof of a chemical change, which of the following definitely could NOT be used as an indication that a chemical change has occurred?W) Color changeX) Change in sizeY) Production of heat Z) Formation of gasANSWER: X) CHANGE IN SIZEBONUS23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What force, in newtons, does an electric field of 1 volt per meter exert on a particle with a charge of 2 coulombs?ANSWER: 2 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP24) ENERGY Short Answer What kind of energy recovery mechanism slows a hybrid vehicle by converting its kinetic energy into electric energy and storing it in a battery for later use?ANSWER: REGENERATIVE BRAKEBONUS24) ENERGY Short Answer Which U.S. state has the largest demonstrated coal reserves? ANSWER: MONTANARound 2 Page 12TOSS-UP25) MATH Short Answer The volume of a cube is 27 cubic centimeters. What is the surface area, in square centimeters, of this cube?ANSWER: 54BONUS25) MATH Short Answer Express the following in standard polynomial form:5x4y7 × zy × 11x2z2y (read as: 5x to the fourth y to the seventh times zy times 11 x squared z squared y).ANSWER: 55x6y9z3Round 2 Page 13