ROUND 1 TOSS-UP1) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Providing your answer as a decimal to the nearest hundredth, what is the density in grams per cubic centimeter of a material with a mass of 2.02 grams and a volume of 0.500 cubic centimeters?ANSWER: 4.04BONUS1) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer By number, identify all of the following four characteristics that are TRUE of hail: 1) most hail is less than 5 inches in diameter; 2) it is formed of partially frozen raindrops; 3) it is formed from chunks of ice; 4) it falls from the clouds as rain.ANSWER: 1 AND 3 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP2) MATH Short Answer In triangle ABC, angle C is a right angle, side AC is equal to 15 units, and side BC is equal to 8 units. What is the length, in units, of side AB?ANSWER: 17BONUS2) MATH Short Answer By how much is the sum of the first 10 even positive integers greater than the sum of the first 10 positive integers?ANSWER: 55          Round 1 Page 1TOSS-UP3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer How many protons are in an atom of carbon-14? ANSWER: 6BONUS3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Given g as 10 meters per second squared, what is the weight, in newtons, of a crate with a mass of 10 kilograms being raised from the floor at a steady speed?ANSWER: 100 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP4) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following determines the size of the image formed by a telescope?W) The focal length of the main lens or mirror X) The thickness of the lensY) The size of the apertureZ) The size of the mirrorANSWER: W) THE FOCAL LENGTH OF THE MAIN LENS OR MIRRORBONUS4) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, identify all of the following four moon phases in which a neap tide can occur: 1) first quarter, 2) last quarter, 3) new moon, 4) full moon.ANSWER: FIRST QUARTER AND LAST QUARTER (ACCEPT: 1 AND 2)Round 1 Page 2TOSS-UP5) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer A female who is heterozygous for a dominant, X-linked trait crosses with a male who also displays this trait phenotypically. What percentage of their sons will display this trait?ANSWER: 50%BONUS5) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, identify all of the following four choices that are unsaturated hydrocarbons: 1) propane, 2) ethene, 3) acetylene, 4) benzene.ANSWER: ETHENE, ACETYLENE, BENZENE (ACCEPT: 2, 3, AND 4) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer How many valence electrons are in beryllium? ANSWER: 2BONUS6) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following compounds is LEAST soluble in water?W) AmmoniaX) Molecular nitrogen Y) Sodium chloride Z) MethanolANSWER: X) MOLECULAR NITROGENRound 1Page 3TOSS-UP7) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer In which geologic period did reptiles first appear in Earth’s history?ANSWER: CARBONIFEROUSBONUS7) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer The stratopause is the boundary between which two atmospheric layers?ANSWER: STRATOSPHERE AND MESOSPHERE _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer When an electron or proton is accelerated through a potential difference of 1 volt, how much energy does it gain in electron volts?ANSWER: 1BONUS8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Lanthanides are elements with which of the following orbitals partially filled?W) S X) P Y) D Z) FANSWER: Z) FRound 1Page 4TOSS-UP9) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of the Tampa Bay desalination plant?W) It can produce up to 25 million gallons of drinking water per dayX) It uses the process of reverse osmosis to produce drinking water from saltwaterY) Concentrated seawater is directed back to the power plant, where it is mixed with cooling water and returned to the BayZ) Increased salinity in Tampa Bay is a proven environmental hazard of this operationANSWER: Z) INCREASED SALINITY IN TAMPA BAY IS A PROVEN ENVIRONMENTAL HAZARD OF THIS OPERATIONBONUS9) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following processes involves the scattering of a photon off of an electron?W) Compton scattering X) Møller scatteringY) Pair productionZ) Bhabha scatteringANSWER: W) COMPTON SCATTERING _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) MATH Short Answer Given that a plane is at an angle between 1 and 89 degrees to the axis of a right circular cylinder, what is the name of the curve formed at their intersection?ANSWER: ELLIPSEBONUS10) MATH Short Answer To be labeled “sugar free,” a candy must contain less than 0.5 grams of sugar per 40 grams. If a serving of sugar free candy is 25 grams, what is the maximum amount of sugar allowed, to the nearest hundredth of a gram?ANSWER: 0.31Round 1 Page 5TOSS-UP11) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a depositional feature formed by a glacier?W) Arête (read as: ah-RATE) X) HornY) CirqueZ) Kame (read as: CAME)ANSWER: Z) KAMEBONUS11) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Iceland is very tectonically active; which of the following does NOT contribute to its interesting geologic and tectonic past and present?W) Location atop a divergent boundaryX) Location adjacent to a subduction zone Y) Location atop a hot spotZ) Abundant transform faultsANSWER: X) LOCATION ADJACENT TO A SUBDUCTION ZONE _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP12) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The kinetic energy of an object is proportional to which of the following?W) Its velocityX) The square of its velocity Y) Its momentumZ) Its angular momentumANSWER: X) THE SQUARE OF ITS VELOCITYBONUS12) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer One liter of oxygen and two liters of hydrogen are reacted in a closed container to form a gaseous product. If the temperature within the container is the same before and after the reaction, what is the ratio of final pressure to initial pressure in the container?ANSWER: 2 : 3 (ACCEPT: 2 TO 3, 2/3)Round 1 Page 6TOSS-UP13) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following events are associated with the highest tides?W) Spring tides X) Neap tides Y) Slack tides Z) Ebb tidesANSWER: W) SPRING TIDESBONUS13) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, rank the following sedimentary rocks in order of increasing grain size: 1) conglomerate, 2) sandstone, 3) shale.ANSWER: SHALE, SANDSTONE, CONGLOMERATE (ACCEPT: 3, 2, 1) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP14) ENERGY Short Answer What is the name of the device that relies on sunshine to cook food when firewood is scarce?ANSWER: SOLAR COOKER (ACCEPT: SOLAR OVEN)BONUS14) ENERGY Short Answer Which U.S. state will have the first wave-power farm? ANSWER: OREGONRound 1Page 7TOSS-UP15) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What kinds of leaves do not possess a petiole (read as: PEH-tee-ōel)?ANSWER: SESSILEBONUS15) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Match the terms serrate, entire, and lobed with the numbers of the following leaf descriptions: 1) they have little bent teeth like those of a saw; 2) they have divisions that do not arrive at the center of half of the blade; 3) they have a smooth margin.ANSWER: SERRATE = 1; ENTIRE = 3; AND LOBED = 2 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) MATH Short Answer Bob is building shelves 18 inches long. He uses a saw with a kerf, or cut width, of an eighth of an inch. Considering the kerf, how many shelves exactly 18 inches long can he make from a board that is 72 inches long?ANSWER: 3BONUS16) MATH Short Answer What is the perimeter, in inches, of an isosceles (read as: eye-SOHS- leez) trapezoid with parallel sides measuring 4 inches and 10 inches and a height of 4 inches?ANSWER: 24Round 1 Page 8TOSS-UP17) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes the position of a gene on a chromosome?W) Chiasma (read as: ky-AHZ-mah) X) AlleleY) HistoneZ) LocusANSWER: Z) LOCUSBONUS17) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What are the common names of the two generally accepted families of living owls?ANSWER: TRUE (ACCEPT: TYPICAL) OWLS AND BARN OWLS_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP18) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following tectonic settings is MOST conducive to geothermal power generation?W) Plate boundaries X) Passive margins Y) Continental shields Z) DenudationANSWER: W) PLATE BOUNDARIESBONUS18) ENERGY Short Answer You want to design a battery pack filled with many cell phone lithium (read as: LI-thee-uhm) ion batteries capable of storing 10 megawatt hours of energy to offset a gas turbine power plant. If the battery pack operates at a constant voltage of 4 volts, how much capacity, in ampere hours, would you need to store 10 megawatt hours of energy?ANSWER: 2,500,000Round 1 Page 9TOSS-UP19) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term for the reactant used up first in a reaction?ANSWER: LIMITING REAGENTBONUS19) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A spring lies flat on a frictionless table and oscillates with a mass attached to the end of it. Which of the following is NOT true regarding this system?W) Kinetic energy is greatest at the equilibrium positionX) Potential energy is greatest at two different displacementsY) Potential energy is least at the equilibrium positionZ) Increasing the mass of the attached object will increase the magnitude of the spring forceANSWER: Z) INCREASING THE MASS OF THE ATTACHED OBJECT WILL INCREASE THE MAGNITUDE OF THE SPRING FORCE_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following ocean animals’ eggs hatch at low tide?W) Sea turtleX) Sea starY) GrunionZ) Sea anemoneANSWER: W) SEA TURTLEBONUS20) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of a small, circular piece of bacterial DNA that contains only a few genes?ANSWER: PLASMIDRound 1 Page 10TOSS-UP21) MATH Short Answer Identify the real zeros of the function f x =   x2  4 (read as: f of x equals the square root of the quantity x squared minus 4).ANSWER: -2 AND 2BONUS21) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following points lies on the curve with equation y = 2x3  |5x | + 3 (read as: y equals 2 x cubed minus the absolute value of 5 x plus 3?W) (-2, 29) X) (-2, 1) Y) (-2, 9) Z) (-2, -23)ANSWER: Z) (-2, -23)TOSS-UP22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, identify all of the following four organisms that are mollusks : 1) squid, 2) sea star, 3) chiton (read as: KY-tun), 4) sea cucumber.ANSWER: SQUID AND CHITON (ACCEPT: 1 AND 3)BONUS22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, identify which of the following three coral reef types is directly attached to a shore, or borders it with an intervening shallow channel or lagoon: 1) atoll, 2) barrier, 3) fringing.ANSWER: FRINGING (ACCEPT: 3)Round 1 Page 11TOSS-UP23) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following minerals has the highest density?W) ChromiteX) Galena (read as: gah-LEE-nah) Y) PlatinumZ) Pyrite (read as: PY-ryt)ANSWER: Y) PLATINUMBONUS23) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer Kyanite (read as: KY-ah-nyt) is a metamorphic mineral that forms at temperatures greater than 600° Celsius. Assuming a geothermal gradient of 20° Celsius per kilometer, what is the minimum depth, in kilometers, at which kyanite (read as: KY-ah-nyt) will form?ANSWER: 30 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP24) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, identify all of the following three properties that would be the same at both sea level and the top of Mount Everest: 1) mass, 2) specific heat, 3) weight.ANSWER: MASS AND SPECIFIC HEAT (ACCEPT: 1 AND 2)BONUS24) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What type of photoreceptor is most abundant in the human eye?ANSWER: RODSRound 1 Page 12TOSS-UP25) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What type of tree has cones and needlelike leaves? ANSWER: CONIFER (ACCEPT: EVERGREEN)BONUS25) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What element is most commonly used as the final electron acceptor during oxidative phosphorylation (read as: fahs-fohr-i-LAY-shohn)?ANSWER: OXYGENRound 1 Page 13