ROUND 10 TOSS-UP1) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a present- day lithospheric plate?          W) Philippine X) ScotiaY) Arabian Z) ArcticANSWER: Z) ARCTICBONUS1) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice During the month of January, the Earth moves along its orbit at a rate that is which of the following?W) Faster than during JulyX) The same rate as any other month of the year Y) Slower than during March or SeptemberZ) The same rate as it is in JuneANSWER: W) FASTER THAN DURING JULY _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which of the following pairs are both properties colligative?W) Freezing point depression and lowering of vapor pressure X) Freezing point depression and densityY) Boiling point elevation and colorZ) Boiling point elevation and ionic strengthANSWER: W) FREEZING POINT DEPRESSION AND LOWERING OF VAPOR PRESSUREBONUS2) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the noble gas electron configuration for gold? ANSWER: [Xe] 6s15d104f14Round 10 Page 1TOSS-UP3) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is associated with Karst topography?W) Fossiliferous sandstones X) Hydrothermal activityY) Large granitic boulders Z) SinkholesANSWER: Z) SINKHOLESBONUS3) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the gradient, in feet per mile, of a stream slope whose highest elevation is 1600 feet to a point with an elevation of 400 feet over a distance of 5 miles?ANSWER: 240 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP4) ENERGY Multiple Choice Identify which of the following forces has the weakest relative strength.W) Electromagnetic X) GravityY) Weak nuclearZ) Strong nuclearANSWER: X) GRAVITYBONUS4) ENERGY Short Answer By name or number, rank the following four states from least to greatest in terms of average daily solar radiation intensity: 1) Indiana, 2) South Dakota, 3) Arizona, 4) California.ANSWER: INDIANA, SOUTH DAKOTA, CALIFORNIA, ARIZONA (ACCEPT: 1, 2, 4, 3)Round 10 Page 2TOSS-UP5) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following will NOT alter a somatic cell’s genome during an organism’s lifetime?W) Gene amplificationX) Selective gene lossY) TransposonsZ) Meiosis (read as: my-ŌE-sis)ANSWER: Z) MEIOSISBONUS5) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following reptiles is known as a living fossil?W) Komodo dragonX) Sea turtleY) AnacondaZ) Tuatara (read as: tuh-ah-TAHR-ah)ANSWER: Z) TUATARA _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) MATH Short Answer How many subsets does the set consisting of the numbers 1, 2, and 3 have?ANSWER: 8BONUS6) MATH Short Answer Sarah is 10 years older than Tom. Tom is 4 years younger than Jim. Sarah is twice as old as Jim. Give the ages, in years, of Sarah, Jim, and Tom, respectively.ANSWER: SARAH=12;JIM=6; TOM=2Round 10 Page 3TOSS-UP7) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term for fractures that result in smooth curved surfaces, such as broken glass?ANSWER: CONCHOIDALBONUS7) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer Give the name of the soft, porous, calcium carbonate spires found in places like Mono Lake in eastern California that formed long ago when calcium-bearing fresh water bubbled up into the alkaline lake rich in carbonates.ANSWER: TUFA _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP8) ENERGY Multiple Choice The mass of a brick is measured on Earth, then transported to the Moon and measured again. Compared to its mass on Earth, the brick’s mass on the Moon will be which of the following?W) SmallerX) The sameY) LargerZ) Impossible to determine without further informationANSWER: X) THE SAMEBONUS8) ENERGY Short Answer By name or number, rank the following four choices from least to greatest annual methane emissions: 1) wastewater treatment, 2) landfills, 3) ruminant digestion, 4) manure management.ANSWER: WASTEWATER TREATMENT, MANURE MANAGEMENT, LANDFILLS, RUMINANT DIGESTION (ACCEPT: 1, 4, 2, 3)Round 10 Page 4TOSS-UP9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Atoms of the most active nonmetals have which of the following characteristics?W) Small atomic radii and high ionization energies X) Small atomic radii and low ionization energies Y) Large atomic radii and high ionization energies Z) Large atomic radii and low ionization energiesANSWER: W) SMALL ATOMIC RADII AND HIGH IONIZATION ENERGIESBONUS9) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Suppose you tie a rock to the end of a 1 meter long string and spin it in a vertical circle. Given 10 meters per second squared as g, what is the minimum integer speed needed to “just” get around the top?ANSWER: 4 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer By mass, what element is the most abundant in the human body?ANSWER: OXYGENBONUS10) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following are NOT bryophytes (read as: BRY- oh-fyts):?W) Liverworts X) FernsY) Hornworts Z) MossesANSWER: X) FERNSRound 10Page 5TOSS-UP11) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following inequalities has a finite solution set over the integers?W)x2 +5x+6>0X) |x + 2| > 4 (read as: the absolute value of the quantity x plus 2 is greater than 4) Y) 9x – 7 < 3x + 14Z)x2 –4x+3<0ANSWER: Z)x2 –4x+3<011) MATH Short Answer Alice stands 30 feet away from a building and looks up to the top of it.The angle of elevation is 45 degrees. If she is 5 feet tall, how tall is the building in feet?ANSWER: 35 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP12) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Monotremes (read as: MOH-noh-treems) are often considered ancestral mammals. Which of the following characteristics are present for every species of mammal except monotremes (read as: MOH-noh-treems)?W) Mammary glands X) Live birthY) Fur or hairZ) Warm-bloodedANSWER: X) LIVE BIRTHBONUSBONUS12) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following temperatures is the warmest?W) 31o Celsius X) 74o Fahrenheit Y) 84o Fahrenheit Z) 303 KelvinANSWER: W) 31o CELSIUSRound 10Page 6TOSS-UP13) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following represents the rate at which atmospheric gases and particles are moved across a surface?W) Vertical dispersionX) TurbulenceY) FluxZ) Stratospheric transportANSWER: Y) FLUXBONUS13) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, what is the order, from thinnest to thickest, of the Earth's: 1) crust, 2) mantle, 3) outer core, and 4) inner core?ANSWER: CRUST, INNER CORE, OUTER CORE, MANTLE (ACCEPT: 1, 4, 3, 2) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP14) MATH Short Answer What is the largest subset of the real numbers that can be the domain of the function f(x) = 1/x?ANSWER: THE REAL NUMBERS EXCEPT FOR 0BONUS14) MATH Short Answer Find the area in square centimeters of an irregular dodecagon that looks like a plus sign formed from 12 equal segments with lengths of 7 centimeters each.ANSWER: 245Round 10 Page 7TOSS-UP15) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following do chloroplasts have in common with mitochondria (read as: my-toh-KOHN-dree-ah)?W) They do not contain ribosomes (read as: RY-boh-sōems) X) They have a single membraneY) They replicate themselves and their own DNAZ) They contain thylakoids (read as: THY-lah-kohids)ANSWER: Y) THEY REPLICATE THEMSELVES AND THEIR OWN DNABONUS15) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the phrase for the maximum number of individuals of a given species that an area’s resources can sustain indefinitely without significantly depleting or degrading those resources?ANSWER: CARRYING CAPACITY _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following animals does NOT belong to the scientific suborder Ruminata?W) CowX) LlamaY) MooseZ) WildebeestANSWER: X) LLAMABONUS16) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In a given reaction, three moles of Substance A react completely with two moles of Substance B to create Substances C and D. The reaction continues to completion and feels cold to the touch, but neither Substance A nor B was cold to the touch prior to the reaction. Which of the following is TRUE regarding the reaction?W) There was a total of 5 moles of products createdX) The overall reaction was exothermicY) Substance B is the limiting reagentZ) The activation energy of the reaction is less than the activation energy of the reverse reactionANSWER: Y) SUBSTANCE B IS THE LIMITING REAGENTRound 10 Page 8TOSS-UP17) MATH Short Answer In simplest radical form, what is the magnitude of the complex number 2 + 3i ?ANSWER: 13BONUS17) MATH Multiple Choice Which of the following features would indicate that a dataset is not from a normal distribution?W) The range is equal to 6 standard deviationsX) There are outliersY) The range is much larger than the interquartile range Z) The mean is much larger than the medianANSWER: Z) THE MEAN IS MUCH LARGER THAN THE MEDIAN _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP18) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the charge of the ammonium ion? ANSWER: +1BONUS18) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Providing your answer as a decimal to the nearest tenth and given that the speed of sound in air is 350 meters per second, what is the length, in meters, of a closed organ pipe that can produce a tone of 440 hertz?ANSWER: 0.2  Round 10 Page 9TOSS-UP19) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the general term for an enzyme that unwinds the DNA double-helix during DNA replication?ANSWER: HELICASEBONUS19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice A farmer has planted corn in a field for the last 5 years, and has been disappointed with his crop yield for the last 2 years. Which of the following crops should he plant next year to maximize the corn yield for the following year?W) Nothing, it will let the soil recover completely from being plantedX) Potatoes, because they have the deepest roots and will aerate the soil Y) Peas, because they will maximize the nitrogen in the soil for the corn Z) Wheat, because they use different nutrients than the cornANSWER: Y) PEAS, BECAUSE THEY WILL MAXIMIZE THE NITROGEN IN THE SOIL FOR THE CORN_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the process in which nitrogen from dead and decomposing animals is converted to inorganic forms such as ammonium salts?ANSWER: MINERALIZATIONBONUS20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Of the 5 nitrogenous bases commonly found in either DNA or RNA, name all of the pyrimidines found in RNA.ANSWER: CYTOSINE AND URACILRound 10 Page 10TOSS-UP21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer The generator of a utility company produces 100 amperes of current at 10,000 volts. The voltage is then stepped up by a transformer to 100,000 volts for transmission. What will be the current, in amperes, in the transmission lines?ANSWER: 10BONUS21) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the term for the process by which a gas under pressure escapes through an opening that is much smaller than the distance between gas molecules?ANSWER: EFFUSION ______________________________________________________TOSS-UP22) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following parts of a fish can be used to estimate its age?W) Scale X) FinY) GillZ) MouthANSWER: W) SCALE**[See http://www.fw.delaware.gov/Fisheries/Documents/agegrowth.pdf to learn how this is done.]BONUS22) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the principle difference between the two types of active transport?W) Primary active transport involves an electrochemical gradient, while secondary active transport involves chemical energyX) Primary active transport involves chemical energy, while secondary active transport involves an electrochemical gradientY) Primary active transport involves moving ions into a cell, while secondary active transport involves moving ions out of a cellZ) Primary active transport involves moving ions out of a cell, while secondary active transport involves moving ions into a cellANSWER: X) PRIMARY ACTIVE TRANSPORT INVOLVES CHEMICAL ENERGY, WHILE SECONDARY ACTIVE TRANSPORT INVOLVES AN ELECTROCHEMICAL GRADIENT Round 10 Page 11Round 10 Page 12TOSS-UP23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Atoms with one or more unpaired electrons are which of the following?W) Diamagnetic X) Paramagnetic Y) PolarZ) RadioactiveANSWER: X) PARAMAGNETICBONUS23) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the current, in amperes, produced by a lightning strike that lasts 0.5 seconds and transfers 100 coulombs?ANSWER: 200 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP24) ENERGY Multiple Choice In the mid-nineteenth century, the English physicist James Joule created a device in which falling weights rotated paddles immersed in a barrel of water. Which of the following results did he observe?W) The potential energy of the weights transferred entirely into kinetic energy to drive the paddlesX) The potential energy of the weights transferred entirely into elastic energy to drive the paddlesY) The water in the barrel warmed slightly Z) The water in the barrel cooled slightlyANSWER: Y) THE WATER IN THE BARREL WARMED SLIGHTLYBONUS24) ENERGY Short Answer What is the term for the accumulated partially decayed vegetation or histosol that forms in wetland bogs, moors, and pocosins?ANSWER: PEAT (ACCEPT: TURF)Round 10 Page 13TOSS-UP25) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following minerals might you use in insulation?W) TalcX) AlbiteY) Pyrope (read as: PY-rōep) Z) QuartzANSWER: X) ALBITEBONUS25) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice An ice cube dyed with red food coloring is placed into a cup of fresh water at room temperature. An identical cube is placed into salt water. Where will the color go as the ice cubes melt?W) Bottom of the cup in fresh water and top of the cup in salt water X) Top of the cup in fresh water and bottom of the cup in salt water Y) Mixed into the water in both cupsZ) Bottom of the cup in both cupsANSWER: W) BOTTOM OF THE CUP IN FRESH WATER AND TOP OF THE CUP IN SALT WATERRound 10 Page 14