ROUND 14 TOSS-UP1) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Naked mole rats are mammals, but they differ from every other species of mammal in one defining characteristic. What is this characteristic?W) They lack mammary glandsX) They lack fur or hairY) They are nearly poikilothermic (read as: pohi-KEE-loh-thehr-mik) Z) They do not give live birthANSWER: Y) THEY ARE NEARLY POIKILOTHERMICBONUS1) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer In what class of fish do sharks belong? ANSWER: CHONDRICHTHYES_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP2) MATH Short Answer A tic-tac-toe game is played by placing Xs or Os at consecutive lattice points of a coordinate system. If your opponent had marks at (-1, -2) and (1, -4), what are the coordinates of the point where you would place your mark in order to block your opponent?ANSWER: (0, -3)BONUS2) MATH Short Answer Solve the inequality 33x – 2 > 1 (read as: 3 to the power of the quantity 3x minus 2 is greater than 1).ANSWER: x > 2/3          Round 14 Page 1TOSS-UP3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the change in energy of an atom in the gaseous state when an electron is added to the neutral atom to form a negative ion?ANSWER: ELECTRON AFFINITYBONUS3) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer By number, identify all of the following three statements that are TRUE about Lewis acids and bases: 1) Lewis acids accept an electron pair; 2) Lewis bases donate an electron pair; 3) Lewis acids and bases do not require the presence of water.ANSWER: 1, 2, AND 3 (ACCEPT: ALL) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP4) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What are the common names of the two main groups of cetaceans (read as: si-TAY-shehns)?ANSWER: BALEEN WHALES AND TOOTHED WHALESBONUS4) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice What effect does the wobble position in a codon have on protein synthesis?W) The 1st and 2nd bases are interchangeable X) The 2nd base can change and have no effect Y) The 3rd base is an absolute determinantZ) The 3rd base is often irrelevantANSWER: Z) THE 3RD BASE IS OFTEN IRRELEVANTRound 14Page 2TOSS-UP5) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following functional groups does NOT contain an oxygen atom?W) Carboxyl X) AmineY) Hydroxyl Z) CarbonylANSWER: X) AMINE6) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following ions has a noble gas configuration?W) P2− X) N3−Y) Ca3+ Z) F2−ANSWER: X) N3−BONUS5) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following countries is most likely to experience droughts during an El Niño event?W) PeruX) IndiaY) KenyaZ) South AfricaANSWER: Z) SOUTH AFRICA _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer For a given pair of atoms, which of the following kinds of bonds are the shortest: single, double, or triple?ANSWER: TRIPLEBONUSRound 14Page 3TOSS-UP7) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer Give the name of the most frequently occurring iron-bearing oxide mineral in soil that has a characteristic yellowish brown color and often forms under cool temperatures, moist soil conditions, and in the presence of comparatively large amounts of organic matter.ANSWER: GEOTHITEBONUS7) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Stromatolites were once very common but are now quite rare. Which of the following is a plausible explanation?W) Light conditions are no longer favorable for the photosynthetic organisms that form stromatolitesX) Ocean acidification makes the formation of stromatolites difficultY) Few places are warm enough for the organisms that form stromatolitesZ) The organisms that produce stromatolites were not able to compete effectively enough with other organismsANSWER: Z) THE ORGANISMS THAT PRODUCE STROMATOLITES WERE NOT ABLE TO COMPETE EFFECTIVELY ENOUGH WITH OTHER ORGANISMS_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer As electrons are gained by an element in a redox reaction, what happens to the oxidation state of that element?ANSWER: IT DECREASES (ACCEPT: BECOMES MORE NEGATIVE)BONUS8) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the oxidation state of tin in (NH4)2SnCl6? ANSWER: +4Round 14Page 4TOSS-UP9) ENERGY Multiple Choice In which of the following years did the U.S. have the highest energy consumption per person?W) 1949 X) 1959 Y) 1979 Z) 1989ANSWER: Y) 1979BONUS9) ENERGY Short Answer What is the adjective for a material that generates an electric charge when mechanically deformed?ANSWER: PIEZOELECTRIC _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) MATH Multiple Choice If f(x) = 1/x, then f −1 (x) (read as: f inverse of x) equals which of the following?W) x – 1 X) xY) 1 x2Z ) 1xA N S W E R : Z ) 1x   BONUS10) MATH Short Answer If local sales tax is 9%, and tax is rounded to the nearest cent, what is the most a purchase can cost, before tax, to not exceed a total of $25 including tax?ANSWER: $22.94Round 14 Page 5TOSS-UP11) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer As sea ice melts, the Earth reflects less sunlight back into space, resulting in further warming and more loss of ice. What kind of feedback relationship is this?ANSWER: POSITIVEBONUS11) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following rocks likely formed from the lowest temperature melt?W) GraniteX) BasaltY) DioriteZ) Andesite (read as: AHN-di-zyt)ANSWER: W) GRANITE _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP12) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following reactions is NOT an example of oxidation-reduction?W) CuSO4(aq) + 2NaOH(aq) → (read as: yields) Cu(OH)2(s) +Na2SO4(aq) X) 3CuS(s) + 8HNO3(aq) → 3CuSO4(aq) + 8NO(g) + 4H2O(l)Y) Fe(s) + CuSO4(aq) → FeSO4(aq) + Cu(s)Z) Cu(s) + HNO3(aq) → Cu(NO3)2(aq) + NO2(g)ANSWER: W) CUSO4(AQ) + 2NAOH(AQ) → CU(OH)2(S) +NA2SO4(AQ) [NOTE: AQ = AQUEOUS; S = SOLID; L = LIQUID]BONUS12) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice John and Michael look from their 80 meter high balcony to a swimming pool with a 20 meter horizontal distance from the base of their building. If they were to jump off the balcony into the pool, how fast in meters per second would they have to jump horizontally to succeed in reaching the pool?W) 4 X) 5 Y) 9.8 Z) 12ANSWER: X) 5Round 14Page 6TOSS-UP13) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following types of geologic folds are pointed, not curved, around the axial plane?W) Recumbent X) ChevronY) IsoclinalZ) SymmetricalANSWER: X) CHEVRONBONUS13) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer On a topographic map, a river runs from east to west. If a north-south-trending contour line crosses the river and forms a V that points to the right, in which direction is the river likely flowing?ANSWER: WEST _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP14) ENERGY Short Answer If you live near a nuclear power plant, you may be issued tablets of what compound, which, in the event of a release of radioactive iodine, can prevent it from being collected in your thyroid?ANSWER: POTASSIUM IODIDEBONUS14) ENERGY Short Answer By number, rank the following four sources of radiation from least to greatest annual relative millirem doses: 1) diagnostic radiology, 2) natural radioactivity in the body, 3) radon in the average home, 4) living near a normally operating nuclear power station.ANSWER: 4, 2, 1, 3Round 14 Page 7TOSS-UP15) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the common name of the land bird with the largest wingspan of any North American bird?ANSWER: CALIFORNIA CONDORBONUS15) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the stage of the insect life cycle, lacking in hemimetabolous (read as: heh-mi-meh-TAH-boh-luhs) insects, during which many tissues degenerate and are reorganized?ANSWER: PUPA _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) MATH Short Answer What is the degree of the polynomial 6x2y + 3yx4 – 2x? ANSWER: 5BONUS16) MATH Short Answer Consider the system of two equations: 3x   4y = 23 and 2x   5y = 20. What is the value of x + y?ANSWER: 3Round 14 Page 8TOSS-UP17) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What small, regularly-shaped cell fragments circulate in the blood of mammals and lead to the formation of blood clots?ANSWER: PLATELETSBONUS17) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following processes is MOST under the influence of the hormone aldosterone?W) Sodium and potassium electrolyte balance X) SpermatogenesisY) Heart rateZ) Gastric motilityANSWER: W) SODIUM AND POTASSIUM ELECTROLYTE BALANCE _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP18) ENERGY Multiple Choice About what fraction of the petroleum consumed in the United States is used for transportation?W) 1/4 X) 1/2 Y) 3/4 Z) 7/8ANSWER: Y) 3/4BONUS18) ENERGY Short Answer By name or number, rank the following five renewable energy sources in order from least to greatest according to their contribution to U.S. energy production in 2009: 1) geothermal, 2) biofuels, 3) wind, 4) hydropower, 5) solar.ANSWER: SOLAR, GEOTHERMAL, WIND, BIOFUELS, HYDROPOWER (ACCEPT: 5, 1, 3, 2, 4)Round 14 Page 9TOSS-UP19) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The Aufbau principle is used to determine which of the following?W) Spin of an electronX) Electron configuration of an atomY) Position and momentum of an electron Z) Relative mass of an atomANSWER: X) ELECTRON CONFIGURATION OF AN ATOMBONUS19) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the chemical name for the compound HC8H4O4−1?ANSWER: HYDROGEN PHTHALATE _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of regular echinoids (read as: i-KY-nohids)?W) PentamerismX) Tube feetY) Globoid shapeZ) Branched tentaclesANSWER: Z) BRANCHED TENTACLESBONUS20) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Identify the term used to describe the process of humans purposely ingesting insects.ANSWER: ENTOMOPHAGYRound 14 Page 10TOSS-UP21) MATH Short Answer If a 20 meter tree casts a 20 3 meter shadow, what is the angle of elevation, in degrees, of the Sun?ANSWER: 30°BONUS21) MATH Short Answer Solve the inequality: 15x2 – 2 > x.ANSWER: x < -1/3 OR x > 2/5(NOTE: STUDENTS MUST GIVE BOTH ANSWERS) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What rare earth element with atomic number 73 is used in GPS systems, laptop computers, cellular phones, hearing aids, and some video game systems?ANSWER: TANTALUMBONUS22) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer For many types of bees, fertilized eggs become females while unfertilized eggs become males, and females have two sets of chromosomes while males only have one set. For sister bees that have the same parents, what is the average percentage of DNA that they share?ANSWER: 75%  Round 14 Page 11TOSS-UP23) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the common point around which both the Earth and the Moon revolve?ANSWER: BARYCENTERBONUS23) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer Earth is nearest the Sun around January 3rd. What is the term for this point in Earth’s orbit?ANSWER: PERIHELION _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP24) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice In eukaryotic cells, which of the following portions of an mRNA molecule is translated?W) Poly (A) tailX) ExonY) IntronZ) Guanosine (read as: GWAH-noh-seen) triphosphate capANSWER: X) EXONBONUS24) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Which group of amphibians is characterized by their surficial resemblance to earthworms or snakes?ANSWER: CAECILIANS (ACCEPT: AMPHISBAENIDS)Round 14 Page 12TOSS-UP25) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following molecular formulas corresponds to an organic acid?W) CH3ClX) CH3OHY) CH3COOH Z) CH3COOCH3ANSWER: Y) CH3COOHBONUS25) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A segment of unlabeled DNA undergoes replication in a solution containing all necessary materials and in which the nitrogenous bases in the solution are radioactively labeled. Two complete, double-stranded DNA segments form. Following replication, which of the following is likely to be observed?W) One strand on each of the two DNA segments is radioactively labeled, while the other strand on each of the two segments is unlabeledX) Both strands of one DNA segment are radioactively labeled, while both strands of the other segment are unlabeledY) Both strands on each segment of DNA contain a mixture of radioactively labeled and unlabeled base pairsZ) Both segments of DNA have all their nitrogenous bases in both strands labeledANSWER: W) ONE STRAND ON EACH OF THE TWO DNA SEGMENTS IS RADIOACTIVELY LABELED, WHILE THE OTHER STRAND ON EACH OF THE TWO SEGMENTS IS UNLABELEDRound 14 Page 13