ROUND 8 TOSS-UP1) MATH Short Answer What is the largest number of sides possible for a regular polygon that tessellates the plane?ANSWER: 6BONUS1) MATH Short Answer The hypotenuse of a right triangle is 9 feet, and one leg is 6 feet. What is the area, in square feet, of the triangle in simplest radical form?ANSWER: 9 5 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP2) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Besides xylem and phloem (read as: FLŌE-ehm), what is the third tissue layer that comprises the stele in eudicot roots?ANSWER: PERICYCLEBONUS2) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Give the common names of two of the principal species of Pacific salmon.ANSWER: (ACCEPT TWO) SOCKEYE, CHUM, COASTAL CUTTHROAT TROUT, CHINOOK, COHO, STEELHEAD, OR PINK            Round 8 Page 1TOSS-UP3) ENERGY Short Answer What is the term for the minimum amount of fissile material required for a chain reaction to be self-sustaining?ANSWER: CRITICAL MASSBONUS3) ENERGY Short Answer What is the name of a device which consists of dissimilar metals joined together at one end that is used as a sensor for measuring temperature?ANSWER: THERMOCOUPLE _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP4) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The mechanical advantage of a block and tackle depends on which of the following?W) The size of the ropeX) The length of the ropeY) The diameter of the wheelsZ) The number of sections of ropeANSWER: Z) THE NUMBER OF SECTIONS OF ROPEBONUS4) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following situations produces the MOST power?W) 160 newton force acting over 20 meters in 32 seconds X) 160 newton force acting over 2 meters in 3.2 seconds Y) 16 newton force acting over 20 meters in 3.2 seconds Z) 16 newton force acting over 200 meters in 3.2 secondsANSWER: Z) 16 NEWTON FORCE ACTING OVER 200 METERS IN 3.2 SECONDSRound 8Page 2TOSS-UP5) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Give the class of mollusks in which squid would be classified. ANSWER: CEPHALOPODABONUS5) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Unlike other mollusks , cephalopods (read as: SEH-fah-loh- pohds) have which of the following characteristics?W) GillsX) RadulaY) Open circulatory system Z) Closed circulatory systemANSWER: Z) CLOSED CIRCULATORY SYSTEM _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP6) MATH Multiple Choice Assuming that all of the following two dimensional shapes have the same area, which has the least perimeter?W) Triangle X) CircleY) Trapezoid Z) SquareANSWER: X) CIRCLEBONUS6) MATH Short Answer At a special showing of “The Magic Flute,” all 300 tickets were sold for a total of $5,360. If an adult ticket was $20 and a youth ticket was $12, how many adult tickets were sold?ANSWER: 220Round 8 Page 3TOSS-UP7) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice For a certain genetic disorder in humans, the mother always passes the disease to all of her children, but a father never passes it to any of his children. Which of the following explanations best explains this phenomenon?W) The gene for the disease is located on the X-chromosomeX) The gene is dominant and is located on an autosomal chromosomeY) The gene is located on ribosomal (read as: RY-boh-sōem-ahl) DNAZ) The gene is located on mitochondrial (read as: my-toh-KOHN-dree-ahl) DNAANSWER: Z) THE GENE IS LOCATED ON MITOCHONDRIAL DNABONUS7) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most stable isotope of rutherfordium (read as: ruh-the(r)-FOHR-dee-uhm)?ANSWER: RUTHERFORDIUM-267 _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP8) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What kind of rock fragments are produced when magma is torn apart by volcanic eruptions?ANSWER: PYROCLASTSBONUS8) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What was the name of the space probe, launched in 2001, that orbited Mars to measure elements in its crust and search for signs of water?ANSWER: MARS ODYSSEYRound 8 Page 4TOSS-UP9) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Sediment with a diameter between 2 millimeters and 4 millimeters would be classified as which of the following?W) SiltX) Coarse sand Y) Medium sand Z) CobbleANSWER: Y) MEDIUM SANDBONUS9) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer When a free neutron undergoes beta decay, what three particles does it form?ANSWER: ELECTRON, PROTON, AND ELECTRON ANTINEUTRINO (DO NOT ACCEPT: ELECTRON NEUTRINO)_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP10) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the most likely effect on the remaining bacteria after killing 90% of bacteria with antibacterial soap?W) They will reproduce and form a colony of bacteria that are more resistant X) They will die because there are not enough bacteria left to reproduceY) They will relocateZ) They can no longer cause infections because their numbers are too lowANSWER: W) THEY WILL REPRODUCE AND FORM A COLONY OF BACTERIA THAT ARE MORE RESISTANTBONUS10) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Give the scientific names of the three small bones found in the human ear.ANSWER: MALLEUS, INCUS, AND STAPESTOSS-UP11) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following characteristics is NOT true of cannonball jellyfish?W) They can make up more than 16% of biomass in shallow inshore areas off the southeastern coast of the United StatesX) They commonly sting humansY) One of their main predators is the leatherback sea turtleZ) They can reproduce both sexually and asexuallyANSWER: X) THEY COMMONLY STING HUMANSBONUS11) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the genus of the oldest known vertebrate to show viviparity (read as: vy-vi-PAH-rit-ee)?ANSWER: MATERPISCIS _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP12) MATH Short Answer Evaluate: 10! (read as: 10 factorial over the quantity 8 factorial times 3 factorial). ANSWER: 158!3!BONUS12) MATH Short Answer Harry bought a shirt that was marked 50% off the sale price, which was 40% off the original price. Providing your answer as a decimal to the nearest tenth, after paying a tax of 8%, what percent of the original sticker price did he pay?ANSWER: 32.4%Round 8 Page 6TOSS-UP13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice In a transverse wave, the medium vibrates in which of the following ways?W) In a direction opposite the wave direction X) At right angles to the wave directionY) In the same direction as the waveZ) At a 45 degree angle to the wave directionANSWER: X) AT RIGHT ANGLES TO THE WAVE DIRECTIONBONUS13) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name three ferromagnetic elements.ANSWER: (ACCEPT THREE) IRON, NICKEL, COBALT, DYSPROSIUM, PLUTONIUM, AND GADOLINIUM_______________________________________________________TOSS-UP14) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name of the branch of science specifically concerned with the study of fungi?ANSWER: MYCOLOGYBONUS14) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer The beta-galactosidase (read as: gah-lahk-TŌE-si-days) enzyme aids in lactose digestion by separating lactose into what two monosaccharide (read as: moh-noh-SAH-kah-ryd) molecules?ANSWER: GALACTOSE AND GLUCOSERound 8 Page 7TOSS-UP15) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following nutrients is most often limiting in freshwater aquatic ecosystems?W) CarbonX) NitrogenY) Phosphorus Z) SulfurANSWER: Y) PHOSPHORUSBONUS15) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the common name of the only penguin that lives north of the equator in the wild?ANSWER: GALAPAGOS PENGUIN _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following does the slope on a distance- time graph represent?W) VelocityX) Acceleration Y) Displacement Z) MotionANSWER: W) VELOCITYBONUS16) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer In a second-class lever, where is the fulcrum located: 1) between the input and the output forces; 2) closer to the output force than the input force; or 3) closer to the input force than the output force?ANSWER: CLOSER TO THE OUTPUT FORCE THAN THE INPUT FORCE (ACCEPT: 2)Round 8 Page 8TOSS-UP17) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following types of sediments came from shells and skeletons of animals?W) Terrigenous (read as: teh-RI-jeh-nuhs) X) SulfurousY) HydrogenousZ) Calcareous (read as: kahl-KAHR-ee-uhs)ANSWER: Z) CALCAREOUSBONUS17) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer What are the names of the two irregularly shaped moons of Mars?ANSWER: PHOBOS AND DEIMOS _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP18) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following elements has the highest melting point at standard atmospheric pressure?W) Tungsten X) Thallium Y) GoldZ) CopperANSWER: W) TUNGSTENBONUS18) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the kinetic energy, in joules, of a 70 kilogram tiger running at a speed of 8 meters per second?ANSWER: 2240Round 8 Page 9TOSS-UP19) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following countries generates the greatest share of its electricity from wind power?W) DenmarkX) SpainY) GermanyZ) United StatesANSWER: W) DENMARKBONUS19) ENERGY Short Answer By name or number, rank from greatest to least the total amount of each of the following four products produced from crude oil in the U.S. in 2009: 1) jet fuel, 2) gasoline, 3) diesel, 4) heating oil.ANSWER: GASOLINE, DIESEL, JET FUEL, HEATING OIL (ACCEPT: 2, 3, 1, 4) _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP20) MATH Multiple Choice If a polyhedron had seven faces, exactly six of which were triangles, which of the following could it be?W) Hexagonal prism X) Hexagonal pyramid Y) Pentagonal prism Z) Pentagonal pyramidANSWER: X) HEXAGONAL PYRAMIDBONUS 20) MATH Short Answer Solve for real numbers x if   9x- x2 > 0 (read as: the square root of the quantity 9x minus x squared is greater than 0).ANSWER: 0<x<9Round 8 Page 10TOSS-UP21) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is an example of a well-known group of extinct marine arthropods that existed in abundance during the lower Paleozoic?W) Brachiopods X) Ammonites Y) TrilobitesZ) NautilusesANSWER: Y) TRILOBITESBONUS21) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Short Answer If due north is 0°, what degree is the intercardinal direction southwest?ANSWER: 225° _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes how the frequency of an ocean wave changes as its wavelength changes?W) It increases as the wavelength increases X) It increases as the wavelength decreases Y) It decreases as the wavelength decreases Z) It decreases as the wavelength increasesANSWER: X) IT INCREASES AS THE WAVELENGTH DECREASESBONUS22) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer If a sound wave traveling through water has a speed of 1,450 meters per second and a frequency of 2900 hertz, providing your answer as a decimal to the nearest tenth, what is its wavelength in meters?ANSWER: 0.5Round 8 Page 11TOSS-UP23) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following characteristics is generally NOT used for classification of ocean waves?W) Disturbing force X) WavelengthY) Wave heightZ) Restoring forceANSWER: Y) WAVE HEIGHTBONUS23) EARTH AND SPACE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a characteristic of a turbidite?W) Graded beddingX) Lived during the CambrianY) Found in alkaline bodies of water Z) Often found in cavesANSWER: W) GRADED BEDDING _______________________________________________________TOSS-UP24) ENERGY Multiple Choice Which of the following states produces the most coal?W) WyomingX) West Virginia Y) GeorgiaZ) MontanaANSWER: W) WYOMINGBONUS24) ENERGY Short Answer Many factors affect the overall price of gasoline. By name or number, arrange the following four factors based on the extent to which their costs influence the price of gasoline in descending order: 1) taxes, 2) distribution, 3) crude oil, 4) refining.ANSWER: CRUDE OIL, TAXES, REFINING, DISTRIBUTION (ACCEPT: 3, 1, 4, 2)Round 8 Page 12TOSS-UP25) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer By name or number, identify all of the following four substances that emulsify fat during digestion: 1) gastrin, 2) amylase, 3) motilin, 4) bile.ANSWER: BILE (ACCEPT: 4)BONUS25) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer When genetic drift results from the colonization of a new habitat by only a few individuals, what is the name of the resulting loss of genetic variation?ANSWER: FOUNDER EFFECTRound 8 Page 13