ROUND 9 TOSS-UP1) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following is the magnitude of the focal length of a spherically curved convex mirror in air, where R stands for the radius of curvature:W) R divided by 1.22 X) R divided by 2Y) R divided by 1.5 Z) R times 4ANSWER: X) R DIVIDED BY 2BONUS1) PHYSICS Short Answer An emergency floodlight draws 1 ampere from its battery pack. How many coulombs will flow through the light in 4 hours?ANSWER: 14,400TOSS-UP2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice About how many calories per gram will it take to sublimate water at standard pressure:W) 180 X) 360 Y) 540 Z) 720ANSWER: Z) 720(Solution: sublimation is solidvapor; 80 cal + 100 cal + 540 cal = 720 cal)BONUS2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice A Buchner (read as: BYOU-kh-ner) funnel is a piece of laboratory glassware often used in chemistry labs for which of the following procedures:W) combustion X) filtrationY) centrifugation Z) distillationANSWER: X) FILTRATION High School Round 9Page 1
TOSS-UP3) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following tissues is most directly responsible for the growth in height of a tree:W) apical meristem X) shoot terminusY) terminal cambial Z) cambium terminusANSWER: W) APICAL MERISTEMBONUS3) BIOLOGY Short Answer What specific cells and how many of them border each stomal pore? ANSWER: GUARD CELLS; 2TOSS-UPx4) MATH Multiple Choice If e 5 = 30, which of the following is the value of x, assuming that thenatural log of 2 = 0.7, and the natural log of 15 = 2.7:W) 15 X) 16 Y) 17 Z) 18ANSWER: Y) 17(Solution: x/5 = ln 15 + ln 2 = 3.4; x/5 = 3.4; x = 17)BONUS4) MATH Short Answer If the area of a regular pentagon is 280 square centimeters, what is the length, in centimeters, of each side if the apothem is 16 centimeters?ANSWER: 7(Solution: A = 1⁄2 ap; 280 = 1⁄2 (16)(p); p = 35/5 = 7 cm)  High School Round 9 Page 2
TOSS-UP5) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Tree growth is often very stunted and gnarly at the tree line of high mountains in North America. Known as Krummholz formations, this is primarily caused by:W) windsX) subsidenceY) lowered atmospheric pressure Z) low sunlight levelsANSWER: W) WINDSBONUS5) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is generally NOT true of the alpine versus arctic tundra biomes:W) alpine tundra does not contain permafrost whereas arctic tundra does contain permafrost X) alpine tundra is warmer and has a longer growing season than arctic tundraY) alpine tundra has a lower species diversity than arctic tundraZ) alpine tundra has less severe winters than arctic tundraANSWER: Y) ALPINE TUNDRA HAS A LOWER SPECIES DIVERSITY THAN ARCTIC TUNDRATOSS-UP6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Name 2 of the following 4 choices that are the 2 main logical reasoning methods used in science: inductive; synthetic; observational; deductiveANSWER: INDUCTIVE; DEDUCTIVEBONUS6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer To the nearest whole number, convert 50oF into kelvin: ANSWER: 283(Solution: 5/9(50o – 32o) = 10o C + 273 = 283 K) High School Round 9 Page 3
TOSS-UP7) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true:W) the star Sirius at its brightest has an apparent magnitude of about negative 1.5X) metal-rich stars sometimes have planetsY) typical binoculars allow observation of stars with apparent magnitudes of about 9.0 Z) the Sun has an apparent magnitude of about negative 12ANSWER: Z) THE SUN HAS AN APPARENT MAGNITUDE OF ABOUT NEGATIVE 12 (Solution: the Sun’s apparent magnitude is –26.73)BONUS7) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice Astronomers will often refer to certain stars as low metal content stars. In this sense astronomers consider metals as any element:W) heavier than helium X) heavier than carbon Y) heavier than copper Z) heavier than ironANSWER: W) HEAVIER THAN HELIUMTOSS-UP8) PHYSICS Multiple Choice Which of the following MOST directly determines the permittivity of a material:W) ability of the material to magnetize X) electrical susceptibilityY) electrical insulation capacityZ) electrical conductivityANSWER: X) ELECTRICAL SUSCEPTIBILITYBONUS8) PHYSICS Short Answer What are the SI units for permittivity? ANSWER: FARADS PER METER High School Round 9Page 4
TOSS-UP9) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is one of the main reasons why oxygenates are used as gasoline additives:W) allow for more complete combustionX) decrease sulfur buildup in engine pistons Y) prevent water condensation in stored fuels Z) corrosion inhibitionANSWER: W) ALLOW FOR MORE COMPLETE COMBUSTIONBONUS9) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Consider the following equilibrium reaction,PCl5(gas) ↔ PCl3(gas) + Cl2(gas). If a 2 mole sample of PCl5 dissociates to give 0.2 moles of Cl2 at equilibrium, find the molar amounts, to the 1st decimal place, of PCl5 at equilibrium:ANSWER: 1.8 (Solution: 2 – 0.2 = 1.8)TOSS-UP10) BIOLOGY Short Answer During what phase of meiosis-one do homologous chromosomes exchange genetic information?ANSWER: PROPHASE-ONE (ACCEPT: PROPHASE)BONUS10) BIOLOGY Short Answer Order the following 3 choices from the EARLIEST stage to the LATEST stage of ovarian follicle development, and identify which of the structures is typically the LARGEST: secondary follicle; corpus luteum; corpus albicansANSWER: SECONDARY FOLLICLE; CORPUS LUTEUM; CORPUS ALBICANS; LARGEST = CORPUS LUTEUM High School Round 9 Page 5
TOSS-UP11) MATH Short Answer A circle has a diameter of 32 meters. Find the degree measure of the central angle of a sector of the circle if its arc length measures 8π meters:ANSWER: 90(Solution: arc/circumference = no/360o; n = 90o or (8π/2π16)(360o) = 90o)BONUS11) MATH Short Answer Find the sum of the first 10 terms of the arithmetic sequence whose first three terms are 7, 11, and 15:ANSWER: 250TOSS-UP12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the most common type of ocean tide throughout the world and is the type found along the U.S. Pacific coast: W) diurnalX) semidiurnal Y) mixedZ) zonalANSWER: Y) MIXEDBONUS12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice In which of the following regions of the world’s oceans are you most likely to find the greatest uniformity in density changes with increasing depth:W) equatorX) tropicsY) high latitudes Z) desert latitudesANSWER: Y) HIGH LATITUDES(Solution: at high polar latitudes, change is nearly constant)High School Round 9Page 6
TOSS-UP13) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a jaw-less fish:W) lungfish X) catfish Y) lamprey Z) sturgeonANSWER: Y) LAMPREYBONUS13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer In the northern hemisphere, name all of the following 4 northern degree latitudes that will experience a 12-hour length of day during the vernal equinox: 0o; 10o; 15o; 20oANSWER: ALLTOSS-UP14) ASTRONOMY Short Answer As a comet approaches the Sun, most of its icy substances are released during what phase change process?ANSWER: SUBLIMATIONBONUS14) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice During which of the following orbital arrangements can a transit occur for the planet Venus:W) oppositionX) greatest eastern elongation Y) superior conjunctionZ) inferior conjunctionANSWER: Z) INFERIOR CONJUNCTION High School Round 9Page 7
TOSS-UP15) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the general term for the process of making different types of semiconductors by adding slight amounts of impurities into the silicon matrix?ANSWER: DOPINGBONUS15) PHYSICS Short Answer What specific type of semiconductor is produced by doping silicon with arsenic?ANSWER: N-TYPETOSS-UP16) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice The reaction CuCl2 + Na2SCuS + 2NaCl2, is an example of what class of chemical reaction:W) synthesisX) single replacement Y) double replacement Z) decompositionANSWER: Y) DOUBLE REPLACEMENTBONUS16) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Name all of the following 4 species that contain an odd number of electrons: O21–; O22–; SO2; COANSWER: O21– High School Round 9 Page 8
TOSS-UP17) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following is the most common term for an area of primitive cells in plants where active cell division occurs:W) meristemX) ground tissue Y) primary cells Z) germinal tissueANSWER: W) MERISTEMBONUS17) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the layer typically found between 2 plant cell walls of adjoining plant cells which is composed of pectin?ANSWER: MIDDLE LAMELLATOSS-UP18) MATH Short Answer What is the name for the test that can be used to visually determine whether or not a relation defined by a graph represents a function?ANSWER: VERTICAL LINE TEST (ACCEPT: VERTICAL LINE)BONUS18) MATH Short Answer Find the x and y intercepts of the line passing through the point (4, 8) that is perpendicular to the line 3x – 6y – 12 = 0:ANSWER: X-INTERCEPT = (8, 0) (ACCEPT: 8); Y-INTERCEPT = (0, 16) (ACCEPT: 16) High School Round 9 Page 9
TOSS-UP19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a medium or coarse-grained rock that consists primarily of plagioclase feldspar and pyroxene and is essentially the plutonic equivalent of basalt:W) diorite X) rhyolite Y) andesite Z) gabbroANSWER: Z) GABBROBONUS19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Scoria is most typically described as having which of the following textures:W) phaneritic X) fragmental Y) porphyritic Z) vesicularANSWER: Z) VESICULARTOSS-UP20) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Blepharitis (read as: bleff-ah-rye-tis) in humans is an inflammation of the:W) urinary bladder 
X) eyelidY) fingernailZ) tongueANSWER: X) EYELIDBONUS20) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a principal component of a siderite meteorite:W) neptunium X) carbonY) ironZ) erbiumANSWER: Y) IRONHigh School Round 9Page 10
TOSS-UP21) ASTRONOMY Short Answer Which 2 of the following 4 factors most directly determine the apparent visual magnitude of a star: distance from Earth; intrinsic brightness; color; ageANSWER: DISTANCE FROM EARTH; INTRINSIC BRIGHTNESSBONUS21) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What 2 characteristics of Uranus are most commonly noted as the reasons why Uranus was not discovered until the late 1700’s?ANSWER: APPARENT MAGNITUDE; ORBITAL PERIOD ( ACCEPT: BRIGHTNESS or MAGNITUDE)TOSS-UP22) PHYSICS Short Answer In the electrolysis of water, if the production of each molecule of oxygen requires 4 units of electricity, each hydrogen molecule will require how many units of electricity?ANSWER: 2BONUS22) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the maximum number of 100-watt light bulbs that can run on a 110-volt residential circuit protected by a 15-amp fuse without blowing the fuse?ANSWER: 16(Solution: 100W/110 = 0.9 amps; 15 amp fuse/0.9 amp = 16.7 or 16 bulbs) High School Round 9 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What are the 2 alkenes (read as: al-KEENS) with the shortest carbon chains and lowest molecular weights?ANSWER: ETHYLENE; PROPYLENE (ACCEPT: ETHENE; PROPENE)BONUS23) CHEMISTRY Short Answer Arrange the following 4 metals in order of increasing reactivity in dilute HCl: zinc; aluminum; gold; calciumANSWER: GOLD; ZINC; ALUMINUM; CALCIUMTOSS-UP24) BIOLOGY Short Answer Which one of basic plant cell types has a primary and secondary cell wall that is dead when mature?ANSWER: SCLERENCHYMABONUS24) BIOLOGY Short Answer Name all of the following 4 plants that produce seeds: cycads; ferns; mosses; conifersANSWER: CYCADS; CONIFERS High School Round 9 Page 12
TOSS-UP25) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the general name for a substance that facilitates a chemical reaction by providing an alternative reaction pathway with a lower activation energy while remaining unaltered?ANSWER: CATALYSTBONUS25) CHEMISTRY Short Answer You need to prepare 500 milliliters of a 0.100 molar NaOH solution from a 0.250 molar solution. What volume, in milliliters, of the 0.250 molar solution must be diluted to 500 milliliters?ANSWER: 200(Solution: M1V1 = M2V2; (0.250M)(x) = (0.100M)(500ml), x = 200 ml)High School Round 9 Page 13