ROUND 3 TOSS-UP1) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the MOST common term for the type of energy that is most directly related to the energy of atoms, molecules and other small particles that are in random motion within a system?ANSWER: THERMALBONUS1) PHYSICS Short Answer In electrochemical cells, what is the most common term for the electrode that acts as the negative electrode?ANSWER: CATHODETOSS-UP2) CHEMISTRY Short Answer If the electronegativity difference in the bonding atoms is large, what general type of bond is formed?ANSWER: IONICBONUS2) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following molecules has a double covalent bond:W) hydrogen X) oxygen Y) nitrogen Z) methaneANSWER: X) OXYGEN High School Round 3Page 1
TOSS-UP3) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following BEST describes the function of the golgi (read as: GOAL-gee) complex:W) metabolism of carbohydratesX) production of peroxidesY) modification and packaging of proteins for exocytosis Z) storage of lipidsANSWER: Y) MODIFICATION AND PACKAGING OF PROTEINS FOR EXOCYTOSISBONUS3) BIOLOGY Short Answer Most corticosteroids are synthesized in what specific part of the human body?ANSWER: ADRENAL CORTEX (ACCEPT: ADRENAL GLANDS)TOSS-UP4) MATH Short Answer Simplify the following, giving your answer in proper scientific notation: (6.0 × 1012)(2.0 × 1010)2ANSWER: 2.4 × 1033BONUS4) MATH Short Answer Factor the following expression completely: 81x2 + 180xy + 100y2 ANSWER: (9x + 10y)2 High School Round 3 Page 2
TOSS-UP5) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice In the oceans, waves and surf currents are generated by:W) windX) El-NinoY) salinity and temperature gradients Z) the Intertropical Convergence ZoneANSWER: W) WINDBONUS5) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What is the name for the common ocean waves that are not driven by the wind but sustained by the energy they obtained by the sea?ANSWER: SWELL(S)TOSS-UP6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer A hexadecimal number is a numeral system with a radix or a base of what?ANSWER: 16BONUS6) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Convert a pressure of 1.2 atmospheres into millimeters mercury:ANSWER: 912(Solution: 1.2 atm × 760 mmHg/1 atm = 912 mmHg) High School Round 3 Page 3
TOSS-UP7) ASTRONOMY Multiple Choice The temperature of a star can be estimated most directly from its:W) distanceX) elemental makeup Y) colorZ) densityANSWER: Y) COLORBONUS7) ASTRONOMY Short Answer The local group is generally referred to as a collection of what celestial objects?ANSWER: GALAXIESTOSS-UP8) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the SI unit of electric charge? ANSWER: COULOMBBONUS8) PHYSICS Short Answer Giving your answer in kilometers per hour per second, what is the average acceleration of a truck traveling on a straight road from 10 kilometers per hour to 50 kilometers per hour in 1 minute and 20 seconds:ANSWER: 0.5(Solution: 40/80 = 0.5 km/hr/sec) High School Round 3 Page 4
TOSS-UP9) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the name for the most malleable and ductile metal which can be dissolved in aqua regia but is unaffected by air and most other reagents?ANSWER: GOLDBONUS9) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the molecular formula for the conjugate acid of the following Brønsted-Lowry base: SO42–ANSWER: HSO4–TOSS-UP10) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the MOST common term for the division of a somatic cell into 2 nucleated cells following of mitosis?ANSWER: CYTOKINESISBONUS10) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the anticodon on a tRNA for AAA (read as: A, A, A)? ANSWER: UUU High School Round 3 Page 5
TOSS-UP11) MATH Short Answer Giving your answer as a proper fraction, what is the cube root of 125 ? 343ANSWER: 7511) MATH Short Answer Find the following product, giving your answer in standard form:(4x3 + x)(7x3 + 4x2)ANSWER: 28x6 + 16x5 + 7x4 + 4x3 (ACCEPT: x3(28x3 + 16x2 + 7x + 4))TOSS-UP12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following cloud types is classified as a low cloud:  BONUS W) altostratusX) cirrostratusY) cumulonimbus Z) nimbostratusANSWER: Z) NIMBOSTRATUS12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Panning is a simple mining technique that is used for extracting gold deposited in:W) banded gold formations X) evaporite depositsY) placer depositsZ) lode depositsANSWER: Y) PLACER DEPOSITSBONUSHigh School Round 3Page 6
TOSS-UP13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer The lush forest of the Pacific northwest is classified as what type of rain forest?ANSWER: TEMPERATE (ACCEPT: TEMPERATE RAIN FOREST)BONUS13) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer The reaction of lead oxide in the presence of what acid is fundamental to the operation of the lead-acid rechargeable battery found in most cars?ANSWER: SULFURIC ACID (ACCEPT: SULFURIC or H2SO4)TOSS-UP14) ASTRONOMY Short Answer The stars Merak and Dubhe in the bowl of the big dipper are most commonly used to locate what star?ANSWER: POLARIS (ACCEPT: POLE STAR; NORTH STAR; ALPHA URSA MINORIS)BONUS14) ASTRONOMY Short Answer The main asteroid belt is located immediately between what two planets?ANSWER: MARS AND JUPITER (in any order) High School Round 3 Page 7
TOSS-UP15) PHYSICS Short Answer What is the most common term used to describe the velocity of an object at any one discrete moment along its path?ANSWER: INSTANTANEOUS VELOCITYBONUS15) PHYSICS Short Answer What lepton was the first to be discovered? ANSWER: ELECTRONTOSS-UP16) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice A beaker of concentrated aqueous ammonia is placed next to a beaker of concentrated aqueous hydrochloric acid at room temperature. After a short while, a white cloud forms between the beakers. This is a demonstration of: W) effusionX) diffusionY) efflorescence Z) effervescenceANSWER: X) DIFFUSIONBONUS16) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice In addition to the “sniff test”, which of the following is a standard laboratory test for a sulfide, such as hydrogen sulfide gas:W) the gas passed over a filter paper soaked in colorless lead nitrate turns the paper brown X) when inserted into a flame, a glowing wooden splint bursts into flamesY) a flame test gives off a deep purple colorZ) paper chromatographyANSWER: W) THE GAS PASSED OVER A FILTER PAPER SOAKED IN COLORLESS LEAD NITRATE TURNS THE PAPER BROWN(Solution: H2S(g) + Pb(NO3)2(aq) )2HNO3 + PbS(s))High School Round 3 Page 8
TOSS-UP17) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following would BEST describe the quaternary structure of collagen:W) fibrous X) globular Y) planar Z) transportANSWER: W) FIBROUSBONUS17) BIOLOGY Multiple Choice Which of the following BEST describes what the term virulence means:W) the specificity of a virus to cause disease in a certain hostX) the ability of a microbe to cause cellular damageY) any transmissible disease caused by a microbeZ) the degree to which a microbe causes disease or harm to its hostANSWER: Z) THE DEGREE TO WHICH A MICROBE CAUSES DISEASE OR HARM TO ITS HOSTTOSS-UP18) MATH Multiple Choice If triangle ABD is congruent with triangle EFG, which of the following MUST be true:W) side AB is congruent to side EFX) side AD is congruent to side FGY) measure of angle B = measure of angle G Z) measure of angle A = measure of angle GANSWER: W) SIDE AB IS CONGRUENT TO SIDE EFBONUS 18) MATH Short Answer Simplify the following rational expression by combining like terms, assuming x is not equal to 4: (x2 −16) (4x − x2 )ANSWER: −x+4 (ACCEPT: x+4 or −(x+4) or −x−4)    x−xxxHigh School Round 3 Page 9
TOSS-UP19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes the luster of quartz:W) dullX) silky Y) metallic Z) vitreousANSWER: Z) VITREOUSBONUS19) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is LEAST accurate regarding earthquakes:W) scientists agree that mega-quakes of magnitude 10 are very likely in the near futureX) the world’s greatest earthquake zone is the circum-Pacific seismic beltY) Alaska has the greatest number of earthquakes in the U.S.Z) deep earthquakes are much less likely to be followed by aftershocks than shallow earthquakesANSWER: W) SCIENTISTS AGREE THAT MEGA-QUAKES OF MAGNITUDE 10 ARE LIKELY IN THE NEAR FUTURETOSS-UP20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Identify the following 3 fabrics as derived from animals or plants, respectively: jute; linen; woolANSWER: JUTE = PLANTS; LINEN = PLANTS; WOOL = ANIMALSBONUS20) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Rounded to the nearest whole degree, what is the obliquity of the ecliptic?ANSWER: 23 (ACCEPT: 24) High School Round 3 Page 10
TOSS-UP21) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What is the proper name for the closest spiral galaxy to the Milky Way?ANSWER: ANDROMEDABONUS21) ASTRONOMY Short Answer What is the common name for the 88 sections into which the International Astronomical Society has divided the sky?ANSWER: CONSTELLATIONSTOSS-UP22) PHYSICS Short Answer In one cycle of alternating current, 180o is given to the point at what fractional amount of the way through the cycle?ANSWER: 1⁄2BONUS22) PHYSICS Short Answer If the speed of sound in a certain medium is 360 meters per second, what is the wavelength, in meters, of a sound-wave that has a frequency of 60 hertz?ANSWER: 6(Solution: wavelength = speed/f; = 360/60 = 6 meters) High School Round 3 Page 11
TOSS-UP23) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is a gas that is tested for by ignition in air on contact with a lighted splint to produce a high-pitched “popping” sound:W) oxygenX) hydrogenY) heliumZ) nitrogen monoxideANSWER: X) HYDROGENBONUS23) CHEMISTRY Short Answer The Lewis dot structure for the N+2 ion would show how many dots? ANSWER: 3TOSS-UP24) BIOLOGY Short Answer What is the scientific term given to the shape of the E. coli bacterium? ANSWER: BACILLUS (ACCEPT: ROD or BACILLI or BACILLIFORM)BONUS24) BIOLOGY Short Answer Name all of the following 4 plants that produce seeds with a fleshy covering that are eaten by animals and dispersed in their droppings: apple; orchid; cherry; sphagnum mossANSWER: APPLE; CHERRY High School Round 3 Page 12
TOSS-UP25) CHEMISTRY Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT an endothermic process:W) sublimation X) meltingY) vaporization Z) condensationANSWER: Z) CONDENSATIONBONUS25) CHEMISTRY Short Answer What is the molarity of a sodium hydroxide solution made by dissolving 4 grams NaOH in 250 milliliters of water?ANSWER: 0.4(Solution: 4.0 g (1 mole / 40 g) = 0.1; 0.1 moles/0.250 L = 0.4 M or moles/L)High School Round 3 Page 13