DOUBLE ELIMINATION ROUND 1 TOSS-UP
1) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What layer of the Sun�s atmosphere is immediately interior to the corona?
ANSWER: THE CHROMOSPHERE
BONUS
1) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer According to the internationally accepted system of scientific units called the SI system, what are the basic units for mass and time?
ANSWER: KILOGRAM AND SECOND
TOSS-UP
2) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The source of energy for the movements of crustal plates is currently thought to be the result of:
W) tidal motion that produces a net westward movement of landmasses X) the pulling apart of the poles resulting from the Earth�s rotation
Y) convection currents produced within the mantle
Z) remnant magnetism
ANSWER: Y) CONVECTION CURRENTS PRODUCED WITHIN THE MANTLE
BONUS
2) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Studies of the atmosphere have recently linked global warming with increases in the height of which layer of the Earth�s atmosphere?
W) Troposphere X) Stratosphere Y) Mesosphere Z) Ionosphere
ANSWER: W) TROPOSPHERE
 Double Elimination 1, Page 1
TOSS-UP
3) MATHEMATICS Short Answer What is the sum of the measures of the exterior angles in a convex polygon?
ANSWER: 360 DEGREES
BONUS
3) MATHEMATICS Short Answer Given a circle of radius 1 how many radians are in the circle?
ANSWER: 2 PI
TOSS-UP
4) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice In mammals, what teeth are evolved primarily to function in gripping and tearing:
 W) incissors X) canines Y) molars Z) wisdom
ANSWER: X) CANINES
BONUS
4) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer How many teeth are found in the normal human adult jaw or mandible?
ANSWER: 16
Double Elimination 1, Page 2
TOSS-UP
5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice To which of the following is the ozone layer of Earth�s upper atmosphere most opaque:
W) Most infrared radiation
X) Most ultraviolet radiation.
Y) Most of the visible light spectrum. Z) Most radio waves.
ANSWER: X) MOST ULTRAVIOLET RADIATION
BONUS
5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer Calculate the density, to the first decimal place, for an object with a mass of 2500 grams that displaces 200 milliliters of water.
ANSWER: 12.5 GRAMS/MILLILITER (ACCEPT 12.5 GRAMS/CM^3)
TOSS-UP
6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What can analog signals do that digital signals cannot do?
W) Carry only discrete values
 X) Transmit binary data
 Y) Transmit information
 Z) Have a continuum of values
 ANSWER: Z) HAVE A CONTINUUM OF VALUES

6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What do scientists call the apparent shift in position of an object when viewed from two different positions?
W) parallax
X) interference Y) subduction Z) occultation
ANSWER: W) PARALLAX


BONUS

TOSS-UP
7) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is one of the principal causes of property damage during earthquakes and occurs when vibrations force groundwater upwards, making the soil lose its cohesion and behave temporarily as a fluid?
W) rifting
X) desedimentation Y) fluidization
Z) liquefaction
ANSWER: Z) LIQUEFACTION
BONUS
7) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Name, in order from the oldest to the most recent, the three major subdivisions of the Phanerozoic Eon.
ANSWER: PALEOZOIC; MESOZOIC; CENOZOIC (must be in order)
TOSS-UP
8) MATHEMATICS Short Answer What are the first 5 prime numbers greater than 1? ANSWER: 2, 3, 5, 7, 11
BONUS
8) MATHEMATICS Short Answer When 6 times a number is decreased by 11, the result is 37. What is the number?
ANSWER: 8
 Double Elimination 1, Page 4
TOSS-UP
9) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true of the plasma membrane:
W) it is made partly of lipids
X) it contains proteins imbedded in the lipid bilayer
Y) it is selectively permeable
Z) it is rigid and helps maintain a definite shape for the cell
ANSWER: Z) IT IS RIGID AND HELPS MAINTAIN A DEFINITE SHAPE FOR THE CELL
BONUS
9) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer It is generally believed that most of the oxygen in the air on Earth today came from what general biological process:
ANSWER: PHOTOSYNTHESIS
TOSS-UP
10) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following best explains why door knobs are located on the edge of the door away from the door�s hinges?
W) To increase the door�s mass X) To increase the door�s inertia Y) To increase the applied torque Z) To decrease the door�s inertia
ANSWER: Y) TO INCREASE THE APPLIED TORQUE
BONUS
10) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer If acceleration because of gravity is 10 meters per second squared, how many meters will an apple fall in three seconds if friction is ignored and it starts from a resting position?
ANSWER: 45
 Double Elimination 1, Page 5
TOSS-UP
11) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the common name for the dinosaur from the Cretaceous Period whose name in Greek means �three horned face�?
ANSWER: TRICERATOPS
BONUS
11) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer In a hydroelectric powerplant, what is the common name for the machine that converts the kinetic energy of falling water into rotary motion?
ANSWER: A TURBINE
TOSS-UP
12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice The densest ocean water is formed during the winter in what region of the Earth?
 W) Norway X) Antarctica Y) Greenland Z) North Pole
ANSWER: X) ANTARCTICA
BONUS
12) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the only ocean current that flows nearly unimpeded around the Earth:
W) the Antarctic Circumpolar Current X) the Gulf Stream
Y) the North Equatorial Current
Z) the South Equatorial Current
ANSWER: W) THE ANTARCTIC CIRCUMPOLAR CURRENT
Double Elimination 1, Page 6
TOSS-UP
13) MATHEMATICS Short Answer If each side of a square is tripled what is the ratio of the area of the enlarged square to the original square?
ANSWER: 9 (Accept "9 to 1", "9:1", or "9 over 1")
BONUS
13) MATHEMATICS Short Answer Eighteen of the 30 students in a class are girls. What percent of the students are boys?
ANSWER: 40%
TOSS-UP
14) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following infectious diseases cannot be cured with current antibiotics:
 W) strep throat
X) toxic shock syndrome Y) scarlet fever
Z) influenza
ANSWER: Z) INFLUENZA
BONUS
14) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a phylum of plants that is characterized by naked or uncovered seeds?
W) Gymnosperms X) Angiosperms Y) Algae
Z) Monocots
ANSWER: W) GYMNOSPERMS
Double Elimination 1, Page 7
TOSS-UP
15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is peculiar in the rotation of the planet Uranus?
W) It is much slower than is typical for Jovian planets
X) It is much faster than is typical for Jovian planets
Y) The equator rotates much faster than the poles
Z) It rotates on its side with its axis is nearly parallel to the plane of its orbit
ANSWER: Z) IT ROTATES ON ITS SIDE WITH ITS AXIS IS NEARLY PARALLEL TO THE PLANE OF ITS ORBIT
BONUS
15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following requires the most energy:
W) Raising the temperature of one gram of water by one degree Celsius
X) Changing one gram of ice from a solid to a liquid
Y) Changing one gram of water from a liquid to a gas
Z) Lowering the temperature of one gram of water by one degree Celsius
ANSWER: Y) CHANGING ONE GRAM OF WATER FROM A LIQUID TO A GAS
TOSS-UP
16) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Sigmund Freud proposed the idea that the subconscious mind existed in three separate divisions two of which he called the ego and the superego. What was the third?
ANSWER: THE ID
BONUS
16) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is the best description of galaxies:
W) clouds of gases around stars X) clusters of billion of stars Y) rare in the universe
Z) always spherical in shape
ANSWER: X) CLUSTERS OF BILLION OF STARS
 Double Elimination 1, Page 8
TOSS-UP
17) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice What do scientists call the current produced when wave water flows rapidly back to the ocean through a break in a sandbar?
W) Rip tide
X) Longshore current Y) Tidal bore
Z) High tide
ANSWER: W) RIP TIDE
BONUS
17) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following best describes a Plesiosaur that lived during the Late Triassic Period?
W) a giant marine reptile
X) a small, lightweight, plant-eating dinosaur Y) a flying reptile
Z) the largest herbivore of the Triassic Period
ANSWER: W) A GIANT MARINE REPTILE
TOSS-UP
18) MATHEMATICS Short Answer The ratio of boys to girls enrolled at Big High School is 2:3. There are 1500 students enrolled. How many are girls?
ANSWER: 1000
BONUS
18) MATHEMATICS Short Answer How many distinct diagonals are contained within a regular octagon?
ANSWER: 20
 Double Elimination 1, Page 9
TOSS-UP
19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice In bean and corn seeds, the food supply that is used by the seed to germinate and grow is in which of the following:
W) cotyledon (PRONOUNCED: KOT-ill-ee-don) X) root tip
Y) abcission zone
Z) petiole
ANSWER: W) COTYLEDON
BONUS
19) BIOLOGY Short Answer What physical condition that has reached alarming proportions in the U.S. population is most closely correlated with type II diabetes?
ANSWER: OBESITY
TOSS-UP
20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following does not ultimately derive its energy to move from the sun?
W) A sail boat
X) A car with a gasoline engine
Y) A marathon runner
Z) A nuclear powered submarine
ANSWER: Z) A NUCLEAR POWERED SUBMARINE
BONUS
20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer If the atomic weight of manganese is 55, how many kilograms of manganese, to the third decimal place will contain two moles of manganese atoms?
ANSWER: .110
 Double Elimination 1, Page 10
TOSS-UP
21) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer In a compound light microscope, what is the most common name of the lens closest to the specimen?
ANSWER: OBJECTIVE
BONUS
21) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Ring, Helix, Dumbbell and Veil are all names of what specific type of heavenly bodies?
ANSWER: NEBULA
TOSS-UP
22) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer The floor of what ocean is expanding in size as a result of sea-floor spreading, tectonic plate movement, and subduction?
ANSWER: ATLANTIC OCEAN
BONUS
22) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Surprisingly more common than rainbows in most parts of the world, what is the name of the optical phenomenon where blobs of light that are often tinged with color appear to the left and/or right of the sun, and are caused by the refraction of sunlight through flat, hexagonal ice crystals?
ANSWER: SUNDOGS (ACCEPT: PARHELIA)
 Double Elimination 1, Page 11
TOSS-UP
23) MATHEMATICS Short Answer Find the y-intercept of the following line: 2x + 3y = 6.
ANSWER: y = 2 (accept 2)
23) MATHEMATICS Short Answer What is the sum of the whole number factors of
20? ANSWER: 42
TOSS-UP
24) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What male reproductive part of a plant produces pollen?
ANSWER: THE ANTHER (ACCEPT: STAMEN)
BONUS
24) LIFE SCIENCE. Short Answer What are the respective scientific names for the three basic shapes of bacteria with the following appearances spherical, rod-shaped and spiral-shaped?
ANSWER: COCCUS BACILLUS SPIRILLUM ( ACCEPT: COCCI, BACCILI and SPIRILLA)
BONUS
 Double Elimination 1, Page 12
TOSS-UP
25) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the name for the procedure which is used to separate molecules of different polarity by placing them on paper and then placing the bottom edge of the paper on in a certain polar or nonpolar solvent?
W) electrophoresis X) titration
Y) chromatography Z) vertical separation
ANSWER: Y) CHROMATOGRAPHY
BONUS
25) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Astronauts in the space shuttle are about 100 miles above the earth's surface. What is true about the effect of gravity on these space shuttle astronauts?
W) The astronauts are far outside the earth's gravitational field
X) The astronauts have some mass, but it is less than their mass would be on the earth's surface
Y) The astronauts experience "apparent weightlessness" because they are constantly falling around the earth
Z) The astronauts have no mass as they are orbiting the earth
ANSWER: Y) The astronauts experience "apparent weightlessness" because they are constantly falling around the earth

