ROUND ROBIN 2 TOSS-UP1) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What plant was brought over from the Americas to Europe in the 1500’s and although was first thought to be poisonous soon became a staple because it had a high yield per acre and could be left un-harvested until needed.ANSWER: POTATOBONUS1) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer Pure gold is how many karats? ANSWER: 24TOSS-UP2) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice In meteorology, what is another name for a region of high pressure? W) Anticyclone X) CycloneY) FrontZ) SquallANSWER: W) ANTICYCLONEBONUS2) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Marble is a metamorphic rock that is often used for buildings and statues. What is the sedimentary rock that marble is commonly derived from?W) Limestone X) MarleY) ShaleZ) SandstoneANSWER: W) LIMESTONETOSS-UP3) MATHEMATICS Short Answer Two angles are supplementary. If one angle measures 60o, what would the other angle measure?ANSWER: 120oBONUS3) MATHEMATICS Short Answer Simplify the ratio of the following factorial: 4! (read as: 4 6!factorial divided by 6 factorial) ANSWER: 1/30 (ACCEPT: 0.033)TOSS-UP4) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following organisms is probably the most commonly studied prokaryote?W) E. coliX) C. elegans Y) M. musculus Z) H. sapiensANSWER: W) E. COLI  BONUS4) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice Most of the wood in a typical 100 year old oak tree is made of which of the following cells?W) cork cells X) phloem Y) epidermis Z) xylemANSWER: Z) XYLEMTOSS-UP5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common scientific term for the chemical reaction in which oxygen combines with a substance or hydrogens are removed from a substance?ANSWER: OXIDATIONBONUS5) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is NOT true?W) for two pots of boiling water the one which is boiling faster has the hottest waterX) the process of condensation is opposite to that of evaporationY) when water changes from a gas to a liquid, energy is releasedZ) absolute zero is the point where all thermal motion stopsANSWER: W) FOR TWO POTS OF BOILING WATER THE ONE WHICH IS BOILING FASTER HAS THE HOTTEST WATERTOSS-UP6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice A severe and chronic deficiency in what vitamin causes the disease known as pellagra:W) vitamin CX) vitamin DY) niacinZ) thiamineANSWER: Y) NIACINBONUS6) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice If a wind turbine with a 1 meter diameter is replaced with a wind turbine 3 meters in diameter, what is the increase in sweep areas for the turbine rotor or blades?W) 3 times X) 5 times Y) 7 times Z) 9 timesANSWER: Z) 9 TIMESTOSS-UP7) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following features is not usually associated with Shield Volcanoes?W) Broad and Gently SlopingX) Made primarily of Highly Fluid Basaltic LavasY) They are commonly considered to be the most explosive and dangerous type of volcano. Z) Fissure eruptions are common on the flanks of these volcanoes.ANSWER: Y) THEY ARE COMMONLY CONSIDERED TO BE THE MOST EXPLOSIVE AND DANGEROUS TYPE OF VOLCANO.BONUS7) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Which Hawaiian God is said to control volcanic eruptions and the direction of lava flows?ANSWER: PELETOSS-UP8) MATHEMATICS Multiple Choice A right triangle with sides of integer length has a ratio of leg lengths of 3:4. What is a possible length of the hypotenuse? W) 7 X) 12 Y) 15 Z) 21ANSWER: Y) 15BONUS8) MATHEMATICS Short Answer Simplify: 5 ÷ 5 ÷ 5 ÷ 15 (read "five divided by five divided by five divided by one fifth").ANSWER: 1 Round 2, Page 4TOSS-UP9) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice The nucleolus is the primary site for the manufacture of which of the following?W) ribosomesX) ProteinY) LipidZ) messenger RNAANSWER: W) RIBOSOMESBONUS9) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice The evolution of flowers in many plants is believed to have depended most directly on the presence and evolution of which of the following:W) insect pollinatorsX) certain predatory carnivores Y) symbiotic plant virusesZ) fungiANSWER: W) INSECT POLLINATORSTOSS-UP10) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Ionic compounds are most commonly formed between what two types of elements?W) Nonmetals and nonmetals X) Metals and metalsY) Metals and nonmetalsZ) Metalloids and nonmetalsANSWER: Y) METALS AND NONMETALSBONUS10) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is a diatomic molecule?W) H20X) methane Y) H2Z) NAClANSWER: Y) H2 Round 2, Page 5TOSS-UP11) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The mass of a new 2002 USA quarter is about how many grams:W) 1.0 X) 2.5 Y) 5.5 Z) 7.0ANSWER: Y) 5.5BONUS11) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer If you have 1 milliliter of a 75% ethanol solution, how much water, in milliliters, must be added to the 1 milliliter to obtain a 25% ethanol solution?ANSWER: 2(Solution: 75%/25% = 3df; 1 part stock + 2 parts water = 3df)TOSS-UP12) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer What wind currents help move the return flow of water in the polar regions to the east?ANSWER: THE WESTERLIESBONUS12) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Order the following four minerals from the hardest to the softest, according to Mohr’s hardness scale: Talc, Calcite, Diamond, Topaz.ANSWER: DIAMOND, TOPAZ, CALCITE, TALCTOSS-UP13) MATHEMATICS Multiple Choice Simplify: (x^8 * x^4)/x^2 (quantity x to the 8th times x to the 4thdivided by x squared)W) x^16 X) x^10Y) x^6 Z) x^4ANSWER: Y) x^6BONUS13) MATHEMATICS Short Answer A recipe calls for flour, sugar and butter to be mixed in a ratio of 7 to 5 to 2, respectively. Assuming there is enough sugar and butter to use all the flour and 20 pounds of flour is available, how many pounds of the mixture can be made?ANSWER: 40TOSS-UP14) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice What is the joint that is formed by the direct interaction of the tibia, fibula, and femur?W) wrist X) knee Y) elbow Z) ankleANSWER: X) KNEE  BONUS14) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer What is the nitrogen-containing base present in RNA that is not present in DNA?ANSWER: URACILTOSS-UP15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice The time required for the Moon to return to the same position relative to the background stars (as seen from Earth) is about how long?W) A day X) A week Y) A month Z) A yearANSWER: Y) A MONTHBONUS15) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer A force that produces an acceleration of 2 meters per second per second when applied to a half-kilogram object is a force of how many Newtons?ANSWER: ONETOSS-UP16) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Methods that cause human hair to have curls usually rely on manipulating which of the following types of hair molecules? W) carbohydrates X) lipidsY) amino acids Z) DNAANSWER: Y) AMINO ACIDSBONUS16) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Rust and smut are plant disease that attack plants such as wheat, rye or corn. Both rust and smut are classified as what type of organisms.W) virusesX) larval insects Y) bacteriaZ) fungiANSWER: Z) FUNGITOSS-UP17) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice What does the prefix “alto” indicate when describing clouds?W) Deep X) High Y) LowZ) ShallowANSWER: X) HIGHBONUS17) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice 70% of all the Fresh Water on Earth is found in:W) The Caspian Sea X) Lake BaikalY) The Great Lakes Z) AntarcticaANSWER: Z) ANTARCTICA TOSS-UP18) MATHEMATICS Multiple Choice Two angles whose sum is a right angle are best described as:W) complementary X) supplementary Y) adjacentZ) correspondingANSWER: W) COMPLEMENTARYBONUS18) MATHEMATICS Short Answer Twelve blue socks and twelve white socks are loose and mixed up in a drawer. If you try to select them in the dark, how many socks do you need to take from the drawer to be sure that you have a matching pair?ANSWER: 3TOSS-UP19) LIFE SCIENCE Multiple Choice The antibiotic penicillin halts bacterial growth by doing which of the following?W) Interfering with the synthesis of the bacterial cell wallX) Interfering with the synthesis of bacterial ribosomesY) Preventing gene transcriptionZ) Preventing attachment of messenger RNA to the ribosomeANSWER: W) INTERFERING WITH THE SYNTHESIS OF THE BACTERIAL CELL WALLBONUS19) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Where is intercellular fluid normally found? ANSWER: OUTSIDE OF CELLS (ACCEPT: IN BETWEEN CELLS OR IN THEINTERSTITIUM)TOSS-UP20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following describes a liquid in which visible particles settle?W) SolutionX) Homogeneous mixture Y) ColloidZ) SuspensionANSWER: Z) SUSPENSION BONUS20) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What aqueous acid primarily results from the production of acid rain?ANSWER: SULFURIC ACID (ACCEPT: H2SO4)Round 2, Page 10TOSS-UP21) GENERAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice If you need to measure 100 milliliters of room temperature water, which of the following would be the most accurate instrument to use:W) 100 milliliter Erlenmeyer flask X) 100 milliliter graduated cylinder Y) 100 milliliter beakerZ) 200 milliliter volumetric flaskANSWER: X) 100 MILLILITER GRADUATED CYLINDERBONUS21) GENERAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common term for the Doppler shift for light from a distant galaxy that is moving away from the Earth?ANSWER: RED SHIFT (ACCEPT: RED SHIFTED)TOSS-UP22) EARTH SCIENCE Multiple Choice Water is released into the atmosphere by plants through a process know as. W) Teleportation X) Transfiguration Y) Transpiration Z) TransportationANSWER: Y) TRANSPIRATIONBONUS22) EARTH SCIENCE Short Answer Limestone is a sedimentary rock often associated with cave formation. What is the name of the weak acid that is primarily responsible for the creation of these caves?ANSWER: CARBONIC (ACCEPT: H2CO3).TOSS-UP23) MATHEMATICS Multiple Choice Simplify: (10^10 )^(−10)  (Read as: parentheses ten to thetenth power close parentheses to the negative tenth power)W) 1020X) 102Y) 10 −100Z) 10 billionANSWER: Y) 10^(−100)BONUS23) MATHEMATICS Short Answer If two consecutive months in a calendar year each have aFriday the 13th, what months would they be?ANSWER: February and MarchTOSS-UP24) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer Silviculture is a branch of agricultural science that is concerned with the development and care of what?ANSWER: FORESTS (ACCEPT: TREES)BONUS24) LIFE SCIENCE Short Answer In a mating between a color blind human male and a normal vision female with a color blind father, what is the percentage chance a son would be color blind?ANSWER: 50%TOSS-UP25) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Short Answer What is the most common term used for sound wave frequencies greater than 20,000 Hertz?ANSWER: ULTRASONICBONUS25) PHYSICAL SCIENCE Multiple Choice Which of the following is not considered a true force?W) gravityX) electromagneticY) centrifugalZ) strong nuclear forceANSWER: Y) CENTRIFUGALRound 2, Page 13